<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO8859-1" ?>
<history>
	<chapter name="the short version" year="1997-2008">
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows was founded as a solo-project in the autumn of 1997 by Niclas Frohagen. After having
			recorded the demo "the silent cry", multi-instrumentalist Micce	Andersson joined the band. Together
			they reinterpreted and polished up the old material and released it as promotion material both on cd
			and online at mp3.com, all with the intention of attracting a record deal. Putting songs on mp3.com
			turned out to be a winning concept and for a couple of weeks forest of shadows dominated the metal
			charts. The english company "rage of achilles" (cult of luna, mistress) had noted this and offered the
			band a record deal. In 2001 the mCD "where dreams turn to dust" was released and soon afterwards the
			work on a full-length album began. During its production, Niclas and Micce started drifting apart, not
			as friends but in terms of musical direction. This resulted in that Niclas finished the album, later
			on titled "departure", on his own. As if the separation wasn't bad enough "rage of achilles" went out
			of business just as the album was finished. The record deal was handed over to finnish label
			"firedoom" who not only released the album but also offered a deal for yet another album. This time
			things went	more smooth and in 2008, after three years of slow progression, the album "six waves of
			woe" was finished.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="foundation" year="1997">
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows was founded in the autumn of 1997 by me Niclas Frohagen. I had been composing music
			for quite some time, starting out with digital productions using tracker programs and slowly moving
			into writing songs for acoustic guitar. Already at this early stage I had a fixed vision of what I 
			really wanted to create but working with samples or strictly acoustic guitar didn't allow me to get 
			there. When I one day bought an electric guitar I didn't even get to learn how to play before I found
			myself composing riffs. The idea of starting a band came directly and I saw myself as the singer/
			guitarist. I found a drummer and bassist quite soon and we started discussing direction and type of
			music. We never really rehearsed. After a while I realised that my new bandmates didn't share my
			vision of the music I wanted to create and to be honest there wasn't much motivation anyway to do
			something with this new constellation. I decided to try and do it all by myself using my compuer as
			an aid where my instrumental skills were lacking.
		</p>
		<p>
			Being high on creativity and a will that saw no	boundaries it didn't take long to accomplish a first
			demo recording. The result was a first version of the song "moments in solitiude". I played this first
			piece for some friends and even though most of them didn't really like it a few ones did and this
			boosted my ego enough to create another song short thereafter, the song "november dream". Music was
			suddenly pouring out of me and all the	ideas I had	been hiding away inside needed to get out. Before
			the end of 1997 I had a demo ready that included, apart from the two mentioned songs, "the silent cry"
			and "under the dying sun". I uploaded these songs to the website I had made for the band and attracted
			a few fans. One of these fans were Stéphane	Peudupin. We later on founded the band Ningizzia.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="evolution" year="1998">
		<p>
			Having recorded some demo songs I felt that I wanted to give the idea of forming a real band another
			chance but instead of focusing on starting a band from scratch the already established "forest of
			shadows" was intended to grow. In the beginning of 1998 Johan Svensson showed interest in the band and
			joined on guitar/bass. We did some jamming and discussed ideas but quite soon, at least I, realised
			that we had quite different aims and ambition. Since I was about to move some month later anyway I
			didn't see much future in the cooperation and thus ended it.
		</p>
		<p>
			Already while Johan was "in the band" I had started to rearrange the old demo recordings in order to
			record them once again. This resulted in the first official demo "the silent cry", which was released
			in may 1998. Even though I had at that time gained some more experience both as a musican and producer
			the demo sounded quite rough but considered the equipment and facilities I had at hand I couldn't have
			done that much better. Still, the melodies and the atmosphere was there and to some extent that is
			what matters. I spread the demo to friends and fans I had gathered on forums and thru my website and
			got quite nice response. 
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="enter micce andersson" year="1998">
		<p>	
			One person who got to hear the demo was Micce Andersson, a friend of a friend who I hadn't been in
			contact with before. He really liked the songs as such but was very open with how bad he thought the
			production was. Still, he offered to change this by joining the band and considering that he was far
			superior at handling most instruments and also had more more experience when it comes to recording I
			was honoured and very positive to the idea of having him in the band. Already at the first occasion
			when we jammed, outdoors on a cliff on the island orust northwest of gothenburg, the intro-riff for
			"eternal autumn" came to life. By then I knew that teaming up Micce was the best thing that could have
			happened to the band.
		</p>
		<p>
			I started hanging around with Micce more and more and apart from just jamming I introduced Micce to
			the music I had as references and he replied by trying to educate me both as guitarist and composer.
			We also started discussing a remake of one of the songs from the demo "the silent cry" to present as a
			sign of the bands evolution and ofcourse to do that song more justice with better execution and
			production.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="hybris" year="1999">
		<p>
			The first song to address turned out to be "the silent cry" which was a good choice due to its
			simpilicty and relative short duration. To spice it up we added a piano interlude and some violin to
			accompany the lead guitar. Some weeks earlier we had contacted Katatonia (a band that served a great
			influence to us at that time especially with their masterpiece "brave murder day") about doing a cover
			of the song "rainroom". We had rather high thoughts about ourselves at that time and one of the
			purposes of doing the cover was that we thought the original song didn't achieve its full potential.
			They approved anyhow and we recored the cover at the same time as the remake of "the silent cry". The
			two songs got unofficially released on a promo called "promotion-cd 1999". The intention of the promo
			was nothing else than to attract attention from labels and in the long term sign a contract.
		</p>
		<p>
			Copies were shipped to most of the record companies we wanted to work with and it didn't take that
			long before we got feedback. Unfortunatelly, most of it said that the material showed potential but
			wasn't good enough for a contract.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="becoming a band" year="1999">
		<p>
			While waiting for that contract that would bring us to the next level we decided to try and expand
			so we could to start with rehearsing as a band and not just two guitarists. There were ofcourse
			visions of doing live performances in the future as well but first we needed to get some extra
			members. Martin Claesson, a classmate of mine from Chalmers, turned out to be interested in joining
			and since I already knew that we shared she same taste in music I thought it was a good brilliant
			idea. As a three-piece we started rehearsing with me on vocals/guitar, Micce on guitar/bass and
			Martin on guitar. Due to the lack of a drummer Micce spent most of the time behind the drums but for
			a few songs at each rehearsals I changed place with him. We rehearsed ofcourse "the silent cry" but
			apart from that it was mostly covers of katatonia and my dying bride.
		</p>
		<p>
			About a month after Martin joined we got in contact with a friend of Micce called Tommy Rydberg who
			was interested in join us as drummer. This was ofcourse more than welcome. The fact that he had a
			double-pedal made us even more satisfied. His background as drummer in a ska band was something we
			tried to ignore totally. We were just so very, very happy to had a drummer. Such fools we were.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="mp3.com" year="2000">
		<p>
			Before the arrival of Martin and Tommy we had started working on a remake of the old song "Under the
			Dying Sun". Even though they joined the band during this process we decided not to involve them. The
			reason? Well, we just didn't see one. We had it all under control and didn't want any kind of
			interference. Most parts of the song were recorded in Micce's apartment apart from the growled vocals
			and some additional guitars which were recorded in our rehearsal place. It all went very smooth and the
			result turned out, as we saw it, much more magical than "the silent cry". It was a magic time indeed
			and there were no limits to how proud we felt about what we had created. The song was later on
			released on yet another promotion-cd and this time we really thought that the labels would pay
			attention to us.
		</p>
		<p>
			Short after we had start spreading copies of the new promotion-cd we discovered the site mp3.com.
			Suddenly we had a chance to reach out to millions with our music without having to manufacture and
			ship a single cd. Ofcourse it kind of kills the beauty to rip a song out of its context being the
			album its was placed but in a perspective of promoting the band worldwide new possibillity was far
			superior than any other alternative we had at hand. To start with we uploaded the remakes of the songs
			"the silent cry" and "under the dying sun".
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="wish" year="2000">
		<p>
			After having rehearsed with Martin a couple of weeks we figured it was about time what we started
			working on a song all of us, as a band. It started with some really nice melodies that I wanted to do
			something with. We had tried them out a couple of times as seperate parts but it was first when Martin
			presented a really nice passage that we tied it all together into something that would later on become
			the song "wish". The cool thing about the passage that Martin had written was that it differed from
			the typical	"forest of shadows" riff at that time which made the song sound very fresh to us. I was so
			into this new song that I wrote som lyrics straight away as well as some additional passages to
			complete it. With "wish" we had created a new direction of our sound, something we ofcourse wanted to
			present with a new demo and all we needed now was a few more new songs of similar style.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="a first performance" year="2000">
		<p>
			On the 17th of February we were to give our first live-performance at the University of Chalmers.
			Since Tommy hadn't shown up much on the rehearsals we couldn't count on him as drums and Micce had to
			replace him temporarily. The setup for the gig was thus me on rythm-guitar and vocals, Martin on
			lead-guitar, Micce on drums and finally a friend of Micce's, Martin Olsson, on bass. We rehearsed a
			couple of times and it all felt really nice. The songs weren't all that technical after all which was
			good since Martin Olsson (our session musician) was the only one who really mastered his instrument.
		</p>
		<p>
			The 17th of february came in bad company with the news of Martin Olsson being injured in an accident.
			For obvious reasons he couldn't do the bass that evening and we had a couple of hours to find a
			replacement, cancel the show or solve it all in some other creative way. I was quite clear about that
			canceling the show wasn't an option no matter if we had or hadn't a bassist. Micce didn't really like
			idea of doing the show without bass and we tried our best to find a replacement. At the time I was
			playing in another band called "shubend" and I phoned our bassist, Martin Pettersson, to see if he
			wanted to help us which he did. He appeared and we rehearsed the songs with him under really poor
			circumstances (most of our equipment were already rigged for the show). It all felt really weird and
			all we could do was to hope for the best or that the sound wasn't good enough to hear that we hadn't
			rehearsed enough. The set for the evening was: "vårvindar friska" (traditional), "the silent cry",
			"wish" and "brave" (katatonia).
		</p>
		<p>
			After the gig we decided to fire Tommy since we realised he lacked both motivation and talent. Micce
			replaced him temporarily as there was a new gig coming up and we didn't think we would find a new
			drummer with such short notice. We were just about to start searching for a session bass-player for
			the gig when Robert Mårtensson showed up and wanted to join the band. He seemed ok and we thought
			that if he didn't fit in the band he could at least do as session bassist for the moment.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="a last performance" year="2000">
		<p>
			Since we had started playing live and rehearsing alot as a band we needed more material both to expand
			our repetuar and to avoid playing the same old songs over and over again. Me and Martin started
			working on some lyrics together which was a great experience since I had previously written everything
			all by myself. While doing this I wrote some music or rather arranged some old ideas with some new 
			ones to accompany the lyrics. It all resulted in the song "of sorrow blue" which was to be performed
			with an additional orchestral prelude on the upcoming gig on the 13th of April.
		</p>
		<p>	
			We were really excited about this second gig but at the same time a little bit nervous about how we
			should accomplish it all since our new bassist hadn't shown up on any rehearsals and most likely
			would stop us from doing a good performance. What we didn't know then was that the audience would 
			consist of mainly friends and people who didn't really like our kind of music so if we did well or
			not wasn't of that great importance. Still, it's never fun to do a gig when the band fails to deliver,
			the sound is horrible and the gear is doing it's best to complete the disaster. It was devestating.
			The songs that had to carry the shame of this disaster was "of sorrow blue", "the silent cry" and
			"wish".
		</p>
		<p>	
			Since Robert was part of the failure we fired him some days after the gig. Somewhere we thought that
			it would help us to move as a live performing band but what we didn't know was that this was the
			beginning of a new direction. We would never perform live again.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="exit martin claesson" year="2000">
		<p>
			We kept struggling to find members to our band and a week after Roberts departure we found a session-
			drummer in Oscar Nathorst of Vinterblod. Unlike Tommy, Oscar was really good and the first time he 
			rehearsed with us we knew that this guy was defintelly capable of doing our material justice. Still, 
			he was just a session member and I never really thought there were any talk of him becoming more than
			that. He simply wasn't one of us and I don't think he wanted to be that either. With Oscar behind the
			drums Micce could return to his bass-duties and it felt like all was going to be fine again. We had a 
			setup that wouldn't fail us.
		</p>
		<p>
			We finished "Eternal Autumn" and started approaching the recording of the a demo. Our songs on mp3.com
			started to climb on the charts and we became more and more reputated. But, even though everything was
			going better than ever a tension started growing in the band. I don't know what started it but one
			idea is that we were becoming more of a band me, Micce and Martin. It just wasn't possible for me to
			keep running it all as my visionary dream since the dream was now ours. This was a change that I
			wasn't ready for and giving up the control and placing it in the hands of the band, the collective
			just wasn't an option for me. It was as if I would put myself in the hands of others. When Martin
			started suggesting new directions and even starting up the band under a different name I knew there
			was no future in our cooperation and thus he had to go. Despite his talents and good ideas the band,
			as it was meant to be, was better of without him.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="where dreams turn to dust" year="2000">
		<p>
			Fed by the increasing success at mp3.com me and Micce decided to start all over again as a studio-band
			and forget about live-performances and rehearsals. We felt that the most important thing at the moment
			was to focus on the recording of the new demo. These recordings took place at the rehearsal place of
			my second band, Shubend, with some additional recordings done in Micce's apartment. The recording
			session lasted during nights and weekends between the 7th of June to 22th of July and was rather
			painless. Our plan was to get signed with these new songs and use them for a mini-CD. Thus, we didn't
			set a release-date for what initially was just a demo. Nothing happened though and the demo became an
			item of promotion instead of reaching the audience. Since we really wanted to reach the audience with
			the new stuff we uploaded the entire demo at mp3.com to be downloaded for free. This later on turned
			out to be a very wise move.
		</p>
		<p>
			The 19th of July the song "Under the Dying Sun" reached the #1 position at the metal-chart at mp3.com
			followed by "The Silent Cry" as #2. Fan-mails started to drop in almost every day now and we started
			to gain great respect from zines and bands. We were mentioned as one of the more important bands on
			the rise in the realms of dark-metal. It felt like all these years of struggle had finally started to
			show some result. And all without having released a proper album!
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="a last attempt" year="2000">
		<p>
			After a period of about two months as studio-band the brothers Fredrik and Richard Johansson contact
			us and wanted to join on guitar and drums respectively. Since we still had a dream about doing a
			decent shows and since we were missing the rehearsals we decided to give it a try. We did a couple of
			rehearsals and the brothers showed really good potential. Still, there was something not right about
			it all. Maybee we didn't like to split the growing success with two new members? Maybee we just didn't
			like to be more than a studio-band? No matter what the cooperation came to end rather quick.
		</p>
		<p>	
			After this last attempt of forming a band at least I lost all of hope of ever trying again. Looking
			back at it this was probably the beginning of the end of the cooperation between me and Micce as well.
			I had really tried to make it work with the brothers but I somehow blamed Micce for the failure and
			started to long for the days where I did it all by myself. The motivation to cooperate was fading.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="signing of a contract" year="2000">
		<p>
			Some weeks later we recived a mail which would change the situation abit. A new record company called
			Molded Skull Productions contacted us and wanted to release our mCD. Since no other label seemed to
			show much interest and since we felt our success at mp3.com and the words from the critics showed that
			we were more than ready to get signed we thought we could give this new company a chance. At the 3rd
			day of October we signed a contract with them. I saw hope in a new beginning.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="rage of achilles" year="2001">
		<p>
			The following weeks kept us occupied with fixing all the details for the release. Still, we found time
			to start writing new material. The contract had given us new motivation and we had started picking up
			some new influences that we want to try and blend with our sound. We even started planning a coming
			full-length after the mCD. 
		</p>
		<p>	
			Just as everything was starting to head in the right direction MSP showed signs of unstabillity. In
			April 2001 MSP wrote and told us that they were having major problems with their pressing-company
			which would delay our release quite alot and they suggested us to try and find a new company since
			they couldn't guarantee the release. We had a contract though and they were actually forced to do
			something about it but since they were honest about the situation and we didn't want the release to
			suffer from the potential problems involved we dropped it all. Another, more valid, reason to drop the
			deal with MSP was that other labels had showed interest. The one that seemed most interested in us was
			english label Rage of Achilles who had signed my other band Shubend some week earlier. Due to their
			great interest in our music and their reliabillity based on a couple of other releases we decided to
			give them a try. On the 16th of June we signed a contract with Rage of Achilles which included apart
			from the mCD an upcoming full-length to be released in 2002.
		</p>
		<p>
			The 29th of October 2001 was the date when we had our first "real" release - the mini-CD "where dreams
			turn to dust". It was well recieved by the press and scored very good for being a debute album. There
			were high expectations of the upcoming full- length and we really felt that this album had to be
			special or else we would become just another band. Even before the release of the mCD we had started
			working on the new material and had very rough versions of all what was to come. After all the full-
			length was scheduled for a early 2002 release.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="motivation lost" year="2002">
		<p>
			Even though we had sketches for the entire full-length ready at an early stage we just could get
			started with the recordings. Time passed and in the spring of 2002 we still hadn't made any progress.
			The situation became frustrating and we turned desperate. At the same time our motivation started
			fading away. Working against a deadline seemed to kill our creativity and we simply couldn't handle
			it. On top of this we had started to disagree about what the album should be like. Forest of Shadows
			became less fun to work with and me and Micce lost focus and didn't meet often enough to keep the
			process alive.
		</p>
		<p>
			Despite all negativity both me and Micce wanted to finish the album since we believed in the material
			and though it would turn out great if we just could get ourselves together do the final recordings. A
			decision was made to give it all one last good try and we started preparing for a recording session
			during the spring/summer of 2002.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="exit micce andersson" year="2002">
		<p>
			My bandmates in Shubend, Martin and Dan, had just built a studio in Gothenburg and me and Micce
			thought	it would be a good place for recording drums. We suddenly felt back on track and ready to
			complete the album. With new hope and motivation we entered the studio and Micce sat down behind the
			drums. It didn't take long though before we entered the dark again. Our equipment did its best to
			make our day in the studio a living hell and we mainly spent the time there cursing and messing around
			with various technical issues instead of doing any recordings. We left the studio with a couple of
			takes that we were far from satisfied with.
		</p>
		<p>
			For a short while we thought we could save the situation by applying our engineering skills and
			extract	something useful from the recordings. Unfortunatelly we didn't succeed and instead we started
			looking for alternative solutions like for instance a new recording session. Time went and all of a
			sudden we had lost focus once again.
		</p>
		<p>
			Some weeks later I was about to move from Gothenburg to Stockholm. It came clear to me that if we
			couldn't make things work while living in the same city it would be even worse now. I started playing
			with the idea of completing the album by myself. Some disagreements later and some failed attempts at
			doing progress that idea suddenly felt like the only solution at hand. Even though the loss of Micce
			would be critical I made the decision to go solo once again.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="back to square one" year="2003">
		<p>
			Since I knew I was about to spend alot of time on my own with the songs I took the opportunity to
			rearrange it the way I wanted it. This did ofcourse take alot of valuable time but I felt that it
			needed to be done in order to gain some motivation. About a year later and after hours and hours of
			hard work trying to record the fundaments for all songs I felt I was onto something. It didn't really
			sound the way I wanted it but I thought some further engineering and mixing would fix that.
		</p>
		<p>
			Hours turned into weeks and weeks into months and how much I tried I never really achieved the result
			I was aiming for. I realised that my ambitions didn't match the material I had combined with my skills
			and equipment to mix it properly. Still, it didn't sound all that bad so I decided to just try and
			finish it al and have it over and done with. After all I had spent quite alot of time with the
			material and it was getting old and I wanted to be able to move on.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="saved in the midst of a disaster" year="2004">
		<p>
			In the beginning of 2004 the album now titled "departure" was finally finished and ready for
			mastering. I was told that it would take some time before this would happen and I took it all with
			ease. I was so happy to have it all off my hands and just wanted it to be released. After a while I
			started to get suspicious and in the summer of 2004 the shocking news reached me that Rage of Achilles
			wouldn't be able to release the album due to financial problems. This was bad. Really, really bad.
			Having managed to complete the album so far despite all problems along the way and having invested so
			much time and energy into it all this just couldn't be the end. It just wasn't fair.
		</p>
		<p>
			In the midst of the disaster Rage of Achilles offered to help me out by finding a new label to
			release "departure". After all they were really good guys with lots of love for the scene and lots of
			contacts with other labels especially thoose who handled their distribution in other countries. One of
			these distributors was the finnish label "Firebox". After some discussion they decided to pay for the
			mastering, which was done at Finnvox by Mika Jussila, and release the album worldwide.
		</p>
		<p>	
			Mastering and pressing went on as planned and on the 29th of October 2004, three years after the
			release of the mini-CD, "departure" was released. I can't describe the relief I felt when I got a copy
			of the album in my hands and was able to look back at it all as a closed chapter.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="departed" year="2005">
		<p>
			The completion of "departure" was not only a great relief, due to the many problems involved in its
			production, but also a chance to move on with the music. Already with "departure" I started moving
			away from the classical sound and blend new elements into the music, elements that would never have
			been accepted when I wasn't the only member in the band. Now, I saw a chance to create something from
			scratch where this new direction could be a more fundamental part of the compositions.
		</p>
		<p>
			My initial plan was to compose a three-song mCD on which I bridged the gap between "departure" and
			wherever I was heading with my new ideas and visions. One of these songs should be a remake of
			"moments in solitude" from the first demo. I really liked that song and wanted to give it better
			destiny than to end up on a poor demo. The remaining songs should be new compositions.
		</p>
		<p>
			In september 2005 I had demo versions of these three songs where the two new ones were still untitled
			but later on would evolve into the songs "selfdestructive" and "detached". I contacted firebox and
			asked them if they were interested in releasing the mCD. Their reply was that I should skip the idea
			of a mCD and instead compose a couple of more songs to fill up a full-length. I didn't like this idea
			since I really believed in the mCD and its purpose of being a bridge between the old and new sound.
			After having thought about it for a couple of days I started accepting firebox proposal and plans for
			a new full-length were made.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="silence" year="2006">
		<p>
			For fans of "forest of shadows" 2006 was a year of silence. Some thought I had put the band on ice or
			even abandoned it completely. Nothing could be more wrong. What was happening was that I started
			arranging the new material and experiment with its sound. I also started working on the lyrics for
			the new songs which turned out to be a great challenge. Just like with the music I wanted to depart
			from the old way of writing and the old rather cliché kind of stories that were told. I wanted to
			write something that was more real and less fictional in order to make the songs more dark than
			gothic. With the new direciton I sure didn't want to leave the darkness behind but rather the
			opposite.
		</p>
	</chapter>
	<chapter name="six waves of woe" year="2007-2008">
		<p>
			After having spent the entire 2006 with writing, composing and arranging the songs for the full-length
			I was now ready to start recording it for real. Since there was so much else happening in my life at
			that time the entire process progressed really, really slow. I did all of the recordings in my
			apartment apart from the screamed vocals which were done in a sauna in our cottage in the countryside.
			Unlike with "departure" no distasters happened along the way the entire production was very pleasant.
			The only negative aspect of it all was the slow progress which at times made me loose focus.
		</p>
		<p>
			In April 2008 the album was ready for the final mixing before sending it all to mastering. Once again
			finnvox were to handle the mastering but this time it was placed into the hands of Minerva Pappi. The
			album is currently scheduled for a release in november 2008.
		</p>
	</chapter>
</history>
