<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO8859-1" ?>
<interviews>
	<item author="RaNa Atef" zine="egyptreviewer.blogspot.com" date="181118">
		<p type="question">
			An influential name in the underground Doom Metal scene, the band manages to establish its unique sound of sorrow, and its grieving, aching rhythms. Mostly of Doom Metal lovers initiated their listening career by listening to "Wish", "Eternal Autumn", "The Silent Cry". And after a 10 year of absence, Forest of Shadows is back with a new strong album "Among the Dormant Watchers". Today, I had the honor to interview this great band, the band who influence me to go deeper into Doom Metal music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Thank you guys for giving me this chance, and to make my dream of chatting with you come true. Firstly, I want to start with the gap between "Six Waves of Woe", and "Among the Dormant Watchers". Where have you been?
		</p>
		<p>
			I actually started working on material for what would become “Among the Dormant Watchers” just after “Six Waves of Woe” was released but the progress was slow. The following years it actually almost came to a stall because of other things like family and work. Then it all took a turn. I updated my gear and returned to the material with the determination that it would become the next full length album, which apparently it did.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is there any concept story behind your latest album?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not really. The instrumental part of the album was composed over a period of many years and each songs has its own backstory and set of influences. The lyrics on the other hand do share some similarities between songs. For instance most of them are inspired by the state of the world and feed on the atrocities and darkness that is out there and the guilt and shame of being a part of it all. Still, not really a concept and nothing that goes for all songs but I guess it’s as close as it gets.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I want to go back to the idea of forming the band, How did you choose the name of the band "Forest of Shadows"
		</p>
		<p>
			I was a big fan of Opeth at the time and they had a song on their first album called “Forest of October”. I guess I liked the title and simply swapped october for shadows to make it a bit more dark and doomy. That’s basically it. Later on I found out that “Forest of Shadows ” was a common name for places in role playing and computer games but that didn’t influence me in picking the name. At that time you didn’t really google the name to see if it was taken.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your main musical influences in general?
		</p>
		<p>
			When I founded the band it was mostly classic doom/death metal but over the years I have moved more in a direction of post rock/metal, black metal and all kinds of dark music that take it to extremes. They all influence in different ways and there isn’t one type of music, or a single band or album that I use as style guide for everything. For lyrics I normally don’t get influenced by other bands lyrics at all but rather use books or, as mentioned earlier, the state of the world, normally as told by various documentaries.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			"Six Waves of Woe" is one of the greatest Doom Metal releases ever! Specially "Selfdestructive", please tell us more about this album and the process of writing it
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanks! I also find “Selfdestructive” one of the best song on that album. So, while “Departure” was the first album I did all by myself, or at least completed by myself, “Six Waves of Woe” was the album where I learnt from my mistakes and perfected my visions, or at least took it all to the next level. There was more confidence which resulted in more focus on composing and recording and less on tweaking the sound and editing recordings. I also knew from day one how it all should sound and used the same references during the entire production. In terms of lyrics I started to move away from the classic doom metal thematics, something that has continued on “Among the Dormant Watchers”. Instead I found new inspiration in real life events and the true darkness that is out there instead of over dramatic novels and poetry.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why does the musician drive his inner feelings into sad, gloomy music?
		</p>
		<p>
			Catharsis I guess. You need a way to ventilate your inner darkness and for me it has always been through listening and composing dark music. Somehow those feelings give the songs an extra dimension and more meaning. It makes each and every song personal and something I can relate to.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is there any live performances soon?
		</p>
		<p>
			No. Previous to “Where Dreams turn to Dust” we did two shows and that was during a time when there was a “we” in the band. It was fun but it never did the songs justice. I sometimes play with the idea of doing some live shows with guest musicians but I’m quite confident it will never happen. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you think of your Middle Eastern fans? Are you on contact with them?
		</p>
		<p>
			They write and I answer, just like fans from other parts of the world. I really don’t care too much where my fans come from. Still, for some mysterious reason the majority of my fans do seem to come from the Middle East and I still struggle to get why? So, maybe I should pay those fans some extra attention.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the most difficulties that face underground Metal bands?
		</p>
		<p>
			As of today, acting in Sweden there isn’t really any difficulties. I guess the fact that there is so much music out there could be an issue as it makes it harder for your own stuff to be relevant if you haven’t picked a very unique style. I am perfectly aware of that the situation is different in other countries, especially some of the less free countries in the middle east.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you the see Doom Metal scene now?
		</p>
		<p>
			Quite diverged. There are so many different styles and directions where some share very little so for me it’s not that relevant to talk about the Doom Metal scene at all. I’m not even sure if my own music classify as Doom Metal anymore. I quite often find music that is doomy sorted under Black Metal or Post Rock/Metal and when I browse the stuff sorted as Doom I quite often get disappointed.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your plans, and dreams you want to fulfill? 
		</p>
		<p>
			For music, to keep making relevant music and to continue to perfect the visions I have for Forest of Shadows. Being a DIY artist there is always room for improvement.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Aleksey Evdokimov" zine="doom-metal.com" date="181031">
		<p type="question">
			Hail Niclas! Actually I didn’t expect any news from Forest Of Shadows for years, so I’m surprised with news that your third album Among The Dormant Watchers is about to release through Inverse Records. What did make you return to Forest after ten years of silence?
		</p>
		<p>
			I actually never left the forest, I just got lost in there for a while. The main reason why I awoke was probably because I was iterating on the songs that would later on end up on “Among the Dormant Watchers” in a very, very slow pace during the first five years and it felt that I wasn’t getting anywhere while I still felt that the songs had great potential. So, I upgraded my recording gear and simply started working more focused with a determination that the songs should end up on some album. During this time Firebox went out of business so during a period there wasn’t really a label to release the album but I ignored that and focused on the music. After some struggle with other labels that showed interest but didn’t deliver, Inverse Records showed up as the saviour and offered to release the album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your first full-length Departure was released in 2004, then Six Waves Of Woe appeared in 2008, but then you suddenly stop, was it a kind of creative crisis or something else?
		</p>
		<p>
			Family and work took all focus for a couple of years and even though I never really gave up on my music I simply wasn’t giving it much attention. The creativity was there all the time but the time and energy to channel it into my music simply wasn’t.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Six Waves Of Woe continues the theme of debut album, so what about Among The Dormant Watchers? Could it be a strict successor of Six Waves after all these years? How much of old Forest Of Shadows left in new material?
		</p>
		<p>
			There is much similarity between the two albums but I do explore some new territory on the new album. Regarding old material there is actually one song, I won’t say which, that goes back to times before Forest of Shadows. It has been reworked quite a lot though but if you knew the original song you would recognize the melody. The rest of the songs were all done after Six Waves of Woe although I tried to perfect things I started off on that album. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How actually long did you work over these songs? Was it a fast process as a sudden wave of inspiration or did you take your time and work without hurry?
		</p>
		<p>
			They were worked on for almost ten years but as mentioned, during some of these years I didn’t focus too much on making music so effectively maybe five years. I did not hurry. The only thing that was done pretty fast was the lyrics and vocals, at least in relation to the rest.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What kind of topics do you explore in your new songs? Is it general Forest Of Shadows idea the same?
		</p>
		<p>
			I try to move away from cliche thematics and find topics that are not just overdramatized romantic nonsense but real darkness and pain. It makes it all feel so much more relevant and authentic and gives the songs much more depth and meaning.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Probably, I wouldn’t ask you previous question, but there’s a songs titled ‘Dogs Of Chernobyl’… What’s it about? Actually I have a guess… I remember you did work in PC games industry, so I can suppose that the song is connected with S.T.A.L.K.E.R. video game…
		</p>
		<p>
			I do work in the game development industry but the kind of games I work on are not in any way related to my music. The songs is actually inspired by stories told in the book Voices from Chernobyl by nobel prize winner Svetlana Aleksijevitj. It’s one of the most tragic books I have read and there is an episode about the dogs that were abandoned by their owners during the catastrophe and their tragic demise.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Once you recorded a version of Swedish traditional song, do you have something similar this time?
		</p>
		<p>
			We did play a Swedish traditional song during one of the two gigs we did when the band was not a solo act but we never recorded that one or any other traditional song. Still, some of the songs of Forest of Shadows, especially on the new album, are heavily inspired, at least in terms of melody, by swedish folk music. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Forest Of Shadows always was your solo project, did something change this time? Did someone else help you at the studio?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not always, during When Dreams Turn To Dust and its previous two demos I was running the band with Micce Andersson and during a short period there were other members as well. I guess there were times when the other members saw it all as my one man show as I’m not the best at compromising and it was doomed to end up as a one man show in the end. Everything on the new album was done by me apart from mastering. It’s not the smartest way to do it but at least it gives me full control and allows the music to be as true to my visions as possibly can.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Niclas, where did you record Among The Dormant Watchers? As I understand first records were done in your home studio, so what’s now? And what kind of equipment did you use for this recording?
		</p>
		<p>
			Just like before, nothing has been recorded in a proper studio but instead at random locations. Apart from instruments and microphones I have a mobile studio consisting of a laptop and an external sound card which allows me to record basically anywhere. For instance, I try to record most vocals where I don’t need to care about irritating my neighbors. The rest I do at home, in the living room, at the dinner table, in the basement, wherever it works and wherever I can gets things done. I have been doing this for such a long time that I can record really depressing music while the kids are playing all around me. That being said I don’t get inspired to write depressing music by kids having a good time but once I have the inspiration and the music in my head it doesn’t really matter if I record it all during nighttime in a desolate forest or in suburbia during daytime.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You also did run project Ningizzia, is it still on hold or did you finally put it to rest?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yes, me and Stephane Peudupin used run that band. It was very much of a project or even experiment considering that we did it all over the net during times when internet wasn’t really what internet is today. We haven’t really put it rest for the simple reason that it wasn’t really a band in the classical meaning but more of a collaboration and as I said project or experiment. We still keep contact and we might record something someday or maybe we don’t. I think we both want to do something but none of us have enough time to spend, at least not right now.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item zine="Kronos Mortus Metal Webzine" date="081201">
		<p type="question">
			Tenebra! I am glad to make an interview with you, i like very dark and doom music like yours. Can you
			tell us about your past, to let us know something about you?
		</p>
		<p>
			I founded Forest of Shadows as a solo-project in the autumn of 1997. After having recorded the demo
			"the silent cry" I teamed up with multi-instrumentalist Micce Andersson. We reinterpreted and polished
			up the old material and released it as promotion material both on cd and online at mp3.com, all with
			the intention of attracting a record deal. Putting songs on mp3.com turned out to be a winning concept
			and for a couple of weeks we dominated the metal charts there. The english company "rage of achilles"
			(cult of luna, mistress) had noted this and offered us a record deal. In 2001 the mCD "where dreams
			turn to dust" was released and soon afterwards the work on a full-length album began. During its
			production, me and Micce started drifting apart, not as friends but in terms of musical direction.
			This resulted in that I had to finish the album, later on titled "departure", on my own. As if the
			separation wasn't bad enough "rage of achilles" went out of business just as the album was finished.
			The record deal was instead handed over to finnish label "firedoom" who not only released the album
			but also offered a deal for yet another album. This time things went more smooth and in 2008, after
			three years of slow progression, the album "six waves of woe" was finished. And that brings us up to
			now.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Six Waves Of Woe was released at the end of october. You have started to write the songs years
			earlier, as i know. You spent a lot of time and energie on writing. Was it your goal to create your
			life's biggest masterpiece?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not really. Ofcourse I wanted to top "Departure" and perfect my formula but I wasn't aiming for the
			biggest masterpiece of my life. I don't think I'll ever have that aim. It's also important to know
			that during those three days I far from worked with the album on a daily basis. My work and social
			life doesn't really allow that. If I were to make the masterpiece of my life I would need to put
			myself in a situation where I could focus 100% on my music. Maybee I'll do that one day. Most likely
			not.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Darkness, melancholy, sadness, and void. Your music has it all. Please tell us something about each
			songs!
		</p>
		<p>
			I assume you mean each song on "Six Waves of Woe". Here we go. First there is "Submission", a rather
			short song in terms of lyrics. It's a song about waking up in a relationship where pretty much
			everything has gone wrong and where the victim can see no other solution than to submit to the brutal
			reign of it's master no matter how dark and destructive that destiny may be. It's unfortunatelly a
			rather common tragedy that has been around for ages and doesn't really seem to vanish. The next song
			is "Selfdestructive" which is about trying to save your loved one out of the same destructive pattern
			that almost destroyed you once. It's a song about the desperation you feel when the end is closing in
			with it's suffocating darkness. The third song "Detached" can be interpreted as "Selfdestructive" but
			seen in the eyes of the other part, that is one falling into the dark. While "Selfdestructive"
			actually has some hope and some kind of "lets work this out" attitude "Detached" is all about
			selfpity, losing hope and fading away. Next song, "Moments in Solitude", moves away from the
			relationship theme and is more egocentric. It's actually a really old song from the first demo that
			has been reworked. The story here is about being suffocated by a reality you don't seem compatible
			with and neither want nor can understand. In short terms it's a song about a misanthropic hermit. The
			fifth song, "Pernicous", is about being poisoned by dreadful experiences and how these can be
			powerfull enough to drag you down into a life of complete darkness. It's also about the desperate
			attempts to reach out for light even though it's of no use. To some extent the lyrics were inspired by
			the stories told by people surviving brutal massacres or being witnesses of such. Finally, the last
			song "Deprived" is about falling victim to promises of everlasting bliss that instead turn out to be
			delusive tricks to capture and encage. It can be seen as both falling victim to religious beliefs or
			sects and being mislead into a depriving relationship.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who helped you in the writing process? You don't have full-time members in your band, is it
			intentional?
		</p>
		<p>
			Everything on the album apart from the final mastering was done by me. Doing everything by yourself
			has ofcourse it's pros and cons but that I do it that way is intentional and I have no plans of
			getting any help.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			There's a Forest Of Shadows track on the Katatonia Tribute album. I think that there's some
			similarities between your and Katatonia'a music. What do you think about it, what are the main
			differences and similarities of your music compared to Katatonia?
		</p>
		<p>
			At the time when we did the "Rainroom" cover we were very inspired by Katatonia and especially their
			minimalistic style. I would definatelly say that there are more differences than similarities. If
			there are similarities it's probably the minimalistic and repeatative structure of the songs and the
			use of rather simplistic pumping riffs. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Four years passed since the release of "Departure", which was an awesome record. How succesful was
			that record? How much succesc do you expect from the new release? By the way, do you even care about
			the success?
		</p>
		<p>
			It was succesfull enough to sell all copies of the album and it gained quite good critics. Still, it
			wasn't succesfull enough to attract a major deal or a second pressing. No matter what I'm quite
			pleased with the album just as I am with "Six Waves of Woe". I have no idea if the new album will be a
			greater success or not and to be honest such things are more or less impossible to know. To me it's a
			better album in many ways and it should be more attractive for a wider audience but at the same time
			that might make it a less interesting. What do I know? To answer your final question I do care about
			success, not in a way that I'm aiming for a career but rather to reach out to as many as possible with
			my music. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The front cover of the CD is brilliant. We have already seen some similar type of front covers, but
			this one is so special. What do you think about it?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm very satisified with it and I would definatelly consider it the best one so far. You are right
			about it not being all that original but still there is as you say something that makes it a bit
			special and I think it fits the title of the album very well.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Firedoom Music is not a major record label, but it seems like they really do anything for their bands.
			Are you satisfied with them?
		</p>
		<p>
			Very. I think it's a perfect label for a band such as "Forest of Shadows" that need to work under
			total freedom and not expect to release albums every year.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Will you ever play live? Do you want to spread this special melancholic atmosphere in a live show?
		</p>
		<p>
			When we still were a band we did a couple of shows but they didn't motivate us enough to carry on with
			that. At the present there isn't even a band since I'm the only member so there is very little that
			points at any kind of possibillity for future live shows. It would be fun though but I'm not sure it
			would be worth the price it would cost with all preparations and all. Also, "Forest of Shadows" is a
			small band and it would be quite hard to attract any bigger audiences whih as I see it is a must if I
			were to even think about doing any gigs.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I think that a lot of people will like the new album. I wish you the best in the future!
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanks.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="David E. Gehlke" zine="Metal Maniacs" date="081127">
		<p type="question">
			You've been doing Forest of Shadows for over a decade now. Did you imagine when you started you'd be doing
			this for such a long period of time?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't think I reflected much about the future at all when I started the band. It was too much of a project
			back then and I couldn't even see myself releasing a proper album or having a fanbase. I had dreams ofcourse
			but I didn't find them very realistic and I enjoyed what I had without aiming for the stars. Even though
			Forest of Shadows is still a quite small and obscure band it has by far fullfilled the visions and dreams I
			had a decade ago.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You personally, how have you developed from the first demo?
		</p>
		<p>
			On a personal level I have changed quite alot and I'm far from the person I was back then. When you grow
			older you hear, feel, see and experience more. Altogether you gain a wider perspective on things and I guess
			that's what you might define as maturing. Musically this means that my expression includes more than what it
			did ten years ago. I have learnt that good music is more than sticking to restricting formulas and ideas. I
			have also learnt that looking back at your roots and staying in contact with them can be essential for the
			music and it's soul.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Have you become more self-aware as time has gone on? I say that because each successive FoS album
			brings forth new elements of maturity and insight.
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, I like to listen to criticism no matter if it's from friends or professionalls. It can be hard
			to accept what people say at times but in the end it's essential for the progression of the music.
			Still, I wouldn't say that I streamline my music to suit other peoples taste or ideas. I just pick up
			what I hear people say that makes sense and try to do somehting about it. This skill or whatever is
			something I have gained with the years and in the beginning I wasn't as opened to critics. I had my
			masterplan and nothing could change it.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You experienced some label difficulties early in your career with Rage of Achilles going under, so how
			has your relationship with Firebox/Firedoom worked out?
		</p>
		<p>
			It has worked out very well. I liked working with Rage of Achilles just as I do with Firebox/Firedoom
			but they weren't as professional. Even though I don't make music for a living I appreciate if the
			label give the band the attention it deserves and do everything in its power to market the music.
			This, total freedom and much more is what I get from Firebox/Firedoom and I'm very happy about it all.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			To you, what does Six Waves of Woe represent?
		</p>
		<p>
			Basically, six dark and depressive songs. It's not a concept album and there's no theme that runs thru
			all songs. The title only represent the least common divisor of the albums six songs. As with most
			other songs I have composed this would be the elements of sorrow, losing hope and despair. When I was
			thinking about putting this unification into words I had an idea of using the sea as a metaphore. I
			don't know why but for me the sea has always had some kind of dark aura especially the cold, wretched
			sea we have here up in the north. To make each song a wave that crush down on life with its cold, dark
			woe felt quite powerfull. I guess that sums it all up.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The cover image is striking. Is this something you shot yourself? What does it represent?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's a picture I have taken with my crappy camera and it portraits the landscape where I grew up. It's
			a view I have seen a million times that bring to life alot of old memories both good and bad. What I
			wanted to illustrate with the picture is the cold, dark and desolate aura of the sea, that is the one
			the title is focused around. I would love to have a motivation for the dead tree that really completes
			the picture but I have none apart from that it looked good. Maybee the dead tree was subconciously
			needed to stick to the formula since there's always trees present on my albums.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Does it all tie into your view of nature and if so, what are some of the key points of the story?
		</p>
		<p>
			Nature is complex. The same view can tell a thousand stories as with the view portraited on the album
			cover. I guess my view of nature is that it's a silent watcher. A comforter for your mental state. At
			least I find comfort when I move around in nature. I can think of no better way to illustrate feelings
			than by using pictures of nature since thoose pictures will tell a different story to each viewer just
			as the interpretations of the music and lyrics do.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You worked on the album for over three years - was it difficult to get everything together?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't find it difficult to get it all together. At least not musically. The big challenge for me is
			the lyrics. I don't want them to be romantic nonsense filled with empty phrases. It's ofcourse hard to
			know if lyrics are nonsense or not but to me and my relation to the songs it's important that they
			have a true meaning and some substance. Another challenge is to know your limitations and to know when
			the songs won't get any better. I want to do the songs as much justice as possible but my skills both
			when it comes to instrumentation and recording can be restricting.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the benefits of working alone? Drawbacks?
		</p>
		<p>
			The benefits are total freedom both artisitically and when it comes to when I want to work or not. The
			drawbacks are your own limitations as composer/musican/producer. When I worked with Micce I could
			always rely on his skills and that he would say if something was good or not. Now, I have to be my own
			judge which can be hard especially if you are a perfectionsit as I am.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			In relation to Departure, where does this album rank? Better? More personal?
		</p>
		<p>
			I like to belive that every album I produce is a better version of its predecessor but I'm quite aware
			of that the reality is quite different. If I were to redo "Departure" as a successor to "Six Waves of
			Woe" it might have turned out as the better one but as I see it today it's not. Maybee for the simple
			reason that the sound of "Six Waves of Woe" is more up-to-date with what I like today. Maybee in ten
			years I won't think the same. Still, I would definatelly say that it's a more personal album though
			simply because it's done entirely by me. "Departure" was colored by the cooperation with Micce and as
			such it was not as much a personal piece of work.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The new album appears to be a bit more dark than Departure and your vocals are more dreary than ever.
			Was that the intended the goal? Something like "Selfdestructive" instantly comes to mind.
		</p>
		<p>
			Ofcourse. My goal with "Forest of Shadows" is to make music that is dark and dreary and the more I
			learn how to express this, the closer I will get to my goal. Also, by making the songs more personal
			it's easier to express true emotions and true emotions are hard to compete with.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I'm really intrigued by "Moments in Solitude" both lyrically and sonically. What's the story behind
			this one?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's based on a very old song, actually the first full song I ever wrote for "Forest of Shadows". Due
			to its age the melodies and the way the song is arranged is quite close to the original formula.
			Spiced up with news ways of thinking the result is quite different from any other song on the album. I
			kind of like it since it links to the roots of the band and makes it evident that the original formula
			still works. Lyrically it's a song about a hopeless attempt to escape a depressive reality in which I
			didn't want to belong. To some extent it's a song about being naive. It can also be seen as a song
			about being your own in your own world. An ode to the misanthropic hermit.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is the Niclas in Forest of Shadows anything like the Niclas outside of the band?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, I claim that the music is personal so there must be some kind of resemblance. I think the big
			difference is that I don't express what I do with music in life, that is I don't look lie a suicidal
			black hole. It would be hard to pinpoint me as the person behind the band in a crowd of people. You
			would probably also find it hard to link me with my music if you spoke to me in private since I'm a
			bit more positive and, well, "oridinary". The Niclas in Forest of Shadows is a mental state I keep for
			myself and the music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you do a good job of separating life from art?
		</p>
		<p>
			To some extent I don't want to seperate them totally simply because art is such a big part of my life.
			I don't want to live a life in denial. Still, I can't live the life I portrait in my music since that
			would be devastating. I guess a perfect blend is what I aim for.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where do you think the appeal lies with such dark, harrowing music?
		</p>
		<p>
			Catharasis maybee. To make music that is based on negative things in life is quite close to going in
			therapy. Since most people need that every now and then it's quite appealing to have some kind of tool
			for fixing your own problems by yourself. Ofcourse I know that it doesn't work all the time but it's
			still some kind of comfort to have a ventilation for your inner feelings.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Finally, what are your plans going into 2009?
		</p>
		<p>
			I think I will take a break and gain some distance in order to find new motivation for a new album.
			Since I work under total freedom and since I want to work that way I can't really say when I will
			start working on new songs. Maybe tomorrow, maybe in two years. All know is that there will be new
			songs.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Sebastien" zine="Pavillon 666" date="050324">
		<p type="question">
			Hello forest of shadows! What is your actually line up and where do you come from?
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows come from Stockholm, Sweden and is at the moment a one-man band consisting of me,
			Niclas Frohagen.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your last album "departure" is a beautiful piece of metal, what are your influences?
		</p>
		<p>
			Since the album was developed under a rather long period of four years alot influences came and went
			while others remained. The most important ones would probably be Katatonia, Rapture, Shape of Despair,
			Cult of Luna, Anekdoten, Massive Attack and Opeth.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How did the recording occur? Are you satisfies by it? Have you got echoes about the album?
		</p>
		<p>
			The recording was very problematic. It started out as an album by me and Micce but we soon ran out of
			motivation since we had different visions about what it all should sound like. After a while I came to
			the conclusion that the only way to get it all done without causing a major catastophe was to do it all
			by myself. When Micce left I had to start all over since he had been in charge of both the recording and
			the instrumentation. It was quite a journey and I can't say I liked it all the time but it finally came
			to an end and considering the consequences I must say I'm pretty satisfied with the result. And it seems
			like the media thinks the same since most reviews have very positive. It even got full score in some
			zines and was rated album of the year.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			About this album, what is the concept behind the music?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm sorry if I break the illusion but there isn't really a concept behind it. It's a collection of rather
			depressive songs that happened to end up as at least lyrically pretty similar. Ofcourse I did my best to
			unify the songs production-wise since I quite like such albums but as I said they weren't composed to fit
			some concept.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which are your projects to come (after all promos of this record)? Envisaged live-shows in France or
			Europe?
		</p>
		<p>
			Since I'm the only member of the band live-shows are pretty much out of the question. Instead I will
			focus on the upcoming album whatever that will be. I have alot of ideas and rough versions of songs that
			I really want to work with.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			If you have a message to make pass to your metal fans, it is to you!
		</p>
		<p>
			Check out "departure" if you're into dark and depressive music and stay updated with
			www.forestofshadows.com if you want to know more about the upcoming album...
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Christopher McGuirk" zine="Music with Rocks In" date="050322">
		<p>
			It's nice to be introduced to truly refreshing Doom Metal every now and then; Niclas Frohagen is
			particularly good at that. His solo project, Forest of Shadows, now has a new album out and a comfortable
			deal with a Finnish label that has been an impressive addition to the metal scene for quite some time. In
			order to get an insight into one of Doom's brightest stars, I bit the bullet and asked if he'd care to
			give MWRI an interview. He agreed to do it, so sit back and enjoy an interview with one of alternative
			music's most eclectic stars.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			First of all, congratulations on the simply superb 'Departure' LP. Do you feel the album has been warmly
			received?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, most of the critics has been very positive.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I notice that you play all the instruments on the LP. What prompted the decision to be a one-man band?
		</p>
		<p>
			The last year of my cooperation with Micce Andersson wasn't all that positive and I really felt that we
			were drifting apart musically. As I saw it we would go seperate ways sooner or later and the idea of
			turning the band into a one-man band started spinning in my mind. When I moved from Gothenburg to
			Stockholm in the middle of the production of "departure" I realized that there was no chance that we
			would manage to pull it through together with both the distance and the lack of motivation. I thought
			that the best thing for both of us would be to split up.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Finland has proven to be a hotbed of talent these past few years. Do you feel Finnish metal is about to
			finally rise to prominence on the world stage?
		</p>
		<p>
			Some Finnish bands are already in my humble opinion among the best in the world in their genre and
			there's alot of new fresh bands that most likely will go as far. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your latest album is an exquisite piece of Melodic Doom metal. Have you always been a fan of this genre,
			or do you feel your music has developed over time to incorporate this style?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, since the first time I heard a band of this genre I have been quite addicted to it. There's so much
			more that has influenced me though so to answer your question I would say that the style has been
			developed over time. I actually started composing long before I knew about doom metal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which bands would you cite as your biggest influences, and why?
		</p>
		<p>
			That's a difficult question. If we are looking at Forest of Shadows from the day the band was founded
			until today I would say Opeth, Katatonia, My Dying Bride, Anathema, Shape of Despair and Cult of Luna.
			Opeth inspire me with their epic and beautifull melodies and arrangements, Katatonia with their simple
			and powerfull riffs, My Dying Bride with their dark atmosphere, Anathema with their emotional songs,
			Shape of Despair with the slow, monotonous and haunting sound and finally Cult of Luna with their fresh
			brew of hardcore and doom.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Are you friendly with other bands on the Firedoom label? Have you found your time spent with them?
		</p>
		<p>
			I haven't had any contact with any of them. It would have been fun to get to know some of them but I'm
			too lazy to take the innitiative.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have plans to form a live band and tour? If so, would you consider playing in the UK for some
			dates?
		</p>
		<p>
			There's no plans of putting together a live-act. We tried that once and it wasn't very successfull. I
			guess the songs are better suited for a home environment than the local rock club. It would be very cool
			to play the songs live some day with a proper line-up and at a proper place but it's more of a dream than
			something I plan. If it would happen then I'm pretty sure we would come to the UK.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			If you could describe your sound in 5 words, how would you do it?
		</p>
		<p>
			Depressive, dark, monotone, slow and epic.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Finally, how do you intend to follow up 'Departure'? Can we expect more of the same, or are you thinking
			of changing direction?
		</p>
		<p>
			There will hopefully be something new about it but basically it will probaly be pretty much the same. It
			might be more electronic or more old-school. Who knows? I'll just do whatever sounds good and feels
			right. As long as it's dark and depressive I don't feel that I have let anyone down...
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Karl Haikara" zine="tmetal.com" date="050320">
		<p type="question">
			How's it going for the band?			
		</p>
		<p>
			It's going just fine. Well, there's actually not much happening right now with the band apart from some
			maintenance of the website. I'm giving it all a little break since the production of "departure" was so
			very intense and I really need to grow some distance in order to be motivated for the new material.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Give us a short history of the band, and tell us who is in it.
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows was founded in 1997 by me, Niclas Frohagen and was initially a solo-project. After the
			release of the first demo "The Silent Cry" in 1998 multi-instrumentalist Micce Andersson joined the band.
			Together we recorded two demos: "promotion-cd 1999" and "promotion-cd 2000" before Martin Claesson joined
			on guitar and the band switched from being a studio band to a live-performing act. In the summer of 2000
			after two less successfull gigs with four different session/fulltime-members coming and going we dropped
			Martin Claesson and went back to being a studio band. The demo/mcd "where dreams turn to dust" was
			recorded and shipped out to different labels where "Molded Skull" was the first one to show interest and
			also signed us with a first release being the mcd. Unfortunatelly "Molded Skull" ended up with financial
			problems and instead "Rage of Achilles" showed up and took over the release. In October 2001, one and a
			half year after it had been recorded, the mcd was released. It was well received by the media and the
			expectations of the upcoming full-length were high. The creation of this full-length (departure) would
			turn out to be one long and painfull journey with Micce leaving the band and Rage of Achilles ending up
			in financial problems. About four years after the creation of the album was initialized it finally got
			released thru Firedoom/Firebox.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Any news you want to announce to your fans?
		</p>
		<p>
			Right now there are no official news to share with the audience. In a couple of months there will surely
			be some though so keep updated with the website.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who are your main influences musically?
		</p>
		<p>
			Right now, the bands that influence me most are: Cult of Luna, Isis, Anekdoten, Antimatter, Anathema (The
			Silent Enigma and Eternity), Katatonia (new stuff), Shape of despair and The Funeral Orchestra.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What influences the lyrics?
		</p>
		<p>
			Poetry, films, other bands lyrics and personal experiences.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What mood or feeling do you wish to impart upon the listener?
		</p>
		<p>
			A rather dark, desperate and dismal one :) There are so many happy and positive bands out there that I
			see it as my quest to be their negation. Not even the bands that claim to be dark and depressive live up
			to it. I guess many bands see it as pretentious and overdone but I don't. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you think you fit the "Doom Metal" title, or how would you describe your music to some body who hasn't
			heard it?
		</p>
		<p>
			There are doomy elements in the music but it wouldn't be fair to label it as doom-metal. I feel quite
			satisifed by labeling it as just dark music. I mean some parts aren't even metal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			(for the guitarist(s), bassist and drummer) What gear do you use?
		</p>
		<p>
			Fender hearffield guitar, vester acoustic guitar, washburn XB-100 bass, marshall valvestate amp,
			behringer v-amp, levin 12-string mandolin, august hoffman piano, african djembe, shure microphones and
			lots of samples.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How does the band write the songs?
		</p>
		<p>
			At the moment I write all the material. Even when there were other members involved I wrote most of the
			stuff. I'm not very democratic when it comes to music and a true control freak which makes me rather hard
			to work with.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you listen to, as in, if I were to look into your cd collection what would I see?
		</p>
		<p>
			Mostly metal but also some progressive rock, trip-hop, classical, darkwave and pop. I have a rather huge
			collection so there's most likely something for everyone especially if you like dark music or metal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you think of the following styles: A) Doom Metal, B) Black metal, C) Gothic Metal, D) Death Metal
			(both melodic and otherwise) and E) Power Metal
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm not that obsessed by the actuall styles. I could name alot of bands in all these style that I really
			don't like. Generally, I prefer doom and black but I listen to alot of gothic and death as well. There
			are very few power-metal bands that interest me. The bands that I like most are either the founders of
			their genre or impossible to place in one. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you think the Swedish scene is doing, and what do you think of the bands from Norway and Finland?
		</p>
		<p>
			Without being too much of a patriot I would say that the swedish scene is the most interesting one in the
			world especially considering that Sweden is a rather small country. Most bands are more known outside
			Sweden though so it's really hard to keep track fo the scene. Norway and Finland are also very
			interesting countries that deliver alot of good music. Most of the bands that I really like are from one
			of these three countries.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you think of Satanism in metal?
		</p>
		<p>
			Depends on what you mean. To make satanism a part of the show can be both funny, cool and pathetic. It
			all depends on how you do it. The word satanism is actually rather tricky since it represents alot of
			ideas that aren't unified. The inverted-christianity kind of satanism that is about death and destruction
			is in my opinion as fucked up as chistianity or any other big religion. Being a rather hardcore atheist I
			find all supernatural beliefs as unattractive and stupid and I don't any of them to be synonymous to
			metal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			One thing I like is your artwork, who does it, and do you think it imparts the feeling of your music?
		</p>
		<p>
			I do it and yes it's supposed to visualize of the mood I create with my music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Does the natural enviroment of Sweden or of nature in general inspire you in any way?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's rather inspiring to walk around in nature but I don't think the swedish nature as such inspires me
			more than any other northern nature.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you think of the following statement: "Death is a natural thing, there is no reason to fear it"?
		</p>
		<p>
			Since I don't belive in a life after death or at least don't see it as a very likely scenario I do fear
			death in a sense that I don't feel ready to die. Still I know that it's a natural part of life and there
			not much to do about it. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Does the atmosphere of a funeral inspire you (nice joke question here)?
		</p>
		<p>
			I haven't attended that many funerals and I never felt more or less inspired at any of them. Ofcourse the
			death of a close one can inspire or at least you might need music to be able to deal with emotions that
			are hard to express in other ways.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How are gigs going, what kind of reception do you get?
		</p>
		<p>
			Since I'm the only memeber gigs are pretty much out of the question.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your plans for the near future?
		</p>
		<p>
			To start writing new material. I have alot of ideas already and I just do something about them. I might
			record something within a couple of months.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Finally, is there anything you'd like to say to the readers of Tmetal?
		</p>
		<p>
			Give "departure" a chance and hopefully you'll discover something new and if not then there's not much I
			can do about it...
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Christian" zine="vampster.com" date="050305">
		<p type="question">
			First of all, gratulation for your debut album "Departure". It's a masterpiece of atmospheric and melodic
			Doom Metal. Are you also satisfied with the album?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, I'm quite satisifed with it. There are ofcourse technical details that could be improved quite alot
			but considering the conditions under which I was producing the album I have to accept that I can't
			compete with proffesional super productions.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You are quasi a one-man-band? Are there more advantages or disadvantages?
		</p>
		<p>
			Considering my current situation with a quite demanding work in the gaming industry I don't get much time
			to spend on my music on a daily basis and it would be hell to try and cooperate with someone else. I also
			feel more comfortable when I have full control of the process and when things are done my way. Forest of
			Shadows are too important to me to allow for compromizes. So, generally speaking the advantages are more
			than the disadvantages.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			After you have split with Micce Anderson, who was also involved in writing the songs, what have been the
			biggest problems?
		</p>
		<p>
			To replace Micce's skill as an instrumentalist. My role in the band while Micce still was a member was
			more or less only to write the music and lyrics. I did some rythm guitars and programming and ofcourse
			all the vocals but apart from that Micce did everything. He was also in charge of the recordings and
			owned the fancy gear such as mixers, effects and amplifiers.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is it necessary, to be in a special mood for wirting such songs of pure sadness?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's not necessary but it helps. At least to come up with the basic ideas and melodies. The rest can be
			done no matter what state I'm in. I usually have a pretty clear idea of what it all should sound like in
			terms of production and that idea is always there.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			On "Departure" the sound of the guitars is very dominant - in some cases even the vocals seem to
			disappear into the guitarsound. Was this your intention?
		</p>
		<p>
			Are they? That sure wasn't my intention. Or actually it depends on what you mean. I didn't want them to
			drown the vocals but I wanted them to pretty dominant apart from that. I didn't want it to sound too
			symphonic.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The most tracks on "Departure" are quite long. Do your songs need this time, to develop their whole
			potential - or do you just have a soft spot, to create songs beyond ten minutes?
		</p>
		<p>
			I guess the songs just end up as very long. When I come up with a melody or harmony that I really like I
			want to give it the time it deserves. The alternative would be to split up the songs and instead have
			alot of songs that sound pretty similar. I really don't see the point in doing so. Working with slow
			music also makes the songs last for ages. I used to be a member in a thrash metal band were the music
			was like four times as fast, at least. When I wrote lyrics for these songs I ended up with texts that
			were as long as the ones I wrote for "forest of shadows". I mean if you take an arbitrary thrash song
			and play it at a fourth of the tempo it will last for over ten minutes.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Reading the lyrics, I have found many places, where you tell about the transience of beauty and love.
			What do you want to express with your words?
		</p>
		<p>
			They don't have any hidden messages if that's what you're wondering. They're just stories. Rather sad
			ones. I guess I just want the lyrics to fit the mood of the music. It just wouldn't work to use
			political or gore lyrics with the music of "forest of shadows". There's alot political and philosophical
			things I would like to express and I used to do that in the thrash/death band "shubend" in which I used
			to be a member.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Nearly each track on "Departure" got rewritten several times - so that the album took three years, to
			become "real". Are you such a perfectionist?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yes. Actually, it was not only a matter of perfectionism but also about turning the album into what I
			wanted but didn't get when I worked with Micce.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I could really imagine, that your songs would sound very cool at a live gig. But as you are "alone",
			this remains probably only imagination. Am I wright?
		</p>
		<p>
			Most likely. I mean I could probably get some session members. After all the songs are pretty simple to
			play. The big problem would be to arrange the songs in order to work in a "live" situation. It would also
			need a certain environment. Playing the songs at the local pub with alot of drunk people in the crowd and
			a horrible sound production wouldn't be fair to the songs. I have seen to many gigs with that happening. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You are a kind of a jack-of-all-trades. You played on "Departure" all instruments, wrote the lyrics, did
			the recording and mixing and also designed the booklet. Additionally you design and update your homepage
			on your own. Is there anything, you can't do?
		</p>
		<p>
			Relax? Well, to be honest there's alot of things I can't do and there is much to wish for when it comes
			to my instrumental skills. Still, I like the idea of doing it all by myself no matter if it could be way
			better if I hired session musicans. It gets more "true" and personal and uniform. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you plan to take additional band members into FOREST OF SHADOWS in the near future?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't plan to but I wouldn't say no if the perfect companion showed up.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Besides FOREST OF SHADOWS, you are/were also part of some side-projects. Could you please tell us more
			about these?
		</p>
		<p>
			The two main projects/bands are Ningizzia and Shubend. Ninigizzia is band I have with Stephane Peudpin in
			France. Our music isn't all too different from Forest of Shadows and I would guess that we share the same
			types of listeners. An album to recommend is the full-length "dolorous novella" which we release some
			year ago. It's a really dark and rather diverse album. Shubend, which I'm no longer in, is on the other
			hand more of a thrash/death band. I wouldn't guess that we share many listeners at all but still it might
			be interesting to check them out. We released a full-length on Rage of Achilles some year ago called
			"Synergism" and we recorded an album rather recently called "Posthumous" which unfortunatelly never got
			a proper release. Most likely we will share the songs as mp3's instead of letting them rot in obsurity.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What kind of music is at the time in your CD-player?
		</p>
		<p>
			I just listend to soilwork, a band that hasn't picked up my attention before, and I must say they're
			really good. Not the typical music I listen to these days though. The better bands that spin in my
			cd-player these days are bands like cult of luna, isis, funeral orchestra and shape of depair.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Besides your love and half-time profession of making music, you have a job in the computer games
			industry. Can you tell us more about that?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, I work with sound/music as a programmer at a company called Avalanche Studios here in Stockholm.
			It's quite fun even though it has a rather negative impact on my music not to mention my social life
			since it demands quite alot of time. What makes me pay this rather high price is that it feels much more
			rock'n'roll to work games than to work at some boring company with boring tasks. I'm not saying that all
			companies outside the gaming industry are boring and unattractive but unfortunatelly most of them.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your musical plans for the upcomming months?
		</p>
		<p>
			To continue to grow some distance from "departure" so I can to start my next project with new fresh
			ideas instead of just repeating what I did on that album.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Josean" zine="goimusic.com" date="050209">
		<p type="question">
			The first thing that calls my attention is that Forest Of Shadows is a one man band. How do you manage
			to record by yourself all the instruments?
		</p>
		<p>
			It wasn't easy, even though the songs are far from technical. I mean I'm not really an instrumentalist in
			any way. I know how to handle the guitar and piano but at a rather basic level. Anyways, I had a will of
			doing it and given enough time I knew I would pull it through in some way. And so I did. I guess it
			helped that I arranged the music in such a way to make it as easy as possible to play without losing any
			of the musical quality.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Don't you have the help of any session musician?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not on "departure". I guess somewhere deep inside I really wanted to do it all by myself. I could have
			asked some of the musical friends that I know to help me out but I didn't. Maybe I'll do that for the
			next release. Or maybe I won't. There are rather positive effects of doing it all by yourself. The album
			gets way more personal and it's easier to control the final result. And since I'm a control freak when it
			comes to music I really value that.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Has it always been like this or was ever there more band members?
		</p>
		<p>
			There have been a lot of members coming and going. Micce Andersson is one of these and the one that
			stayed in the band for longest time. He had a key role in forming Forest of Shadows into what it has
			become in terms of sound and arrangements. He was also something of a mentor to me and I learnt alot
			from him about music in general.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What musical studies have you? What instrument do you identify yourself with the most?
		</p>
		<p>
			The only musical education I have apart from piano lessons when I was a kid is a survey course in how
			music is used in film. So pretty much none I would say. I'm pretty much self learnt which has its pros
			and cons. I have actually always been more into composing than playing. I started composing music on the
			guitar more or less the same day I learnt to play it. My main instrument is probably piano since it's the
			one I feel most comfortable improvising on.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			For a single person, composing an album and recording must be tough work. Is this the reason why it's
			taken you three years to release your sophomore album or are there other reasons?
		</p>
		<p>
			That and the fact that I am a normal person with a normal work that takes up a lot of my time. Well,
			actually I wasn't employed during the entire process so I can't just blame it on my work. I guess a more
			accurate reason why it took so long is the fact that I'm a perfectionist. I didn't care about the
			restrictions set by my skills at performing, recording and most important of all my studio equipment. I
			still wanted it to sound as good or even better as an average, professionally produced metal album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The tracks were composed between the 2000-2002 period, when you entered the studio to record, did you
			make some further arragements there or did they remain such as they were?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, to start with I never entered an actual studio since I recorded everything in my apartment.
			Anyways, I did change the arrangements quite a lot during the recording process. This is quite evident if
			you take the oldest song - "November dream" - and compare it with the original recording on the demo "The
			Silent Cry" from 1998.  
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Have you already composed tracks for your next album?
		</p>
		<p>
			I have some sketches and ideas but nothing that is near a final composition. The thing is that I haven't
			even signed a deal for my next album. There will be a next album though but I'm not sure when I will
			start working on it seriously. I need to give it all some distance since the years with "departure" had
			quite a negative impact on my health and life in general. I lived and breathed that album for like three
			years and it felt like being haunted.     
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Apart from composing and playing all the instruments, you have also recorded and mixed the tracks. Don't
			you trust anyone or is it a more comfortable way of working and also a way of saving money in the
			production process?
		</p>
		<p>
			It was mostly because of money but it's also a comfortable way of working since I can record whenever I
			feel motivated and inspired. I wouldn't say it's lack of trust that is the big problem. More that I see
			the recording and mixing as a very important part of the artwork and something I want to control to 100%.
			I don't think there are many producers that want to work under such conditions. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You mix Doom or Funeral Doom with certain Swedish Folk airs. Where does your inspiration come from?
		</p>
		<p>
			When it comes to doom I would say that I'm more influenced by the style in general than specific bands.
			In my opinion there are very few good doom bands but the ones that are good are really good. For some
			reason most doom bands sound dull to me. They have alot of the classical elements but there is always
			something missing.
		</p>
		<p>
			Swedish folk music is something I started to enjoy when I teamed up with Micce in 1998. My interest for
			this music has grown ever since. I can't say that I like everything that is labeled "Swedish Folk". But I
			mean that's just like with all other styles. There's lots of crappy metal music for instance. There is
			something genuine and original in folk music that is hard to find anywhere else and I guess that is what
			inspires me most.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The electronic intro might even remind people of more alternative bands such as Portishead or Massive
			Attack. Have these bands and their sound influenced you?
		</p>
		<p>
			I listen to the mentioned bands every now and then and I like them a lot. What these bands have learnt
			me is that it's more than possible to make doomy music without distored guitars and big drums. I guess
			there is doom and there is doom and to me it's all the same. I care more about what lies beneath surface
			than the surface itself.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Apart from Forest Of Shadows. Do you play in other bands?
		</p>
		<p>
			I am one of two members of the band Ningizzia and up until recently I did the vocals in a band called
			Shubend. The music of Ningizzia is quite similar to Forest of Shadows and I would really recommend it.
			Shubend on the other hand is more of a technical thrash/death band and I wouldn't bet too much on that
			the people who like this band likes Forest of Shadows.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You come from Sweden and have found for the Finish label Firedoom. How did you get in contact with this
			label?
		</p>
		<p>
			I got a tip from Duncan at Rage of Achilles (the label that initially was supposed to release
			"departure") to contact them. Actually Duncan helped me out to establish the contact and I'm very
			thankful for that. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I guess that being a single-man band, playing live it's quite difficult or impossible. How do you see the
			chances of playing live?
		</p>
		<p>
			I actually don't see them at all. Not only would it require a lot of session musicans but also some major
			rearrangements of the songs to make them work live. After all Forest of Shadows is a studio band and it's
			hard or even impossible to create the same atmosphere live. Still, I do dream every now and then of
			playing live with Forest of Shadows. And who knows? It has happened before so it might happen again.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="gero" zine="eutk.net" date="050122">
		<p type="question">
			I think "Departure" in one of the best album of the past year. After four years of work, are you
			satisfied with the result?
		</p>
		<p>
			Considering the fact that it was all done by myself with a more or less	non-existing budget I must say
			that I am very satisfied. On the other hand	I am very aware of how much better it could have been if it
			would have been	recorded in a "real" studio with a nice producer. Still, what counts isn't the polished
			surface but what lies beneath, which is something that I'm very	proud of.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How Micce Andersson contributed to the composition process? Why did he leave the band shortly before the
			release of the album?
		</p>
		<p>
			He co-wrote most of the stuff and we almost pulled it all through together.
			It was in the middle of first recording session when I realized how very
			different our visions were about the final result and I just couldn't see myself
			being part of an album built on compromizes. So, no matter how important Micce
			was to the band I just felt that I had to finish it all by myself. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You had many problems with some labels, but I think you have found in 
			Firedoom the best company according to your style and mood... do you agree?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, even though Rage of Achilles, the previous label, was a very good and
			suitable label for the band I must say that Firedoom is even better. I don't
			know if Firedoom is the ultimate label but they have done a very good job so
			far.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What is the "Forest Of Shadows"? And from what is your "Departure"?
		</p>
		<p>
			Depends on who you ask :) If you ask someone who is into dungeons and dragons
			they would say that it's a place in their fantasy world. When I came up with the
			name I didn't know anything about this so there's no connection whatsoever
			between the band and roleplaying. There were also plans about making a Harry
			Potter book called "Harry Potter and the Forest of Shadows". I don't know what
			happened with that and I sure didn't have anything to do with it. Seriously.
			So, what is my "Forest of Shadows" then? Well, a description of a pretty dark
			and pretty lifeless reality. That's what I wanted it to symbolize anyway.
		</p>
		<p>	
			The title "departure" can be interpreted in many ways. All the songs are about
			leaving life either perceived by the one leaving or the one left behind. So that's
			one interpretation. Another more personal interpretation is that symbolize what
			was happening during the time which the album was recorded. During this time I
			started a new life and left an old one behind I also moved into a new direction
			musically and left the more traditional metal scene behind. Micce, the most
			important member of the band, apart from me :), also departed from the band. So
			to conclude the title "departure" felt pretty suitable.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the feelings you want to express with your music? It's dark, 
			but in certain moments it seems to open for some hope...
		</p>
		<p>
			It's pretty hard to put down in words exactly what I want to express with my
			music. I want to create an overall dark and sinister but still in some way
			beautifull atmosphere. I guess hope is what makes it beautifull, that is if there
			is any hope in my music. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Recently I have listened to another band that plays music similar to 
			yours... it's the dutch band Deinonychus, have you ever got in touch 
			with them?
		</p>
		<p>
			I own one album with Deinonychus called "The Weeping of a Thousand Years". Can't
			say it's my favourite album but it's not all that bad. Apart from that I haven't
			heard much but maybee I should. I know that mr Deinonychus plays (or played)
			in Bethlehem which is one of my favourite bands. At least on "Dark Metal" and
			"Dictius te Necare". I wouldn't say that they sound like "Forest of Shadows" though.
			I have never spoken with any member of either Deinonychus or Bethlehem.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your main influences? And your favourite listens at the moment?
		</p>
		<p>
			My most recent influences are: Cult of Luna, Isis, Anekdoten, Shape of Despair,
			Katatonia and Antimater. There are some other as well but they aren't as important.
			Some of the favourite bands that I listen to these days are: The above mentioned as
			well as Garmarna, Darkthrone, Satyricon, The Provenance, Paatos, The Funeral
			Orchestra, Zyklon, Napalm Death and Rapture.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the advantages and disadvantages of having a real band 
			versus playing completely alone?
		</p>
		<p>
			If you're involved in a real band you have to invest quite alot of time in it on a
			regular basis and that's not something I am able to do right now. In the long run it's
			way more time consuming to do it all by yourself but at least I get to choose when I
			am to spend my time. It's less frustrating on a creative level to be solo since you
			don't to compromize and stuff but it's always more fun to be able to share the joy
			of creating something good with other band members. If I would have had the time and
			money to be able to run the band as a fulltime work then I would definatelly team up 
			with some good people but that's not the case here.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Obviously we're not going to see you in tour...?! Do you think your 
			music is suitable for live shows?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not as a rock'n'roll show. It might work pretty well if it was performed in a more
			dramatic and magic scenery like some old theater or something like that. It would also
			demand quite alot of musicans and alot of rearranging of the songs since they aren't
			made for the standard setup.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Keep up the good works, for "Departure" is truly one of them!
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanx
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Robert Hoyem" zine="metal-norge.com" date="050108">
		<p type="question">
			Death / doom blandet med endel elektronikk. Ikke akkurat dagligdags kost. Det er iallefall hva Forest of
			Shadows driver med, og de (han) gjør det på en helt utmerket måte. Hvis du ikke har skaffet deg et av
			fjorårets beste doom-plater så er det på tide å gjøre det nå. Jeg har uansett sendt avgårde noen
			elektroniske spørsmål til bandets eneste medlem, Niclas Frohagen, og fikk svar på dem ganske nylig...
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Heisann - gratulerer med "Departure", og takk for et av årets beste plater!
		</p>
		<p>
			Det gleder meg å høre at du anser "Departure" som et av årets beste plater.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			For det har ikke vært bare enkelt å få debutplata ut i butikken. Den skulle vel egentlig ut på Rage of
			Achilles, men sånn gikk det ikke til? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Rage of Achilles skulle egentlig gi ut skiva, men det ble avlyst helt mot slutten på grunn av økonomiske
			problemer. Endog hjelpte de til med å finne et nytt plateselskap (Firebox / Firedoom) som kunne ta over
			plateslippet, så det hele gikk ganske bra til. Det var egentlig synd at det gikk som det gikk med Rage of
			Achilles, for de stod bak en hel del interessante skiveslipp og en masse nytenkning innen metal-sjangeren
			som virkelig behøves.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Men dere slapp altså ei miniskive på Rage of Achilles. Hvordan står den seg i dag, i forhold til
			"Departure"?
		</p>
		<p>
			Miniskiva "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" har en hel del likheter med "Departure" av den enkle grunn av at vi
			ville utvikle oss videre i samme retning. En del låter på "Departure" ble dessuten påbegynt samtidig som
			vi holdt på å gjøre ferdig miniskiva. Den store forskjellen er at lydbildet er at lydbildet har fått mer
			framtredende elektroniske innslag, og at arrangementene er mer varierte og velpolerte. Jeg tror
			definitivt at de som liker miniskiva kommer til å like "Departure" og visa versa.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Noe som slo meg når jeg kikket igjennom diskografien på hjemmesida til Forest of Shadows
			(www.forestofshadows.com), var at låta "November Dream" stammer så langt tilbake som til "The Silent
			Cry"-demoen fra 1998 - korriger meg gjerne om jeg tar feil. Hvordan har denne låta utviklet seg, og
			hvorfor har du valgt å beholde den på full-lengderen?
		</p>
		<p>
			Det er en veldig stor forskjell på hvordan "November Dream" på 98'-demoen og på "Departure". En hel del
			partier er skrevet på nytt, og en del av de gamle er strøket. Hvorfor jeg valgte å inkludere på
			"Departure", er av den enkle anledning at jeg synes det er ei bra låt som ikke kom til sin rett på
			demoen. Sannsynligvis kommer låta "Moments of Solitude" som også finnes på 98'-demoen til å bli pusset
			opp på samme måte. Alle låter jeg har sluppet med Forest of Shadows er låter som jeg har et dyptpløyende
			forhold til av ulike grunner, og jeg vil derfor at alle skal få et bedre ytre enn hva de fikk på en
			obskur demo.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Selv om Forest of Shadows i all hovedsak for det meste har vært ditt prosjekt, har du hatt med noen
			medlemmer inni mellom - Micce blant annet er kreditert på endel av låtene på "Departure". Hvor mye har
			han betydd for hvordan alt låter der?
		</p>
		<p>
			Micce har betydd veldig mye for Forest of Shadows, ikke bare som medkompositør på "Departure". Til
			forskjell fra meg er Micce en skolert musiker og han stilte derfor meget høyere krav til både produksjon
			og låtskrivning. Takket være dette styrte han bandet frå å være et obskyrt prosjekt til et band som til
			slutt fikk en platekontrakt og som har flere beundrere over hele verden. Utenom Micce finnes det enda et
			betydningsfult medlem, nemelig Martin Claessib som krediteres på en del av materialet på miniskiva - både
			som låtskriver og tekstforfatter. Martin var akkurat som meg, ingen en supermusiker, men mer en person
			som brenner for sjangeren og atmosfæren - den delen er også veldig viktig. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Hvorfor er nå Forest of Shadows et soloprosjekt igjen?
		</p>
		<p>
			Micce og jeg hadde ikke det samme synet på hvordan ting skulle låte, og til tross hans enorme kompetanse
			var det mot slutten ikke holdbart å fortsette samarbeidet. Jeg vil ganske enkelt ikke at den tida og
			engergien jeg legger ned i Forest of shadows skal brukes til å lage musikk som bygger på kompromisser.
			Det holder ikke i lengden. Demokrati er ikke alltid den beste metoden. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Forest of Shadows framstår på "Departure" som litt halv-elektronisk. Jeg synes faktisk jeg hører endel
			Massive Attack i musikken. Henter du påvirkninger fra andre elektroniske band, isåfall hvilke?
		</p>
		<p>
			Massive Attack, Portishead, Garmarna, Earthling, Depeche Mode, Björk og Animatter er noen av de banda med
			elektroniske innslag som jeg inspireres av. Å tilføre musikken elektroniske innslag er for meg veldig
			viktig, ettersom det fresher opp det utslitte og veldig konservative lydbildet som finnes i de fleste
			metalband. Kunsten ligge i å gjøre det på rett vis, slik at atmosfæren forblir intakt. Man kan med
			enkelhet ødelegge bra låter med å modernisere dem på feil vis og få dem til å låte som radiopop. Band som
			Animatter, Massive Attack,Garmarna og Portishead har lyktes i å lage låter som er mørkere og med doomy
			enn mange doom-band.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			På den måten låter liksom Forest of Shadows litt annerledes. Ikke for det, deathmetal-delen av musikken
			er absolutt fortreffelig også. Hvilke metalband har du hentet inspirasjon fra? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Oj, det er mange. Om vil holder oss til "Departure", så er de viktigste inspirasjonskildene: Shape of
			Despair, Cult of Luna, Isis, Anathema, Opeth, Katatonia og Rapture. Spesielt de to førstnevnte har vært
			veldig viktig for "Departure", av den enkle grunn at begge to har vallgt å gjøre doom metal på sin egen
			måte, og fått det til veldig bra. Hva ren death-metal angår, så finnes det ingen band som har inspirert
			meg særlig mye, selv om jeg hører veldig mye på band i den sjangeren.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Lyrikken på "Departure" er overvelmende trist, og virker veldig ektefølt. Ligger det mye sørgelig bak
			tekstene, eller er det bare historier og skildringer?
		</p>
		<p>
			Sett utenifra, så er det bare historier og skildringer, men bak disse finnes det i de fleste tilfellene
			en for av ekte hendelse som ligger til grunn. Disse hendelsene er åpenbart ikke de gladeste i mitt liv.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Trommene, de er programerte - ikke at det gjør noe, for de er programert veldig bra, men hvorfor er de
			det? Hvorfor ikke en ekte trommis?
		</p>
		<p>
			Vi spilte faktisk inn ekte trommer på "Departure", men resultatet ble ikke helt hva vi håpet på, det er
			selvfølgelig trivlig med ekte ekte trommer, ettersom det gjør låtene mer levende, men det blir dumt å ha
			det med bare for sakens skyld. Spesielt når man ikke er et live-band. Jeg kommer alltid til å forsøke å
			bruke ekte trommer, men ikke til hvilken som helst pris.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Personlig sliter jeg veldig med å plukke ut favorittpartier eller låter fra albumet, men om det er et
			parti som gir meg ekstra gåshud, så er det helt på slutten av tittelsporet, akkurat når du kjører på med
			death-vokal og hurtige trommer. Herlig. Ellers synes jeg hver av låtene har sitt utrykk, og fungerer
			veldig bra på hver sin måte. Har du kanskje noen egne favorittlåter fra plata?
		</p>
		<p>
			Selvfølgelig. Jeg vet av mange artister som ikke kan høre på sine egne saker, men personlig så gør jeg
			det ganske ofte, dog aldri som bakgrunnsmusikk. Ved å høre på min egen musikk kan jeg forflytte meg
			bakover i tid til de følelsene jeg hadde da skiva ble spilt inn. Om man ser på helheten så synes jeg nok
			at tittelsporet "Departure" er det beste på plata. Om man i stedet får velge ut deler av hver låt, så
			synes jeg nok at starten på "Sleeping Death", midtpartiet på "November Dream", slutten på "Bleak
			Dormintion", siste refrenget og framover på "Open Wound" og midtpartiet på "Departure" er høydepunktene.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Er du interessert i hva som foregår i doom-metal-scenen i dag? Er det noen band som interesserer deg mer
			en andre?
		</p>
		<p>
			Jeg er vel interessert, men har ikke nok til og ork til å sette meg ned og holde meg informert. De siste
			bandene jeg sjekket ut og virkelig liker er Shape of Despair, Isis, Krux, Funeral Orchestra og Slumber.
			Noen av dem er kanskje ikke helt "doom", men det var nå uansett de jeg kom på...
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Er du involvert i flere band? I såfall, kan du fortelle litt om disse også?
		</p>
		<p>
			Ningizzia er et band jeg har med Stephane Peudupin som bor i Paris. Vi har hatt dette bandet sammen siden
			1997, og har sluppet en demo; "The Dark Path" og en full-lengder "Dolorus Novella", samt vært med på
			samleskiva "The Cold, The Silent" fra Dragonflight Records, og en hyllest til Mayhem med en cover av
			"Freezing Moon". Musikken til Ningizzia er ganske lik Forest of Shadows med mer variasjon i både steming
			og arrangering.
		</p>
		<p>
			Shubend er et band jeg er med i sammen med Dan Lundberg og Martin Eriksson. Vi har spilt inn to demoer
			"Hook, Line and Sinker" og "Singularis", samt en full-lengder "Synergism". Vi har til og med vært med på
			samleskiva på Rage of Achilles, som heter "Conquest of the Empire", som forøvrig også inneholder ei låt
			fra Forest of Shadows. Likhetene mellom Shubend og Forest of Shadows er veldig få, den største likheten
			er nok at det er jeg som står bak mikrofonen i begge banda. Liker man teknisk death/thrash er det nok
			verdt å sjekke ut.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Helt her til slutt må jeg takke for intervjuet og oppfordre deg til å fortsette å lage så fortreffelig
			musikk vi får høre på "Departure"!
		</p>
		<p>
			Selv takk. Jeg skal gjøre mitt beste for å tilfredstille de som liker mine tidligere verk. 
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Haiko" zine="Tinnitus Mag" date="041226">
		<p type="question">
			Hi Niclas. Puh, after four years of hard work the record is finally finished. Very facilitated I guess?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, it was a very demanding period with respect to both time and energy so when it all was finished it
			felt like a great relief. When you work on something for such a long time and with such intensity you get
			addicted to it in a weird way. I was so used to listening to the stuff on a regular basis that I
			continued doing so even after the release. Not because I felt like it but more like an addiction. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What were the problems during those years? I heard about band members coming and going, but finally
			"Forest Of Shadows" is just you..
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, there was just one more member apart from me that was involved in "departure" so it wasn't that
			much about people coming and going, more about one very important member that left the band. This member,
			Micce Andersson, was the main instrumentalist so his departure had quite an impact on the recording of
			"departure". This problem was something I felt I had to live with though since I didn't believe in us two
			finishing the album since we disagreed on too many details.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How is the resonance to "Departure"? I for my part must say that I really like it.
		</p>
		<p>
			I would say it's pretty good. There has been some negative words about it but generally speaking it has
			been very positive. Much more than expected.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			"Departure" offers very intense and very melancholic music and lyrics. How much is this atmosphere part
			of you? Do you have to be in a certain mood for the creation of your art?
		</p>
		<p>
			I wouldn't label myself as melancholic, not even sad. Still, there is a huge part of me that is far from
			happy and I guess we all have that part inside us. Some just choose to hide it deep within. So, to answer
			your question I would say no, I don't have to be in a certain mood to create my music even though it help
			if I'm feeling a bit down.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Can you say something about your way of songwriting? What inspires you to create certain music or lyrics?
		</p>
		<p>
			I usually base my music on a simple melody or harmony. On top of this I add layer after layer until I
			can't come up with anything more to add. After that I try to remove everything that I find redundant in
			order to make it sound less messy. Somewhere during this phase I start adding the vocals. The lyrics for
			the vocals are written and re-written during the entire process. 
		</p>
		<p>
			What inspires me then? Well, I get inspired by a lot of things. For music I guess other pieces of music
			are the main inspiration but I could get inspired by certain events in life as well. Sometime the
			melodies just come to you and sometimes you have to search by listening to other pieces of music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What kind of music is Niclas Frohagen listening in private? 
		</p>
		<p>
			I try to listen to all kinds of music and focus on what's good or bad music instead of what belongs to
			certain genres. Currently I'm quite into stuff like Cult of Luna, Isis, Darkthrone and Shape of Despair. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you earn a living? I can't imagine it's possible to earn to much money with the music you create,
			especially with that work load, ha ha. I heard the welfare state is going down the tubes in Sweden,
			similarly to Germany...
		</p>
		<p>
			I earn my living as a programmer at a game developer here in Stockholm. I work alot with sound and music
			so I like it very much. And, no. You can't make a living by producing my kind of music. Not the way I
			want it anyway. We have a welfare system in Sweden as you said that do allow people to more or less work
			with music on a full-time basis. This provided that you fool the system to some extent. It's not very
			good for the country at least not when the amount of lazy people are growing as much as it does. I
			wouldn't say that the welfare system is going down the tubes though but it's not very far from doing so.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Let's go back in time a little bit. Can you tell the readers something about the history of "Forest Of
			Shadows"? What are your aims with this band?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, it started out in 1997 as a solo-project of mine in that half a year later resulted in the first
			demo "The Silent Cry". Later on Micce Andersson joined the band and took it to a new level which was
			proven on the albums "promo '99" and "promo 2000". During this time Martin Claesson joined as well and
			the band turned into a rehearsing band with ambitions of doing live gigs. That didn't last very long
			though partly because of the two less good gigs we did during that time. So, some time later Martin left
			and me and Micce started recording what would result in our first official release, that is the mCD
			"where dreams turn to dust". There was some mess about who was supposed to release the demo and for some
			time we didn't even know if it was to be released officially at all. At last it ended up in the hands of
			the english label "Rage of Achilles" who released it in October 2001. The contract with RoA included a
			full-length as well which we started working on right before the release of the mCD. This process didn't
			go all that well though and lasted for quite sometime duing which Micce left the band and RoA ceased to
			exist due to financial problems. As we all know there was a happy end and in 2004 finnish label Firedoom
			released the first full-length "departure".
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What is it that people in Sweden are often such great multi- instrumentalists? You for example have
			played any instrument On "Departure"..
		</p>
		<p>
			It's true that I play all instruments on "departure" but there is alot of work and will behind it. Why we
			have so many good instrumentalists in Sweden is probably because we have a good musical education in
			school. Most people in Sweden play or have played some kind of instrument.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the plans for the future? Is "Forest Of Shadows" going to stay as a solo - project of yours? If
			yes, are there any plans of performing live, maybe along with session musicians?
		</p>
		<p>
			I really don't know about the future of Forest of Shadows right now apart from that it will exist for yet
			a couple of albums. I have no ambition of recruiting any memebers but I wouldn't say no if someone shows
			up that really suits the band. There are no plans or ambitions for that matter of doing any performances
			with or without session musicans.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How many years will we have to wait for the next Record? 
		</p>
		<p>
			That's very hard to say. It all depends on how much time I get to spend on my music and as it is right
			now I wouldn't expect anything within a year from now.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Niclas, thanks for your time, much luck for the future of "Forest Of Shadows", time for some last words:
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanx for a nice interview and good luck with the zine.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Jens" zine="Walls of Fire" date="041215">
		<p type="question">
			Hello Niclas, how are you doing?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm doing just fine, thanx. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			First up, congratulations for your new album - it's really awesome. I rated it 9/10. How has the other
			feedback been?
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanks alot. It's always flattering to get such high rating no matter if it's common or not. So far I
			have actually scored pretty well in most reviews, especially the german ones. Not everyone likes the
			album though and especially	here in Sweden there are some critics that really have issues with it. And to
			some extent I understand them since it's a quite provocative album with it's monumental and monotone
			songs. It's very easy to label it as pretentious and overdone, even though I wouldn't consider it as
			such. Well pretentious in a	good way maybe. I mean I really try to make it as good as possible and I
			don't see anything wrong with that.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What took you that long to finish the songs? The MCD "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" is now three years old.
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, alot of things happened during these three years so it's actually not that much of a mystery why it
			took so long. When Micce left the band we had already been working on the new album for about a year. The
			material was more or less finished but it was filled with compromizes caused by our diverging visions.
			When I suddenly had it all in my own hands I felt that I had to	straighten it out before I could continue
			working with it. I did some major rearranging which took quite alot of time and while I was doing this I
			also had to learn how to play it since Micce was the one who normally handled the instruments. So with
			this in mind it didn't take that long to produce the album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why didn't you write really new material? I mean the songs were all written a long time ago.
		</p>
		<p>
			All songs apart from "November Dream" were written after the material on the mCD so it's as new as can
			be. Ofcourse I could have dumped the songs when Micce left and started working on new songs. But I
			didn't. And the reason is quite simple: I liked the songs very much and dumping them was not an option.  
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Considering the fact that some of the songs are from the year 1997 - would you speak of progress when
			comparing the MCD and the new album? I think the My Dying Bride influence is little less.
		</p>
		<p>
			I never saw and I still can't see the resemblance to My Dying Bride in Forest of Shadows. I might be
			blind but I just don't think that we sound that similar, at all. Don't get me wrong, I do love My Dying
			Bride and they are a big influence, especially the albums "turn loose the swans" and "the angel and the
			dark river" but I never tried to be a My Dying Bride clone in any way. Anyways, there has definatelly
			been a huge amount of progress since mCD. The sound has changed from being more standard doom/death to
			a weird fusion of electronica, metal and rock with both more aggression and cheesy elements. On a basic
			level it's pretty much the same as on the mCD though.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why did you reduce the folk elements?
		</p>
		<p>
			Did I? I think the new album has as much folk elements as the mCD. The big difference is that there is no
			flute or violin on the new album. No matter what it was not my purpose to get rid of these elements. I
			really love folk music and I wish that I could incorporate it more into the songs.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your former bandmate Micce Anderson has co-written nearly all of the songs. Did that happen when he was
			till in the band or have you worked together after the official "split"?
		</p>
		<p>
			It happened before we split up. As I said before the material was more or less finished when he left so
			why it took yet another two years before it was really finished was because I rearranged it all to match
			my visions. If we would have continued to work together we would probably have finished the album within
			a couple of months.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You have recorded the album on your own. Please describe what is like to do everything? Isn't it too
			much work?
		</p>
		<p>
			To do everything by yourself is very good since the album gets very personal. It also gets closer to your
			visions which is very satisfying. The bad thing about it is that it's very time and energy consuming. The
			fact that it's hard to master all instruments can also restrict the album and in my case I would say that
			it did. If it's too much work to do it all on your own is hard to say. If you know that the result will
			be better then it's definatelly worth the extra work. In my case I did it all by myself because since
			there was no alternative.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Was it a special challenge writing an instrumental like "Bleak Dormition" - or was it ordinary
			songwriting without adding some lyrics?
		</p>
		<p>
			I wouldn't say writing an instrumental is more difficult than one with lyrics. Rather the opposite. In
			most of the songs that I have written I added the lyrics after the instrumental part was finished. So
			with that in mind, writing "Bleak Dormition" wasn't any different than any other songs apart from the
			fact that I didin't have to spend any time on writing lyrics for it.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The lyrics once again deal with death. Is it just because it fits to the depressive music or do they
			really reveal what you are thinking?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm not suicidal and thus they don't reveal my exact thoughts. The lyrics can be read in more than one
			way though and in another interpretation they could be more close what I am thinking. Why they are as
			they are is like you say, they fit the music. It's as simple as that.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			"Departure" is released on Firedoom Music - why aren't you signed to Rage of Achilles anymore? I heard
			from other bands that ROA couldn't afford paying the studio bills for their records (e.g. Omnium
			Gatherum) - same problem with you?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, "departure" wasn't recorded in a "real" studio and thus there were no bills to pay. The only thing
			that they said that they would pay was the mastering. Anyways, why Forest of Shadows left Rage of
			Achilles for Firedoom was because they said that they wouldn't be able to release the album due to
			financial problems. I was never disappointed at Rage of Achilles and their work and if it wouldn't have
			been for the financial issue I would probably still be signed to them. They actually helped me by getting
			in contact with Firebox/Firedoom and thus saved the band from disaster.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are your plans for the near future? A new album - do you already have some new songs - or adding
			some members to the band?
		</p>
		<p>
			There are some unofficial plans for the future that I don't want to get into yet since it will only
			create alot of expecations. I don't like, or am able for that matter, to work under too much pressure so
			I will unfold these new plans once I have the new material ready to be recorded. What I can say is that
			I have more than enough material already for the next release.
		</p>
		<p>
			Adding new members isn't anything I am planning for. But if someone shows up that has the right attitude
			and talent then I guess I won't turn that person down.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Toni" zine="Miasma Magazine" date="041213">
		<p type="question">
			Greetings from Finland! How's life in the Forest of Shadows camp?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's quite alright, thanks.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You've finally managed to put out your debut CD, how does it feel?
		</p>
		<p>
			It feels very nice. Especially due to the circumstances. I mean it was developed over a rather long
			period of time filled with various kinds of problems that made it all rather painfull. But there's an end
			to everything and this time it was a happy one. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You did everything on Departure yourself. What was the process like and What are your methods in making
			an album?
		</p>
		<p>
			Most of the basic parts of the compositions were done together with former member Micce so I can't take
			credit for doing it all by myself. Apart from that I did everything by myself and I must say that it
			wasn't always that funny. I mean when I create music I want it to sound a certain way and if my far from
			perfected skills restricts me from reaching this goal I get rather frustrated. I guess that's one of the
			main reason why it all took so long. My ambitions were far higher than my skills and it all ended in alot
			of recordings until I was satisfied.
		</p>
		<p>
			My methods for creating an album is of the incremental type. I record alot of simple melodies and
			harmonies and merge the similar parts to basic song structures. Then I build layer after layer upon each
			foundation to make it all more complete and unified. Finally I try remove as much as possible apart from
			the very essential notes so it doesn't get too messy. The actuall recordings are done while the songs
			are being composed over and over again.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Could you ever think of using outside assistance with FOS albums?
		</p>
		<p>
			Sure I could if this assistance adds something to the music that can't be added in some other way. I
			really try to do as much possible by myself since it gives me more control but I'm very aware of the fact
			that there are limits to my instrumental skills and I don't like to be restricted by such limits.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What kind of a process is songwriting for you?
		</p>
		<p>
			A rather long and frustrating one since I never get satisfied.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How would you describe the music of FOS?
		</p>
		<p>
			As dark, depressive, melodic and progressive. By progressive I don't mean pretentious and overdone but
			more the kind of music that breaks boundraries.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do people usually react to the music of FOS, and why?
		</p>
		<p>
			Most people seem to react pretty positive. Even some of thoose who normally don't like the style. I would
			almost call it easy-listening metal at times. Most people find it rather dark and melancholic though. A
			bit more than they can handle.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your music is very dark, sad and cold, in a good way. Is darkness a natural thing for you?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not natural as in me being a depressed and suicidal person. I'm just attracted the darker kinds of art.
			Ofcourse I have had my share of grief which function as inspiration but apart from that I'm not that dark
			minded. I have a rather dark and morbid sense of humour though and I'm very aware of the fact that there
			is more in life than peace, love and understanding.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where does this darkness come from?
		</p>
		<p>
			From within. I never found it hard to get inspiration for making dark music. It's much harder to try and
			create happy music. More or less impossible I would say since I can't take it serious if it's happy.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What is the very essence of your music and what's your biggest inspiration?
		</p>
		<p>
			The very essence of my music is darkness in all kinds of forms and my biggest inspiration for this is
			life itself. Either experience by myself or told by others.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Departure seems to tell a very sad story. Is there a consept behind the album? 
		</p>
		<p>
			The songs weren't composed with a concept i mind but when I rearranged them I tried hard to unify them.
			I really like albums that are unified no matter if there's a concept behind it all or not. It's a much
			bigger experience for me to listen to that kind of albums than listening to albums were you have to skip
			tracks before you reach that special song that is the only reason why you bought the album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is the any philosophy behind the lyrics?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, there is very much more behind the lyrics than the obvious interpretations. I don't want give away
			any secrets and thus I leave it to the listener to figure out what the lyrics are really about.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the thing you like to write about?
		</p>
		<p>
			Emotionall stuff. Things that have a meaning to me and that deals with situations in life that were quite
			hard to get through. It's all very dressed up in fancy and pretentious pseudo-poetry to match the style
			of the music but the very core of it is rather simple and personal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who do you think are the biggest influences in the music of FOS, and why?
		</p>
		<p>
			That varies with time. For "departure" I would say Opeth, Katatonia, Rapture, Cult of Luna, Massive
			Attack, Portishead, Anekdoten and Anathema. Why? Well, since they all resembled the kind of music that I
			wanted to create for this release.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			FOS has existed from the year 1997, but it's still fairly unknown here in Finland. Could you tell us
			something about the history of FOS?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's not very mysterious that Forest of Shadows isn't that known since there has only been two official
			releases and both on rather small labels. What has happened since 1997 then. Well, quite alot. It all
			started in Halmstad as a solo-project of mine with no ambitions whatsoever. After the release of the
			first demo "The Silent Cry" in 1998 Micce Andersson arrived and made the band to alot more than it used
			to be. We released two promos "promo '99" and "promo 2000" before we became a stable three-piece with
			Martin Claesson on guitar. The three of us had the ambition of turning Forest of Shadows into a
			performing band and we did two gigs with various session members. It didn't go very well though and when
			Martin left since he didn't share the same vision as me we turned the band into a studio project once
			again. With alot of success behind us from mp3.com were we had reigned the charts with the songs from the
			previous two promos we started recording what would be our first offical release, the mCD "where dreams
			turn to dust", with great motivation. The material ended first up at a small American label called Molded
			Skull Records but didn't stay there for very long since the label soon ceased to exist due to financial
			problems. Instead we were picked up by English Rage of Achilles who released it almost instantly. The
			contract with Rage of Achilles also included a full-length and we started working on this one right after
			the release of the mCD. Very soon we bumped into both lack of motivation and disagreement of the
			direction of the music. This resulted in that me and Micce parted and I continued working on what would
			be "departure" all by myself. When the album after years of hard work was finally finished Rage of
			Achilles decided to quit due to financial problems. Lucky enough they helped me by getting in contact
			with a new label, Firebox, who were interested in releasing the album and that's pretty much were we are
			now.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			FOS is now a one-man-band, but it used to have more members. Do you think that FOS works better as a one-
			man-band, or are you planning on recruiting new members in the future?
		</p>
		<p>
			There are no plans of getting any new members but if someone shows up that I just can't turn down then I
			guess I would welcome that person. As it is right now I would say that Forest of Shadows works much
			better now than it used to do. Mainly because I can fulfill my musical visions without anyone else
			interfering.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The most important of your old members was Micce Anderson, who left in 2002. What was his place in the
			band, and why did he leave?
		</p>
		<p>
			He was the main instrumentalist and a pretty good one as well. It was a pretty hard job to substitute his
			departure and to some extent I can't say I really managed that well. He's also a schooled musican and he
			has alot of knowledge in how to make the best out of songs. This means that he was pretty much involved
			in the arrangements and more or less in charge of the recordings and mixings. Why he left was because he
			didn't share the same vision as I did. There was no way that we could pull of an album together that we
			both would have felt was perfectly done. At least we felt that way, or at least I felt that way. Another
			reason why we split up was that I moved from Gothenburg to Stockholm which made it more complicated to
			run the band together.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			FOS was one of the bands that were on Rage of Achilles' roster when it collapsed. What were your feelings
			when this happened?
		</p>
		<p>
			I was ofcourse very sad 'cause for a little while before Firebox showed up I thought that it also meant
			the end for "departure" and maybe even Forest of Shadows in the long run. It was also very sad since Rage
			of Achilles was a very interesting label on the rise that delivered music that felt fresh and far from
			normative. Unfortunatelly this is the reality for most underground labels no matter how good music they
			deliver.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you think that FOS' music will evolve in the future?
		</p>
		<p>
			Most likely away from the normative metal sound but still with the same dark and melodic core. It's very
			hard to predict what will really happen though. I just feel that it's hard to do anything new and fresh
			and still cling to the same old structures and just end up as another perfected clone.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What other plans do you have for the future of FOS?
		</p>
		<p>
			Nothing more than to keep on producing what I belive is good music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you think that could your music be presented in a live situation, and what would be the ideal
			situation for it?
		</p>
		<p>
			It could probably be pretty nice to see the songs performed live and I don't see it as a mission
			impossible. It would demand quite alot of members though and a certain atmosphere. The ideal situation
			would be a setup of seven or eight musicans who all know the songs by heart and can perform them with
			alot of emotion. Such a setup and a dramatic and mysterous place for the actual performance would be
			quite nice indeed.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Ok, I think that this is enough of questions. Any final words? Maybe a question I didn't ask, but you'd
			like to answer?
		</p>
		<p>
			I think you covered quite alot in this interview so I don't have much else to say. Thanx for a nice
			interview.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Ruben" zine="Eternal Terror" date="041206">
		<p type="question">
			Da jeg hørte Forest of Shadows sin debutfullengder for litt siden. Makan til perle av et album er det
			sjelden man kommer over og man måtte selvfølgelig finn ut mer om denne mannen og dette bandet! Jeg fikk
			beskjed om at det å få tak i denne mannen på telefon ikke var direkte lett, så det du leser her er gjort
			via e-mail. Oversettelse føler jeg er unødvendig siden det er på svensk og jeg føler at dere får hans
			svar framfor min oversetting når det gjøres slik. Uansett, kos dere med svarene fra Niclas Forhagen. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Gratulerer så mye med »Departure», der har du virkelig laget noe fantastisk!
		</p>
		<p>
			Tack så mycket
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Jeg regner med at responsen kun har vært positiv på denne plata? Hvor viktig føler du at responsen fra
			media er?
		</p>
		<p>
			Den är väldigt viktig. Både för mig själv och för bandets framtida utveckling och dess popularitet.
			Överlag tycker jag att responsen varit positiv men det finns även en del negativa inslag. Negativ respons
			kan vara bra för den kan peka på saker som verkligen behöver förbättras som man kanske inte tänkt på
			själv. Icke konstruktiv respons är mindre kul dock.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Kan du fortelle leserne om Forest of Shadows, hvordan det hele startet etc.?
		</p>
		<p>
			Bandet grundades i Halmstad 1997 som ett solo-project för att få utlopp för mina musikaliska visioner.
			Ungefär ett år senare och efter det att den första demon släppts gick Micce Andersson med i bandet.
			Tillsammans lyfte vi bandet från att vara ett obskyrt projekt till att bli ett mer kvalitativt och
			seriöst band. Vi spelade in två stycken promoskivor som cirkulerade på nätet och som blev väldigt
			populära och då främst på mp3.com. Så pass populära att de mer eller mindre såg till att vi fick
			skivkontrakt för mCD:n "where dreams turn to dust". Först blev vi kontrakterade av bolaget Molded Skull
			Records i USA men de hamnade i ekonomiska svårigheter och fick dra sig ur. Som ersättare dök engelska
			Rage of Achilles upp och räddade mCD:n. Vårt kontrakt med Rage of Achilles innefattade även en
			fullängdare som vi började jobba på direkt efter mCD:n. Till en början gick arbetet med denna skiva
			väldigt bra men allt eftersom så började mina och Micces åsikter om skivans stil och inriktning glida
			ifrån varandra och detta i takt med att motivationen avtog. Det hela slutade med att Micce lämnade bandet
			och att jag ensam spelade in skivan så som jag ville ha den. Detta visade sig bli en ganska segdragen och
			plågosam process som slutade med att Rage of Achilles hamnade i ekonomiska problem precis då skivan var
			klar för att släppas. Finska Firebox tog snabbt över ansvaret att släppa skivan och till slut, tre år
			senare kom "departure" ut.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Hvordan har så kreeringen av Departure foregått? Har du gjort om på mye etter at Micce forsvant?
		</p>
		<p>
			Det mest grundläggande i låtarna är detsamma som när Micce var med i bandet medan resten har blivit
			omgjort. Skivan gick totalt genom tre processer. Den första ägde rum ungeför samtidigt som mCD:n släpptes
			då vi tillsammans skrev mer eller mindre allt material. Ett halvår senare när vi skulle spela in det hela
			gav vi låtarna en rejäl ansiktslyftning och bytte ut en av låtarna mot instrumentala "bleak dormition".
			När Micce lämnade bandet blev det dags för den sista förändringen vilken också blev den största. Att
			prova låtarna i en massa olika arrangemang var väldigt nyttigt även om det till viss del tog död på de
			grundläggande ideérna.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Hvordan trives du med å holde på med Forest of Shadows for deg selv?
		</p>
		<p>
			Jag trivs väldigt bra i denna sits. Forest of Shadows har ju alltid varit mer eller mindre mitt band och
			det har bara varit väldigt jobbigt när andra har velat styra och ställa. Det fanns en tid då jag och
			Micce fungerade väldigt bra tillsammans men när den tiden tog slut så ville jag inget annat än att Forest
			of Shadows skulle bli mitt solo-projekt igen.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Du har valgt å spille melodiøs doom, hvorfor valgte du akkurat denne formen for musikk? Hvilke
			inspirasjonskilder har du?
		</p>
		<p>
			Jag har egentligen inte valt att spela "melodiös doom". Det råkar bara vara en av många musikstilar som
			jag tycker om och därför har den färgat min musik. När jag gör musik tänker jag inte i banor om att nu
			skall jag göra doom-metal utan jag gör bara vad som känns bra. Ibland blir det doom, ibland mer rockigt
			och ibland elektroniskt och avskalat. De band som inspirerar mig för tillfället är Cult of Luna, Isis,
			Shape of Despair, Anekdoten, Katatonia och Antimatter. Tidigare har Opeth, My Dying Bride och Anathema
			varit stora inspirationskällor och till viss del lever detta säkert kvar även om jag inte tänker på det.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Når jeg leste tekstene dine fikk jeg en følelse av at du har lest Aaron Stainthorpe fra My Dying Bride
			sine tekster, vil du påstå av han i noen grad har påvirket din måte å skrive tekster på? Er dette et band
			som har betydd noe for deg?
		</p>
		<p>
			My Dying Bride har betytt en väldigt massa för mig men jag har aldrig velat köpa deras koncept rakt av.
			Det finns säkert en hel del likheter mellan mina och Aarons texter men jag kan lova att det inte är
			avsiktligt. Jag har faktiskt inte läst hans texter så väldigt mycket trots att jag lyssnat på My Dying
			Bride en hel del under åren som gått. Anathema och Opeth har nog tilltalat mig mer vad gäller lyrik. Den
			största inspirationen till mina texter kommer dock ifrån "riktiga" poeter.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Din MCD kom på Firebox mens Departure kom på Firedoom, hva var det som gjorde at det ble slik?
		</p>
		<p>
			MCD:n kom på Rage of Achilles och inte på Firebox. Varför jag bytte från Rage of Achilles till
			Firebox/Firedoom var för att RoA fick problem med ekonomin och inte kunde släppa skivan.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Når jeg hadde hørt gjennom Departure en del ganger satt jeg igjen med en følelse av at du har latt deg
			bli inspirert av Antimatter/Massive Attack. Er dette noe du kan bekrefte eller er det bare tilfeldig? Hva
			er det så i tilfellet som gjør at du har blandet inn slik lett »industrielle» biter i musikken? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Visst har jag blivit inspirerad av band som Massive Attack, Antimatter, Portishead och liknande. De
			spelar ju faktiskt väldigt "doomy" musik så det kändes inte helt konstigt att nyttja denna inspiration i
			Forest of Shadows.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Har Forest of Shadows holdt noen konserter? Vil du eventuelt gjøre det i framtiden og hvordan vil du da
			gjøre det med folk? Har du noen faste live-session musikere?
		</p>
		<p>
			Vi gjorde två konserter 1999 och 2000 men de var inte speciellt lyckade. Under 2001 försökte vi sätt ihop
			ett band för att kunna göra fler och bättre spelningar men det hela rann ut i sanden. Därefter så har det
			inte funnits några tankar på att spela live igen. Men vem vet vad som händer i framtiden.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Har du noe nytt materiale klart? Hvordan er det eventuelt i forhold til det materialet vi finner på
			Departure?
		</p>
		<p>
			Det finns väldigt mycket material som bara ligger och väntar. Vad det blir av det återstår att se. Jag
			har en del planer men inga som är officiella. Det nya materialet kommer nog att fortsätta i samma
			riktning som "departure".
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Hva synes du om dagens doom scene? Det er jo sinnsykt mange nye og spennende band synes jeg og det er
			blitt utrolig høy kvalitet over mange av de siste utgivelsene, da spesielt med tanke på Firebox/Firedoom
			som spesielt har vist seg å være et selskap å holde øynene åpne for! Hva er dine kommentarer til dette?
		</p>
		<p>
			Jag är inte så insatt i doom scenen. Lyssnar mest på rå, primitiv och skitig musik. Dvs allt ifrån
			Darkthrone till Isis och Cult of Luna. Många doom band tenderar att bli allt för pretantiösa på ett
			dåligt sätt vilket förstör hela grejen. Ett doom band som är grymt bra är dock Shape of Despair. De har
			verkligen hittat ett grymt sound som är både unikt och tungt.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Har du noe avsluttende ord til våre lesere? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Jag skulle vilja ge ett stort tack till alla som stöttat Forest of Shadows på ett eller annat vis och nu
			eller i framtiden.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Jeg vil takke deg for at du har tatt deg tid til å svare på mine spørsmål og ikke minst for å ha laget
			årets beste Doom plate i form av Departure og lykke til videre med Forest of Shadows!!!
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Jan Fischer" zine="German Legacy Magazine" date="041204">
		<p type="question">
			What happened between the release of the mini-cd "When Dreams Turn To Dust" and your latest release
			"Departure"? What exactly happened to Rage Of Achilles?
		</p>
		<p>
			We started working on the material for "departure" even before the release of the mCD and it was
			initially scheduled for a release in early 2002. Even though there was very good progress in the
			beginning things soon came to a stall. We were both lacking motivation and there was some disagreement
			about what it all should sound like. Eventually, during the summer of 2002, we decided to get it all over
			with so we started recording. It didn't go very well and when I some month later moved from gothenburg to
			stockholm it all felt like it would never be finished. That was when I decided that I'd better try and
			finish it all by myself and thus Micce had to go. What happened then was a long process or rearranging
			the songs and learning how to play them, followed by a pretty long recording session that lasted for like
			a year until I was satisfied. When everything was recorded and ready to be released the worst I could
			imagine happened and that was that Rage of Achilles had to pull out because of financial problems. They
			helped me finding another label (Firebox) pretty quick though so the disaster didn't last very long.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your band has been in existence for some years now. Looking back, what would you have done differently?
		</p>
		<p>
			That's a tricky one. I mean I'm pretty satisfied with what has been accomplished so far and I don't know
			if there is anything that could have been done that would have improved the situation. Maybee it would
			have been for the best if the cooperation with Micce had ended some months earlier than it did 'cause in
			the end we didn't accomplish much of value together.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Seems like you are the only (constant) member of Forest Of Shadows. Why is that?
		</p>
		<p>
			Because I'm the sole founding member I guess. Forest of Shadows has always been my band to some extent
			and I guess I'm not the easiest person to cooperate with. At least not when it comes to personal things
			such as music. I guess that pretty much explains why there has been so many members coming and going.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who is the person on the inner cd cover? Any story connected to that? Looks like some randomly taken
			foto of some dictator...
		</p>
		<p>
			That's me, the bands dictator. Pretty funny actually since I have been acting like one while there has
			been other members in the band. I never thought of that when I inserted the photo though.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			On a typical Saturday evening, you ...
		</p>
		<p>
			...don't do much. Spend time with my girlfriend and dog. Play games, watch tv or some movie. Every now
			and then I go out for some beer with close friends or even attend to some concert but otherwise it's
			pretty laid back.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The music of Forest Of Shadows is dark and melancholic. There are a couple of other bands that play that
			or some similar style; Katatonia or Rapture come to mind. How do you perceive those bands and what
			distinguishes your music from theirs?
		</p>
		<p>
			I wouldn't say that they are that similar. There are ofcourse passages in my music that resembles these
			bands but generally speaking it's quite different. I do like them both though and they are some of the
			main influences when I write music. What distinguishes my music from theirs is, in my humble opinion, the
			song structures and the diversity. I would dare say that Forest of Shadows is more progressive while 
			Rapture and Katatonia stick to their special sound. Most likely that will be the case for Forest of
			Shadows as well one day.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the plans for the band? Will you stay with Firedoom Music? Will there ever be a tour outside of
			Sweden?
		</p>
		<p>
			The contract with Firedoom was only for the full-length so I don't really know what will happen there. I
			don't see any reason not to stick with Firedoom if they give me a new contract though. Apart from that I
			don't have any official plans right now. I trying to relax after the dramtic time with "departure" and
			gain some energy for the next release whatever that will be.
		</p>
		<p>
			There will not be any tour outside sweden or in sweden for that matter as it looks right now. I can't say
			if there will be one ever. The future will tell.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Something that people don't know about Stockholm but should know in your opinion?
		</p>
		<p>
			That we don't have icebears walking in the streets.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			When you hear your own music, what do you feel?
		</p>
		<p>
			Alot of things. It often brings back old memories of the time when the music was created. Most of the
			time I get a certain degree of satisfaction from what I have accomplished. There are actually few things
			apart from some details that I am feel ashamed of. I always find it strange to hear other musicans who
			can't bear to listen to their own music.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Fernando" zine="Dark Ritual" date="041205">
		<p type="question">
			How does it feel to release an album which the music and the lyrics were developed for the last seven
			years?
		</p>
		<p>
			It was actually just one of the songs that had been around for seven years. The other songs were born
			around the time when we released the mCD. Anyway, it feels really good to be able to add these songs to
			the bands history and focus on new material. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you find an identity on the whole record, or does it look to you more like a compilation of different
			songs, feelings and times?
		</p>
		<p>
			In some way you may say that there is a shared identity. I mean the lyrics are more or less about the
			same topic and the songs are composed and arranged as a unity. Still, the songs where written and
			arranged over a long period of time during which I have had lots of different sources of inspiration.
			It's a unity on the surface and more of a compilation on the inside.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where did you record all these tracks? Do you use your own studio?
		</p>
		<p>
			It was all recorded in my apartment in Stockholm. I don't know if I can say that I have a real studio
			there but I have enough equipment to be able to pull off a recording session. It's far from fancy and it
			sure restricts the quality of the album in terms of production but well, it works.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is owning a studio a good thing when you do doom metal music? I mean, is it necessary a kind of own
			private environment to perform and write this music at it's best?
		</p>
		<p>
			There are pros and cons of having a "studio" at home. The good thing about it is like you say the
			possibillity to record whenever you feel like it and when you feel inspired. The disadvantages are that
			you never leave your "work" which means that it's very easy to start overdoing stuff. It's also a
			problem that you can't record whenever you want to because of your neighbours.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You're alone in this project now. Advantages and disadvantages of working that way, please...
		</p>
		<p>
			The big advantage is that I can follow my visions and fulfill them without any interferance. It's also
			very nice to be able to decide when I want to work with Forest of Shadows or when I need to put it all on
			ice in order to be able to work on other things. The disadvantage is that it's very time consuming to do
			everything by yourself. It's also very hard to perform well on all instruments.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Again, does the fact that you work - compose and perform - alone enable you to achieve the right mood for
			doing this specific kind of music?
		</p>
		<p>
			Even when there were other members in the band I prefered to write everything by myself in solitude. It
			sure makes it easier to bring out that special mood. Performing alone is also pretty good since it's more
			relaxing. A bad thing about performing alone is that it's quite messy to handle the recordings and the
			instruments at the same time. It's also nice if someone else can judge whether or not the recordings are
			good.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Are you a naturally melancholic person, or does this project help you getting rid of that part of your
			personality and make you a somehow "happier" and "more sociable" person?
		</p>
		<p>
			Deep inside I don't think I'm more melancholic than anyone else. The big difference between me and the
			"happy" people is that I accept the fact that there is a melancholic side of me that I can't get rid of
			and thus have to live with. I don't know if I get "happier" by letting out my feelings or "more sociable"
			for that matter. Though, writing dark and depressive music is a way of accepting and revealing these
			parts of me and I guess that's a good thing for me as a person.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You mix not-so-usual elements in your music, as clean vocals and slight electronic elements on rhythms.
			How did you get to this style?
		</p>
		<p>
			I wouldn't say that clean vocals is that very avantgarde in the realms of extreme metal these days and
			actually not electronic elements either. Maybee I use them a bit more than others do which gives my music
			a certain character. Why I choose to add these elements is 'cause I thought they fit the compositions.
			When I compose music I don't really care if it's going to end up as old-school doom or electronica. I
			Just do what feels right. On the next release I might add even stranger elements or maybe I'll just go
			old-school. Who knows?
		</p>
		<p>
			How I got into clean vocals and electronica? Well, I actually listened to synth and pop-music before I
			got into metal so I guess I have it natural. I'm pretty far from a die-hard metal person. I like dark
			music that's all. I don't care if it's metal, rock, goth, pop, synth, electronica, trip-hop, indie or
			whatever.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What's your opinion about the usual puritists that will say this is not doom metal and that you should
			call your music something else?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm not the one that label my music "doom metal" so I'm not the one they should bark at. I totally agree
			that Forest of Shadows isn't a "true" doom-metal band. My opinion about these puritists is that they are
			rather pathetic that care more about a certain label than the actual music. And who are they to say what
			I am allowed to call my music or not. If these persons could stop being so narrowminded they would
			probaly discover that there is alot of "doomy" bands out there apart from the puristic ones.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do your inspiration - for music and lyrics - come naturally, when you want, or do you have to be with a
			special feeling to allow these things to come to you?
		</p>
		<p>
			It just comes, regardless if I want to or not, if I'm in some kind of emotional state. Listening to new
			fresh music adds alot to the inspiration as well. To get inspiration for arranging and producing music is
			pretty easy and I don't even have to be in a special mood for that. The difficult one is the basic
			harmonies and melodies as well as the lyrics.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have any kind of technique - or quimical help - to allow the inspiration to come?
		</p>
		<p>
			For lyrics it might help to read books and other bands lyrics. For music I just need some solitude with
			my piano or guitar and I sooner or later will come up with something.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You do have other musical projects, right? Which ones are you doing these days, and how do you split your
			time between them?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, there are some other project in which I am involved but most of them are on ice right now. First of
			all there is "Ningizzia" which invloves me and Stephane Peudupin. I have spent alot of time with this
			band during the years. For periods I worked 50-50 with Forest of Shadows and Ningizzia. Ningizzia is also
			quite similar to Forest of Shadows but a bit more diverse. Then there is Shubend (/Genesis of Pain) which
			used to be a rehearsing band with five members when I lived in Gothenburg. After I moved I haven't spent
			much time with this band apart from writing some lyrics every now and then. Shubend isn't similar to
			Forest of Shadows at all apart from the fact that I'm doing the vocals. It's more of a technical
			thrash/death band.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You drawn a logo to Sweet Flame, from Portugal. Do you know anything further from the Portuguese scene?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not very much. I used to listen to Moonspell quite alot but I guess that's all. I'm not that well
			oriented in the metal scene these days no matter which country it concerns apart from the scandinavian
			countries.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Andi" zine="Shadowshire" date="041204">
		<p type="question">
			Hei Niclas, how are you?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm pretty fine thanx. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Can you give us a short overview about yourself as a person and about your musical work with Forest Of
			Shadows?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, I'm 29 years old and living in Stockholm, Sweden together with my girlfriend and dog. I have a
			masters degree in computer science and work as a programmer/sound director at a game developer. Forest of
			Shadows has been a project of mine to satisfy the aestetic side of me and it has moved through alot of
			phases during the year ranging from solo-project to five-piece band. The style and direction has always
			been the same though and will probably always be.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			It has happened again: The press lavishes you on doxologies. Did you expect this positive response? How
			does that feel?
		</p>
		<p>
			It's ofcourse very nice to know that people appreciate my work. A part of me didn't expect this response
			since the music contains alot of elements that lies far from the genres normative. But I'm glad that my
			fans aren't as narrowminded as I had feared. I guess that's what makes me most happy. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How did you get in contact with Firedoom?
		</p>
		<p>
			When Rage of Achilles closed down, Duncan, their manager, helped me out to get a new contract with
			another label. He knew Rami at Firebox since they had been distributing Rage of Achilles albums in
			Finland and he introduced Forest of Shadows to him. Rami got interested and we soon inked a deal. Some
			month later Rami started Firedoom as a subdivision to Firebox and let Forest of Shadows be one of the
			first bands to release anything on this label. I felt very honoured.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I read that the work on "Departure" took three years. Why?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, me and former member Micce spent about a year to try and produce the album and it didn't go very
			well for various reasons where the main one was that we couldn't agree about what the album should sound
			like. It all ended up with Micce leaving the band and I had to finish the production by myself. Since I
			wasn't satisfied with the arrangements I redid them all which took quite some time. Then I had to learn
			to play everything which was quite hard since Micce had been the main instrumentalist in the band. I also
			had to spend alot of time messing around with the sound to get everything sounding the way I wanted it to
			sound. So it took quite alot of time.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How was it - working together with Mika Jussila?
		</p>
		<p>
			I didn't really work with Mika. I just sent him the material and he added some final touches based on a
			wishlist I had made. Unfortuantelly he managed to push the levels a bit too much which resulted in some
			unwanted distortions. Apart from that I think he did a good job.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What inspires you when you're writing songs?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't know. Different emotional states, personal experiences and stuff like that. I don't get that
			inspired by other peoples work, well not on a low level anyway. It's really hard to know what actually
			causes your musical visions. They just come.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have a stable line up when you're producing an album?
		</p>
		<p>
			No. There has always been people coming and going during the producitons. The only one where that didn't
			happen was the '99 promo aka "The Silent Cry".
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The live realisation: How do you plan to do that? Up to now you're a one man project.
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't. It would have been fun to perform the songs live but as it is right now I don't see that
			happening ever. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			When you wrote "Departure", what have been your influences. (I can't help but sometimes it remembers me
			of Massive Attack's "Mezzanine".)
		</p>
		<p>
			I've been inspired by Massive Attack, Portishead and Earthling and stuff like that. They're not my main
			sources of inspirations but they sure added a certain touch to the sound. The more important bands that
			influenced the produciton was: Cult of Luna, Isis, Katatonia, Anekdoten and Shape of Despair.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The response to "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" has been very positiv some years ago. Regarding to that, was
			it difficult to try to top that?
		</p>
		<p>
			Departure is not an attempt to top that album. It's a different album with different values and should be
			regarded as such. Of course I tried to write better lyrics and better music as well as giving it all a
			better performance. If I succeeded or not is very personal. I think it's better album but I guess alot of
			people would sy the opposite. For some reason people have a way of clinging onto the old material. There
			are even people who think that the first demo marks the peak of Forest of Shadows career. And why not?
			I'm the kind of person myself who think that alot of bands did their best stuff on their first albums
			even though their later material is far better in many way. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You have another band called "Shubend", haven't you? Tell us what's behind it!
		</p>
		<p>
			I used to do the vocals in a band called Shubend. I'm saying "used to" since the band has more or less
			ceased to exist. We recorded our swansong album some months ago and are still trying to get it released
			in some way. Previous to that we had released one full-length "Synergism" and two demos "Singularis" and
			"Hook, Line and Sinker". Be warned though. Shubend is not very similar to Forest of Shadows at all. It's
			more of a technical thrash/death band. The only thing that unites the bands are the fact that I do the
			vocals in them both.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Music seems to be very important to you - what else is important to you, apart from music?
		</p>
		<p>
			My close ones. Without any competition. Apart from that I'm I would say movies and visual art.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What can we expect next from you? Any plans?
		</p>
		<p>
			There are some plans but I don't want to make them official yet.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Alex Straka" zine="Powermetal.de" date="041105">
		<p type="question">
			Hi Niclas! First of all tell me about your inner life. "Departure" is blasting by an unbelievable
			sadness. Are you ok?
		</p>
		<p>
			Concerning my inner life I would like to keep that private. I hope you respect that. Anyways, I'm not as
			down and depressed as you might get the illusion of from the album. You know, in order to make
			melancholic music you don't have to be melancholic. You just need to have a dark and twisted mind. It
			helps though if you know what it's like to be down and belive me I do know what that's like.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			FOREST OF SHADOWS has a history full of changes of the line-up. Now you act alone. Tell me about please.
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, I guess I'm rather hard to work with at least if you want to change the direction of my music. I
			guess it all comes down to that I started the band as my solo-project and thus I will always consider it
			my band. Not very democratic I know. Being the only member, as it is right now, has its pros and cons. On
			the negative side lies the fact that I need to do everything by myself which is very time consuming and
			restricting. Still, this is something I can live with at the cost of having full control not only over
			the music and visual artworks but also when and how I am to work with FOREST OF SHADOWS. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How you create your songs? This almighty melancholy needs a special daily form or?
		</p>
		<p>
			Writing lyrics and the basic harmonies and melodies do need a certain daily form, a less happy one. The
			rest can be done whenever. I know pretty well how I want it to sound.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The songs of "Departure" are not the newest ones. What´s the reason, you can record the album not
			earlier?
		</p>
		<p>
			Correction: The songs on "departure" are the newest ones. Well, apart from "november dream" which is an
			old demo song from 1997. Still, this remake differs quite alot from the original so it might as well be
			considered a new song. Why I, or actually we (Micce was also in the band we took the decision), choose to
			include "november dream" on the album is because it's a good song that deserves a better destiny than the
			shitty one it got by ending up on the first demo, a demo that was far from well produced.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you await now from the release of "Departure", in my opinion a masterpiece of doomy dark metal?
		</p>
		<p>
			Masterpiece of doomy dark metal. Now that's a nice compliment. What I await from the new album? I don't
			know actually. Guess I'm more than happy if people just like it. I'm not really expecting a grammy or
			anything :)
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			There are enough doom metal bands around the world. But on "Departure" rules the highest score of
			intensity I´ve ever heared. Forced by the continued setlist, you play often with the levels, with
			loudness and silence. Added the variance of your vocals, FOREST OF SHADOWS sounds very similary. The only
			band you compare I think is WHILE HEAVEN WEPT from the states. What do you think about this?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't know much about WHILE HEAVEN WEPT but I guess I heard them once and since I didn't remember them
			all that well I assume they didn't sound that similar to FOREST OF SHADOWS. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Niclas, you are songwriter, arrangeur, producer, mixer, engineer and creative master in personal union.
			Too much time ;-)? What´s the reason you make these jobs alone?
		</p>
		<p>
			If there's something I don't have then it's too much time. My health is actually pretty worn down by
			being involoved in three bands while working and trying maintain a social life. Still, I really value
			being involved in as much as possible when it comes to FOREST OF SHADOWS no matter if it's writing music,
			performing it or doing graphical works for booklets or websites. I guess the main reason is that every
			time that I have involved other people it has ended up with them wanting to change things and forming the
			band into something I can't relate to. I might be an egocentric dictator but FOREST OF SHADOWS means too
			much for me and I don't see any point in keeping the band alive if I can't realte to it 100%. After all
			it's band I formed to express my own musical visions. If I found people to work with that would be
			willing to just obey my orders then I might consider working with them but otherwise I rather do it all
			by myself no matter if it all takes alot more time and lacks of technical quality.  
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Please tell me about the recordings of the album. At final "Departure" was mastered by Mr. Jussila at
			Finnvox, right? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, it was actually recorded two times. One with Micce as a member of the band and one after he had
			left. We started out writing new material even before the mCD was released and had the basic structures
			of all songs to be included in the original tracklist finished some month later. Then we entered a pretty
			uncreative and less motivating phase of finalizing the songs. The main reason to this was that we had big
			problems with merging our visions of what the final material should be like. We didn't work on the
			material on a daily basis, not even a weekly. After a while we started to grow tired of it all and
			decided to do something about it. So we started doing the final recordings. The first step was to record
			the drums and we did this in a small studio called NoiseLab that some friends of mine used to have. The
			three days we spent in the studio were filled with all kinds of problems and we almost gave up on the
			second day. Finally we managed to pull it all together though but the result wasn't very satisfying.
			After some weeks of trying to make it sound good we finally abandoned the drum recordings and replaced
			them with programmed ones. This failure had quite an impact on the rest of the recordings and soon it was
			progressing at snailpace again. When I decided to move from Gothenburg to Stockholm some month later I
			started to realize that the only way this album would be finished would be if either me or Micce did it
			seperatelly since the distance geographically and in musical visions was to big. So unfortuatelly Micce
			had to go. Loosing Micce wasn't easy though since he was the main musican in the band. I had to spend
			alot of time learning how to play the stuff before I could start recording it. It took a year and a half
			until it was all recorded and mixed and ready to be sent to mr Jussila. Mr Jussila did a pretty good job
			I must say even though the levels were pushed a bit too far at some places which produced unwanted
			distortions.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The complete conception (music, photos, artwork etc.) of FOREST OF SHADOWS is focussed on your dark,
			hopeless and sad lyrics. How much time you invest in your project. It sounds like your whole soul ;-).
		</p>
		<p>
			When I started Forest of Shadows I wanted to start a band that was dark and melancholic in a unified way.
			I was kind of irritated at bands that couldn't match their dark music with equally dark lyrics and
			artworks. I'm not saying that I'm the ultimate artist but at least my vision were and is to create art
			that is as dark and melancholic as possible in all possible ways. I guess alot of bands are scared of
			being labeled pretentious or pathetic and thus doesn't go all the way with their dark and melancholic
			art. Or maybee they just have bad taste :) To answer that last question I do spend my entire soul, at
			least the dark side of it, in my music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Have you any other material to record in the near future?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yes, I have lots. I'm in a rather busy phase of my life right now though so I haven't been able to work
			much with this new material. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is FOREST OF SHADOWS a studio project or do you come over with a band at short time?
		</p>
		<p>
			Right now it's as much studio project as it possibly can get. So don't expect any live performances.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Niclas, why our readers must know FOREST OF SHADOWS?
		</p>
		<p>
			If you're into dark and melancholic music you might find something in Forest of Shadows but if not then
			you might be better of not knowing about Forest of Shadows at all. I really don't think that my music
			suits the average metalhead.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			At last a personal question. What do you think is the meaning of life and what is the aim in your life?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't think there is a certain meaning of life generally speaking apart from the one you create by
			yourself. Some people that can handle this fact try to find a meaning in supernatural beliefs of all
			kinds but I rather not. I don't know if I have a ceratin aim in life apart from trying to live in
			harmony with myself and my close ones.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Niclas, thanx for the intie. I wish you all the best with "Departure", an album full of soul and
			heartblood. Any last words for our readers?
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanx for interview Alex and thanx to all you readers for reading the interview. 
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Olivier (Zoltar) Badin" zine="Hard'n'Heavy" date="041108">
		<p type="question">
			Is there any specific reference behind the name of the band?
		</p>
		<p>
			No, I wouldn't say there is. It was just a name that I came up with. Later on I tried to give a meaning
			but initially there was none.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Was at first FOREST OF SHADOWS meant to be a band or was it right from the start bound to be just a
			personal project?
		</p>
		<p>
			When I started Forest of Shadows I did it just for the fun of it. Ofcourse I wanted it to be something
			more than just a personal project but I didn't expect that to happen. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you differ FOS from your other musical projects?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, FOS is my first and most personal band and thus I put more of myself into it than the other ones.
			There were periods though when I felt that I couldn't express all my musical visions because of the other
			members in the band. During these periods NINGIZZIA, another band of mine, became the band in which I
			could express myself freely. At an early stage there wasn't much difference between the musical visions
			of these two bands so if I had an idea and it wasn't welcome in one of the bands then I just tried it out
			in the other one. The third project that I assume you have in mind is the thrash/death band SHUBEND. This
			band differs quite alot from the other two and it was more of a band that I was in than a band that I
			lived for. After all I only did the lyrics, well not only since I put quite alot of energy and thought
			behind them.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Now with a step back, would you say that ´Where Dreams Trun To Dustª was then a good representation of
			FOS or was an unacheived one?
		</p>
		<p>
			It was definatelly a good representation of FOS at that time even though it could have been done much
			better. I mean you have to consider that it was done under very poor circumstances. Technically there's
			also quite alot to wish for but well, that was then and now is now. I'm still very proud of that release
			and the popularity it achived. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Did you settled right from the start on writing very long and epic tracks?
		</p>
		<p>
			I have always been fond of long and epic tracks and I like things to last for more than just a few
			minutes. When I write a song I don't focus on making it long and epic. That's just something that
			happens.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Were you bothered by the tag of being just another early KATATONIA clone?!
		</p>
		<p>
			I never heard that we were a KATATONIA clone and I really don't think that we sound much like them. No
			matter what I could be offended by much worse things so I really don't care.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why was it so difficult to write the follow-up to this mini CD?
		</p>
		<p>
			The actual composition of the material wasn't that hard. Most of the melodies and structures were there
			just a few month after the release of the mCD. What took time was when we started to get into the details
			of it all. Our visions didn't really point in the same direction and the material meant too much for both
			of us. Making sacrifices wasn't really an option. After some time of struggling we started to grow tired
			of it all and more or less just wanted it to be over and done with. This didn't speed up things though.
			It was first when I decided that the only solution was that I made it all by myself that things started
			moving. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			´Departureª seems to be strangely estranged between funeral doom and dark trip-hop. Do you agree?
		</p>
		<p>
			To some extent yes. I mean it shows some of the outer boundaries of the music. It's not very fair to
			describe the music with just these two styles. There's so much more involved. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Did you get inspired by MASSIVE ATTACK's ´Tear Dropª in order to write ´Sleeping Deathª?
		</p>
		<p>
			I might have got some inspiration from MASSIVE ATTACK but not from the song "Tear Drop". They have done
			far doomier songs than that one. Actually, the part that you are refering to wasn't supposed to sound the
			way it does initially. It wasn't even meant to have any elements of electronica at all. I guess I was
			very inspired by electronica (and trip-hop if you prefer) when I rearranged that song. I'm really happy
			about what I did since it gives the song some extra character.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is ´Departureª only focusing only how to deal with the loss of the loved ones?
		</p>
		<p>
			That would be the obvious intepretation but there's more to it. I would say it's more about leaving or be
			left on an abstract plane. It could be about death, it could be about breaking up, it could be about
			moving on in life or whatever you want. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why this album is a mix of newer and older songs, some written in the very early stage of FOS?
		</p>
		<p>
			I have promised myself and some of my fans that the songs that were recorded on the early demos should
			get released properly in due time. I started with "November Dream" on this album and will include another
			one of the demo songs on the next release. It's not only about principles but also about the fact that I
			really like these old songs and want to give them a better destiny than the horrible one they got on the
			demo.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Were you influenced by the extreme doom scene?!
		</p>
		<p>
			A little bit maybee. I can't say that there are that many bands to get inspried from in the extreme doom
			scene any more. The only ones I can come to think of are Shape of Despair, Evoken and Funeral Orchestra.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you see yourself more as a melancolic or as a depressive personne? And how did it affected
			´Departureª?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't see myself as melancholic or depressive. There were times when I sure did and I guess that will
			always affect my music to some extent. Most of the stuff on "Departure" was written during these
			depressive moments and I guess that made them to what they are. I don't belive that you have to be
			depressive to write true depressive music though. It's more about knowing what it's like. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Final last words?!
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanx for the interview and stay doomed
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Christophe" zine="Innate" date="041107">
		<p type="question">
			Hello guys ! How are you by now having a new album released so far?
		</p>
		<p>
			Hey Innate. The release of the new album is going just fine. So far I haven't read anything negative
			about it apart from some small details. This is kind of interessting since it's far from a normative
			metal album or doom-metal album for that matter. I guess the audience is less narrowminded these days
			which is rather nice.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Staying in the past can you remember for us how it all began? In which bands were ou playing before
			creating this new act?
		</p>
		<p>
			It all began in 1997 as a solo-project of mine. I had no experience from any other bands before this
			date. My only experience was that I had been making quite alot of electronic music on the computer.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where Dreams Turns To Dust was released by Rage Of Achilles, why did you decided to not continue with
			this label? 
		</p>
		<p>
			They were supposed to release the full-length but couldn't because of financial problems so there wasn't
			much of a choice but to turn to another label and in this case the Finnish label Firebox/Firedoom. I was
			very satisfied with Rage of Achilles and I had never any plans to turn to another label. Still, I'm very
			lucky that I ended up at Firebox/Firedoom since they are more oriented towards the kind of music that
			Forest of Shadows play.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			In 2002 Micce Anderson left the band, what was exactly his implication in Departure ? Was it a hard
			situation to continue without him?
		</p>
		<p>
			Even though all the songs were rearranged quite alot after Micce's departure he still contributed to very
			much of what you hear on the album. Micce is a very talented person in many ways an he brought alot of
			key elements to the album. While in the band, Micce was responsible for most of the instruments which
			made things rather complicated after he left. Even though the music isn't very technical it was technical
			enough to make the recording sessions a major pain in the ass for me. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			This new album was a long work and your biography says that it was rewritten 3 times. Can you explain us
			why?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, me and Micce started working on the material around the time when the mCD was released. It didn't
			take us very long to have the basic ideas arranged but when we started to get into the details we soon
			ran out of motivation. We started to work on the material more seldom and the span of time between our
			sessions increased. When we were getting close to the final recording sessions we both felt (I guess)
			that we weren't all that satisfied with what we had accomplished in terms of the arrangements. This was
			also the beginning of the end of our cooperation since we had different ideas of how to arrange it all.
			Still we managed to rewrite it all before we were supposed to record it. In the middle of the recording
			session Micce left the band and I had to complete it all by myself. Since I felt that most of the things
			had to be rerecorded anyway I thought that I might as well rewrite it all the way I wanted it. Can't say
			that it was an optimal way of putting together an album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Was it important to rewrite things? Do you believe that the same « head » can have 3 different ways to
			write things?
		</p>
		<p>
			Due to the circumstances I belive that every rearrangement was of importance. I belive that you can
			rewrite things more than 3 times. There is always room for improvements. The danger of rewriting is that
			you tend to drift away from the basic idea of the song. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The usual affirmation is that the upcoming cd is always better than the previous one. Don't you think
			it's a bit annoying to hear that from musicians each time?
		</p>
		<p>
			Whatever someone says about his/hers work is their bussiniess. I don't find it annoying at all. I mean if
			you don't belive that you are getting any better then there isn't much point in going on, is there? At
			least not with the same band. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Actually is the label of Doom music correct for you? According to all the elements on the stuff is there
			not another way to describe Forest Of Shadows?
		</p>
		<p>
			Just like most other musicans I really don't like to put a label on my music. And if I had to then I
			wouldn't say it's doom. There are doomy elements in the music of Forest of Shadows but there is also so
			much more. Dark metal or just metal would suit much better since they are both more abstract. I actually
			don't like to be labeled metal either since it connects my music with music that is pretty far from what
			I create but I guess I have to live with that as long as I use distorted guitars and heavy drums.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I suppose you have others interests than music in life, can you tell us what you love to do when you are
			not playing or working for the band?
		</p>
		<p>
			Music isn't really my work. It's actually pretty far from it which means that music is more what I love
			to do when I'm not working or maintaining my social life.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Metal music is always having new fashions coming and going, for you will it be always like this with new
			styles that are supposed to come again and again?
		</p>
		<p>
			There will always be good albums that will insprire and be a part of the current fashion. Some sources of
			inspiration run dry pretty fast while other can last for ages.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			For years black, thrash, death, heavy metal fans seemed divided in their categories, do you have the
			impression this fact is evolving with time?
		</p>
		<p>
			Evolving towards what? I do belive that they are drifting apart and that's nothing I care the least
			about. The only thing some of the bands in the different genres share in common is he fact that they use
			guitars and drums.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			For you what are the 10 most importants cds in metal history? The ones each new metal fan can't
			understand to metal without knowing it?
		</p>
		<p>
			To me the 10 most important metal albums are the following	(in no particular order).
		</p>
		<p>
			Opeth - "Morningrise", Anathema - "The Silent Enigma", Katatonia - "Brave Murder Day", Cult of Luna -
			"The Beyond", Shape of Despair - "Shades of...", Katatonia - "Last Fair Deal Gone Down", My Dying Bride -
			"Turn Loose the Swans", Opeth - "Blackwater Park", Theatre of Tragedy - "Velvet Darkness They Fear" and
			Celestial Season - "Solar Lovers".
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Innate is based in France, so i would like to have your opinion on our scene there. Do you know so much
			bands from our country? Labels? Magazines?
		</p>
		<p>
			I own a couple of albums by Misanthrope and other Holy Recs bands I find them all quite good. Apart from
			that I know Despond, which is a pretty good doom band. The man behind Despond, Richard, is also running
			the frensh label Haceldama with a friend of mind, Stephane. Me and Stephane is having a band together
			called Ningizzia. Ningizzia released a demo thru Impaler of Trendies once upon a time which is the third
			frensh label I know, or knew. Regarding magazines I can't say that I know any at all. Stephane and Max
			(of Impaler of Trendies) used to run a zine called Ocean Morphique that I also did some graphics for but
			that pretty much it.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you feel that the politic in general, the world's situation of today is a thing you are caring about?
			If yes which movements are at the moment the ones you are agreeing with?
		</p>
		<p>
			I care quite alot both about politics and the situation of the world but I do it as a private person and
			not a musician. Well, at least that's the case with Forest of Shadows. I have written some lyrics with
			the bands Shubend and Genesis of Pain that are quite political but in an abstract way. I'm not the kind
			of person who want to belong to a certain movement or idea and I sure don't want Forest of Shadows to be
			a political band.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What are the expectations for the band on your personal level?
		</p>
		<p>
			Not much. I expect only to be able to keep releasing albums as long as I am worthy of doing so.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			To end the discussion do you think we had forgot something important to talk about? A last word to the
			readers?
		</p>
		<p>
			Check out the new album "departure" and give it a few listenings. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Your wishes for 2004???
		</p>
		<p>
			That "departure" continues being well received and gets good critics. 
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Martin Lazarte Castro" zine="Explosion Cerebral Zine" date="040504">
		<p type="question">
			Can you make a brief story of the band's beginning?
		</p>
		<p>
			The band was formed back in 1997 with me as the only member. I recorded the demo "The Silent Cry" in 1998
			which despite of it's horrible production came to interest multiinstrumentalist Micce Andersson who
			joined the band shortly there after. We did a promo-cd in early 1999 titled "The Silent Cry", mostly
			because it featured a remake of the old demo song. One may also say that it was a silent cry to some
			labels that we wanted to work with :) During 2000 we recorded yet another promo with yet another remake
			called "Under the Dying Sun". The two remakes were uploaded to mp3.com and gained increasing popularity.
			In the meantime we teamed up with Martin Claesson on guitar and started rehearsing with ambitions of
			becoming a live band. Two less successfull gigs later we dropped this ambition and ended the cooperation
			with Martin some month later. Instead of being a live band we became a 100% studio band and started
			working on a new demo right away which ended up in the mCD "Where Dreams Turn To Dust". With this new
			album and the growing popularity on mp3.com we started attracting record companies and in 2001 we signed
			with Rage of Achilles. The deal included a release of the mCD (previously demo) "Where Dreams Turn To
			Dust" and a full-length. While the mCD had been recorded pretty quick the full-length evolved very slow
			even though the material was more or less there as we signed the deal with Rage of Achilles. During this
			slow progress me and Micce started drifting apart and one day I realized that there was no way we could
			do this new album together and make it good so despite his importance to the band Micce had to leave.
			Even though the full-length was already delayed I decided to redo it all from scratch in order to make it
			all the way I wanted it. And this is what I'm still doing even though I am reaching completion now.  
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who is responsible for music and lyrics on the band?
		</p>
		<p>
			With me as the only member I guess the answer is pretty simple :) When Micce was in the band he was
			pretty involved in the music but I guess I have had the main responsibillity all the time.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where do you get inspiration for your lyrics?
		</p>
		<p>
			Poetry, other doomy lyrics, life, death... from everywhere and nowhere.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What shows have you played that stood out in your mind? 
		</p>
		<p>
			None I guess...
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			If you were able to obtain immortality, how would you put to use it advantages?
		</p>
		<p>
			By being (or trying to be) an artist I do become immortal in some non-material sense. Anyway, if I would
			have been immortal, physically, then I guess I would have tormented people forever and ever with my music
			:) Honestly, I don't see that many advantages with being immortal if everone I love is mortal... 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you think about religion, do you think that religion is a dangerous element in mankind's life,
			why?
		</p>
		<p>
			I think that everyone has a right to their own belief no matter what it is. Individual beliefs are pretty
			harmless I would say but big collective religions are quite the opposite. Religion can be the most lethal
			weapon to mankind but also a saviour. I guess the main problem isn't religion in itself but people more
			or less forcing others to think and act in a certain way. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Tell me about the band's musical diversity. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, what can I say. A one way lane will make me insane :) 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What do you know of Peru or Southamerica?
		</p>
		<p>
			Apart from the geography and that there is alot of problems of various kinds I don't know too much. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have any new release, are you working with a new label, how are you promoting your band?
		</p>
		<p>
			I am and have been working on a full-length since late 2000. It will most likely be finished sometime
			during early 2004. I am still working with Rage of Achilles and I have no plans of contacting any other
			label. I don't promote the band apart from having a website.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have any interest in occultism, will you practice any ritual, why?
		</p>
		<p>
			I sure am interested and fascinated by occultism but I don't practice anything or belong to any
			group/sects/movement/circle/whatever.  
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Any future plan?
		</p>
		<p>
			To finish the full-length which is more or less killing me...
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Any last comment?
		</p>
		<p>
			Check out the full-length when it's finished. I hope it won't disappoint you.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="André Groeneveld" zine="Quintessence" date="031217">
		<p type="question">
			Hello Niclas, thanks for doing an interview with us. Could you first introduce Forest Of Shadows to us?
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows is a band devoted to the darker kinds of music. The band was founded in 1997 and has
			released 5 demos/promos where the final one resulted in a deal with English Rage of Achilles who released
			this demo as a mCD. The deal also included a full-length which currently is being finialized and will be
			titled "departure".
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Forest Of Shadows started as a solo project and the idea of playing live resulted in searching and
			finding other musicians. How does it come why there were no other musicians when you started this band?
			Was it hard to find them or were the ones you know not interested?
		</p>
		<p>
			When I founded the band I lived in a pretty small town and I really had no hope of finding anyone who
			would share my musical visions. Especially since I hardly knew anyone there who was into metal music at
			all. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Did you play in other bands at that time? What about now, do you play in other bands at the moment or is
			Forest Of Shadows your main focus?
		</p>
		<p>
			Back then when I started the band I had just ended a hopeless attempt of putting a band together with
			some friends and that failure was partly the reason why I founded Forest of Shadows. Some months after I
			founded Forest of Shadows I founded the band Ningizzia with my friend Stephane and we are still active
			even though there isn't much happening right now. Another band that I am involved in is Shubend and we
			are currently working on a new full-length. Forest of Shadows is definitely my main focus though.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who are the musicians at the moment? I know that there were a lot of changes in the past. Are you still
			searching for other musicians?
		</p>
		<p>
			I'm the only musician in the band right now and I'm not searching for another memeber at the moment.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How would you describe your music for the people who don't know your band? To me it seems that you have
			been influenced by bands like Opeth, Katatonia (On Brave Murder Day) and even My Dying Bride. Do you
			agree with that? Do you like this style of music? 
		</p>
		<p>
			You could probably find elements in the music of Forest of Shadows that hint at these three bands and
			they are all big influences. It would be a lie to say anything else. Still, there are so many other bands
			that inspire like for instance Shape of Despair, Cult of Luna, Anathema, Anekdoten and of course the late
			Katatonia. And yes, I do like the style, not that all of these bands are of similar style but well, they
			all do pretty dark and melancholic music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Like bands in this genre, you're lyrics are full of emotion. Are they based on real life or just fiction? What can you tell me about it?
		</p>
		<p>
			There may be some hints in the lyrics at stuff that has actually happened in real life but most of it is
			just fiction so don't take it to serious. I don't think you have to be sad or depressed in order to make
			dark music. You just have to like it. It's similar with lyrics. I would say that if you are really
			depressed then you don't have any energy to make any music or lyrics at all. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You made 4 promo's in the past if I'm correct. Only after the 2000 promo "Where Dreams Turned To Dust"
			you have been picked up by Rage Of Achilles. They also re-released the promo. Why did it took so long to
			find a label? Where they not interested?
		</p>
		<p>
			I guess we weren't good enough both as a band and at sending promos to labels. The few labels that we
			actually did contact were obviously not interested.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I'm not familiar with the first 2 promo's. Do they sound like the 1999 en 2000 promo or something
			different? Could you tell me something more about them? Do you have the intention to re-release them in
			the future as a bonus? I think that there will be some interest in that material.
		</p>
		<p>
			I know that alot of people want these early recordings and I do get alot of mail about this but I have no
			intention of re-releasing them at least not in their original shape. I mean they are just early versions
			of songs  that deserve far better and they will be (and in some cases have been) released.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You have plans to release an album in 2003. What can you tell me about it? Is it a further development
			from the latest MCD? When will it be released?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, it will actually be released in 2004 since it has been pretty much delayed. The songs will be in
			the same vein as the mCD but with much more variation and diversity. It will have passages that are more
			aggressive than anything done by FoS before but it will also have some pretty soft passages. Overall, the
			atmosphere is more dark and emotional than before so hopefully the new elements will be appreciated.
			There is already samples and lyrics on the website for thoose who can't wait. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have any plans for the future? Any touring plans or just see what happens?
		</p>
		<p>
			As it is right now my only plan is to get this full-length finished 'cause it's killing me.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			That's it, thanks for your time. Anything more to add to this interview?
		</p>
		<p>
			Thanks for the interview and do check out the new album when it's out...
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Jens" zine="Walls of Fire" date="021020">
		<p type="question">
			Wieso arbeitet ihr als Duo mit Session Musikern und habt keine festen Mitglieder für die Band rekrutiert?
		</p>
		<p>
			Dafür gibt es mehrere Gründe. Wir haben uns nach Musikern umgesehen, aber richtig geklappt hat es nie,
			entweder wegen mir oder wegen Micce. Mit mir und Micce kann man nur schwer arbeiten, und ich glaube, dass
			das der Grund ist, warum es zwischen uns nicht geklappt hat. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Was kannst du mir über die Vergangenheit der Band erzählen? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Das war schon eine sehr harte Zeit, wegen den vielen Wechseln im Line-Up und anderen Sachen wie Probleme
			mit Aufnahmen, Labels und Vertrieben. Es gab aber auch schöne Zeiten, zum Beispiel als wir bei mp3.com an
			der Spitze waren und viel Geld verdienten (jaaa, ich bin ein gieriger Bastard). Der Tag, an dem unsere
			MCD erschien war auch ein großartiger Tag. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Wieso hat es so lange gedauert, bis ihr endlich einen Plattenvertrag unterschrieben hattet? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Wir haben nicht viele Demos an Zines und Labels geschickt und ich denke, wir müssen uns selbst dafür die
			Schuld geben, dass wir nicht früher gesignt wurden. Wir sind bei einem Label vor Rage Of Achilles
			untergekommen, dass aber wegen finanzieller Probleme dicht machte. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Wieso habt ihr euer Demo aus dem Jahr 2000 wiederveröffentlicht? Hattet ihr nicht genügend Material, das
			man stattdessen hätte veröffentlichen können? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Das Demo, dass 2000 aufgenommen wurde, war ursprünglich als MCD gedacht. Wir hatten große Hoffnungen,
			dass wir ein Label finden würden, dass es im Herbst 2000 noch veröffentlichen würde. Aber leider hatten
			sich die Dinge nicht so entwickelt. Als wir bei Rage of Achilles unterschrieben, hatten wir genug
			Material, aber wir wollten einfach die MCD veröffentlichen. Und Rage of Achilles hielten das ebenfalls
			für eine gute Idee. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Wo seht ihr musikalische Einflüsse auf euren Sound? 
		</p>
		<p>
			In anderen Bands, Metal- und Nicht-Metal-Bands, als auch in düsterer Poesie und Filmen. Es gibt keine
			spezielle Band oder einen speziellen Poeten oder irgendetwas, das ich als Haupteinfluss bezeichnen würde.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Hat sich euer Sound seit damals, also 2000 in irgendeiner Art verändert? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Das hängt davon ab, was du mit "euer Sound" meinst. Die Musik ist immer noch genau so düster und
			depressiv wenn nicht sogar noch mehr. Die großen Veränderungen betreffen die Verwendung der Instrumente
			und das Songwriting. Meiner Meinung nach ist das neue Zeug viel besser geschrieben und hoffentlich haben
			sich meine instrumentellen Fähigkeiten auch verbessert. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Was können wir vom Full-Length-Album erwarten? Werden dort auch ältere Songs drauf sein oder nur neues
			Material? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Es wird einen alten Song namens "November Dream" enthalten, der ursprünglich auf unserem ersten Demo
			"The Silent Cry" erschien. Das restliche Material wurde nach der MCD geschrieben. Was ihr von dem neuen
			Album erwarten könnt, ist so ziemlich das gleiche wie auf der MCD nur extremer in die Metal- als auch in
			die Non-Metal-Richtung. Es wird noch düsterer und epischer sein. Ich denke, ihr werdet es alle mögen. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Wann können wir mit der Veröffentlichung des Full Lengths rechnen? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Ich denke irgendwann im Frühjahr/Sommer 2003. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Ich habe auf eurer Homepage gelesen, dass Micce die Band verlassen hat! Kannst du uns nähere Details dazu
			geben? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Also, wir beide hatten unsere Ideen und die finden sich nicht immer. Entweder hätten wir auf einer Basis
			von Kompromissen, mit denen wir beide leben können, weiter gemacht oder wir hätten uns getrennt. Ich
			dachte, Letztere wäre die bessere Option. Ich kann mich nicht selbst sehen, wie ich Zeit mit etwas
			verschwende, von dem ich weiß, dass ich viel besser machen könnte. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Ist die geplante Full-Length Platte jetzt in Gefahr? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Es wird wohl nur stark verspätet erscheinen, als jetzt schon ist, da ich alles selbst machen muss, aber
			es ist definitiv nicht in Gefahr. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Siehst du Probleme darin, die Band alleine fortzuführen? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Auf keinen Fall! Ich sah das kommen, da ich wusste, dass es zwischen mir und Micce nicht ewig klappen
			würde. Ich denke, ein Teil von mir war auf die Trennung und auf die Soloarbeit vorbereitet und deswegen
			war es für mich nichts neues. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Wird Micce jetzt seine eigene Band an den Start bringen? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Darüber habe ich mit ihm noch nicht gesprochen, aber das wird er vielleicht machen. Er ist ein verdammt
			guter Musiker und hat viele interessante Ideen. Ich denke, er kann sehr interessantes Zeug vorlegen. Ich
			habe nie verstanden, warum er immer unbedingt mit mir arbeiten wollte. Es gibt soviel das er ohne mich
			besser machen kann. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Eure Texte sind sehr düster und depressiv. Wo bezieht ihr eure Inspirationen dafür? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Einige Teile sind Reflektionen von sehr persönlichen Erfahrungen meinerseits, wenn auch etwas
			dramatischer geschildert und andere Teile sind von dunkler Kunst generell beeinflusst. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Müssen wir uns euch als depressive und melancholische Typen vorstellen - was man erwartet, nachdem man
			die Texte gelesen hat - oder ist das nur, weil diese Art besser zur Musik passt? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Ich war eine lange Zeit sehr down und depressiv, aber ich kann nicht sagen, dass ich noch so bin. Ich
			liebe immer noch dunkle und melancholische Kunst und ernsthaft kann ich mich auch nicht vorstellen, eines
			Tages fröhliche Musik zu machen. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Erachtest du den Erfolg bei mp3.com als eines der wichtigsten Teile im Puzzle eures Erfolges? 
		</p>
		<p>
			Es war sicherlich wegen mp3.com, dass wir unter Vertrag genommen wurden, also ist das in der Tat ein
			wichtiges Teil im Puzzle des Erfolges. 
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Bobo Nickolov" zine="Immortality zine" date="020728">
		<p type="question">
			Hail Niclas.For the start ,can you present Forest of Shadows to the macedonian readers of IMMORTALITY?
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows was founded back in '97 as a contribution to the world of dark music. It was thus a
			solo-project at the beginning. After the release of the first demo "The Silent Cry", multi-
			instrumentalist Micce Andersson joined and gave the band a new fresh sound. This was first heard on the
			promo "Promo '99" which gained good critics in the underground. Due to increasing popularity the idea of
			playing live was born and it resulted in the recruitment of guitarist Martin Claesson. Another result of
			this new popularity was the recordings of a new promo "Promo 2000" which was meant to show even more
			signs of progression.
		</p>
		<p>
			In the beginning of 2000 two gigs were held with the help of some session-musicans. These two gigs were
			far from satisfying and it was decided that focus should be on the recordings of a new demo which
			hopefully would lead to a record-deal and not on any more gigs. Before the recording-sessions took place
			Martin left the band due to several reasons. Even though he had been very much involved with the new
			material it was decided to record it without him. This new material resulted in the demo "where dreams
			turn to dust". The intention of this new demo was that it should be released as a mCD by some record
			company and so it was, though a little delayed due to various problems, by the english label Rage of
			Achilles in October 2001.
		</p>
		<p>
			The deal with Rage of Achilles didn't just include the mCD but also a full-length and as we speak this
			full-length album is being recorded with a scheduled release in late 2002/early 2003.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			At the begging you Forest of Shadows was a solo-project.What was the idea for making a solo-project like
			this one?
		</p>
		<p>
			I just couldn't find any other musicians who shared my musical ambitions so I had to do it all by myself. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Can you tell me something more about your releases?
		</p>
		<p>
			"Under the Dying Sun" (promo 1998) - This album included early takes of the songs later on to be featured
			on the demo "The Silent Cry". These early takes were done under pretty rough conditions and to be honest
			they sound rather horrible in terms of quality.  
		</p>
		<p>
			"The Silent Cry" (demo 1998) - This was the first "real" recording and it was done all by me. Even though
			it sounds way better than the early takes it has a pretty rough sound and the most interessting thing
			about the album is the idea behind the songs and not how they were performed.
		</p>
		<p>
			"Promo '99" (promo 1999) - In order to present how the arrival of Micce had affected the sound of the
			band we decided to re-record the song "The Silent Cry" as well as covering Katatonia's "Rainroom". This
			album was primarily meant for media and record-companies which explains why we didn't release it
			properly. 
		</p>
		<p>
			"Promo 2000" (promo 2000) - Since we didn't have enough material for a new demo we wanted to give
			something to the audience in the meantime and thus we recorded yet another old . This was just like the
			predeccesing album done primarily for media and record-companies.
		</p>
		<p>
			"where dreams turn to dust" (demo 2000/mCD 2001) - This was the first album since '98 to feature new
			material. It was written before Martin Claesson left the band which means that he was involved in its
			creation. We were pretty consumed by the popularity achieved by the promos and we thought that it
			wouldn't be hard to find a record-company to release this material as a proper album. After a while we
			realized that things didn't work that easy and it took about three months before the label Molded Skull
			contacted us and wanted to release us as their first album. Things didn't work out very well for Molded
			Skull though and after awhile we had to look for another label. Actually we didn't need to look very much
			since the english label Rage of Achilles has contacted us while we were signed to Molded Skull and we
			just contacted them again and asked if they still wanted to release our stuff and they were more than ok
			with that.
		</p>
		<p>
			"conquest for the empire" (compilation 2002) - The song "wish" from the mCD was picked to end this
			compilation which features songs from most Rage of Achilles signed bands. Worth mentioning is that one of
			these bands are Shubend, another band of mine in which I am vocalist.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who are the other members of Foreset of Shadows?
		</p>
		<p>
			Right now the only member besides me is Micce Andersson who has been around since 1998.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How many times you are able to play in live in one year?
		</p>
		<p>
			As it is right now we don't play live at all due to various reasons.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Can you tell me about the new upcoming album,when will be released?
		</p>
		<p>
			The new, still untitled, album will be released late 2002/early 2003. The featured material will sound
			pretty much like the mCD but with much more structure and thought behind it. I guess fans of the mCD
			won't be disappointed and I hope that the improved sound will open up for more new fans.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Any future plans,maybe tour?
		</p>
		<p>
			If things work well with the new album and if the right people are willing to help as session musicans
			then we might consider touring. It's nothing that we are planning for though but it would be very cool :)
			Apart from that we don't have any exact plans for the future. Both me and Micce are pretty busy
			individuals so we might need time for other things as well. There will be more albums from Forest of
			Shadows though but I can't say when and what they will feature.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			We came to the end.I`m wishing you luck,and now I`m giving you a space for the message to the fans!
		</p>
		<p>
			First of all if you liked the mCD then go get the full-length when it reaches the stores, it will
			hopefully not let you down. Seconds we would like to show our deepest respect to all our fans in
			macedonia who support us. THANKS ALOT! ...oh, and thanks for the interview by the way.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Petar Mihajlovic" zine="the Others zine" date="020610">
		<p type="question">
			What's bout your name? Why did u named your band like that?
		</p>
		<p>
			I was pretty into "forest-metal" like Opeth at that moment and I wanted to use the forest-thing with my
			own music as well hinting at dark melancholy so the name "Forest of Shadows" felt kinda logic.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why did u start playing?
		</p>
		<p>
			I had been creating music for quite awhile previous to Forest of Shadows but I had never done anything
			really official. What made choose an official direction was the fact that I was very depressed at the
			moment and needed to project my emotional hell on something. To make music and just keep it for yourself
			doesn't really help you so I decided to make it official.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Short Forest of Shadows history?
		</p>
		<p>
			FoS was founded in the autumn of 1997 by me (Niclas Frohagen). As a solo-project FoS recorded two albums
			where one was released in may 1998 as an offical demo called "The Silent Cry". Some weeks after this
			release I got in contact with Micce Andersson who wanted to join. Since Micce had alot of knowledge about
			instruments in general as well as production we decided to try and work on our sound. The result was
			presented on a promo-CD that was released in may 1999. During the following months we started planning to
			get more members and try to rehearse for some gigs. We recruited Martin Claesson as guitarist in November
			that year. Previous to this recruitment we had started working on a new recording which would be yet
			another promo with yet another remake of an old demo-song. It was released in the beginning of 2000.
			During that time we did our first gig on which we had to use session-musican to complete the setup. Some
			month later we did yet another gig with a new recruitment on bass. This gig was far from pleasing to us
			and the main reason was our bass-player who we had to fire. This gig marked the end of our short career
			as a "live-band" and we decided to focus on the recordings of our coming release, the mCD "where dreams
			turn to dust". Unfortunatelly things didn't work out with Martin and he had to leave the band before the
			actuall recordings. The mCD was recorded the summer of 2000 and the idea was to find a label that was
			willing to release the material. Nothing really happened though and we decided to release the stuff as a
			demo and to put the songs on mp3.com where we had gain alot of success. For months nothing happened at
			all in the FoS-camp. In the summer of 2001 we got in contact with Fredrik and Richard Johansson who
			wanted to join on guitar and drums and we started rehearsing. After some months we realized that it
			wasn't gonna work out so we decided to drop it. At the same time we got in contact with a new label
			called Molded Skull Recordings who wanted to release our mCD. The label never managed to release
			anything though due to financial problems so we had to pick another label. The kings of alternative and
			extreme metal "Rage of Achilles" had contacted us while we were signed to MS and we contacted them and
			asked if they were still interessted and so they were. The mCD was released in October 2002. The deal
			with RoA featured, apart from the mCD, a full-length which we are currently working on. Unfortunatelly
			things aren't moving very smooth with the recordings and we don't really know when it will be released
			even though earlier plans said sometime this year (2002).
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Influences? First CD u bought was...?
		</p>
		<p>
			My first CD was the collection "Hero, Hero" by Judas Priest. I don't know if it influenced me to write
			music though. Maybee it did in some way. Generally speaking I guess I have been influenced by most bands
			I've heard that play good melodies and create dark and mournfull atmospheres. I guess I speak for Micce
			there as well. Some influences might be more obvious than others though and the bands that has influenced
			FoS most over the years are Opeth, Katatonia, My Dying Bride and Anathema.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What r u trying to tell with your music? Inner pain, pure emotions, real life, myths...?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well if the lyrics were based on real-life then I wouldn't be alive I guess so lets call them pretty
			dramatic versions of my sour times. FoS doesn't want to preach or moralize or anything we just make music
			for the sake of art. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Did u gave your best to sound original or that came just like that? Your favorite bands? 
		</p>
		<p>
			We don't care much if we are original or not. As long as we like what we do we're satisfied. There's no
			point in ripping off other bands though and if there is some part in our music that seems like stolen
			then it's not done by purpose.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Did u played on some big gigs? Did u open for some other bands or had solo gigs, tour...?
		</p>
		<p>
			We have just done two gigs and none of them were even close to big. We have never toured or opened for
			any other band.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is playing music your only "job"?		
		</p>
		<p>
			Well actually it's not really a job any of us. We do it on our spare time and we do it cuz we feel like
			it. There are no intentions off making any big money even though it would be a lie to say that we
			wouldn't like to.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			R u pleased with your life in general? Would u change something?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, I'm pleased with my life as it is in general but still there are things that could be changed. I
			mean there are always things that you want to change to some extent.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Last one is bout possible playing in Serbia. Would u come n do some gigs here if somebody invites u?
		</p>
		<p>
			If we start doing gigs again and if someone invites us it would be arrogant to say no if it's not due to
			very good reasons.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Nathan Schneider" zine="schnits.org" date="020314">
		<p type="question">
			Who were your musical inspirations?
		</p>
		<p>
			On the early stuff, recorded when FoS was still a solo-project, the main inspiration was Opeth, My Dying
			Bride, Anathema, early Katatonia, Therion and Autumn Tears. The reason why these bands were used as
			sources of inspiration mainly that they contained the fundamentals of what FoS was to represent, which
			was (and is) epic and diverse mournfull music. When Micce joined the band, two very important
			inspirations were added and that was nordic folk-music and simplistic and monotonous metal ala Katatonia
			(Brave Murder Day). These two inspirations became more and more evident as time passed and were
			definately the main inspirations on the debute mCD "where dreams turn to dust"
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What were your personal inspirations?
		</p>
		<p>
			Mainly the current situation and how I felt about my life and all that
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What is your favorite song that you have written?
		</p>
		<p>
			If we are talking stuff that is written and recorded the answer would be "Wish". I especially like the
			lyrics of that one. The new stuff, which is currently being recorded, contains far better songs than
			"Wish" though IMO.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What instruments do you play?
		</p>
		<p>
			I play most kinds of guitars and keyboards and I play with my voice. Micce plays more or less all
			string/keyboard-based instruments. We both play drums fairly.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you often get heavy media attention?
		</p>
		<p>
			No, never.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you plan on touring North America?
		</p>
		<p>
			As it is right now we don't even do any gigs so touring is pretty much out of the question.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What's in the future for you guys?
		</p>
		<p>
			New and improved records that hopefully will attract more people.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you have a website besides the mp3.com/fos one?
		</p>
		<p>
			www.forestofshadows.com, which is maintained by me.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How long does it take to write a song?
		</p>
		<p>
			That's rather hard to tell. I mean the basic structures are often written in a day or two (effective
			time) but the final arrangements are mostly made during the final recordings. The most lengthy part is
			actually the lyrics 'cause its very hard to just sit down and write something that makes any sense and
			that fits the gloomy atmosphere of the music. I would guess each lyric takes about a month or so until
			its considered final. The early lyrics were written in a day or at most a week. I guess we are becoming
			more pretentious :)
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why are you making music? for Money or for Music?
		</p>
		<p>
			Since our kind of music doesn't sell all that much it would be rather foolish to make it because of
			money. We are very happy that we gain some money but we have no	intentions to try and make a living of it
			even though it would be very nice.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How much time do you spend writing?
		</p>
		<p>
			That depends on how inspired you are and how much spare time that is availible. Personally I think I
			spend way to little time writing 'cause I have millions of ideas in my head and if I had the time and
			money I would probably spend all day writing and recording for alot of different projects.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Alev Alikoç" zine="All To The Grave zine" date="020212">
		<p type="question">
			First of all I want to thank you for answering the questions. I like to learn about where the name of the
			group came from or who had the idea and can you describe the music of your band?
		</p>
		<p>
			I came up with the name "Forest of Shadows" when the band was still a solo-project and it was supposed to
			symbolize the life I was living back then. Our music can be described as rather slow and melodic dark
			metal with influences ranging from extreme metal to pop and folk music. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Before "Forest of Shadows" became a two-piece band you had a period that you decided to form
			solo-projects because of not finding a proper member. You were also not happy with those period's
			recordings. When you look back can you sum up the situation in those days? Do you think these period
			helped your own music to became the way it is now?
		</p>
		<p>
			Definately. During the time as a solo-project I defined the direction in which the band still is heading.
			The biggest differences between the old and the new stuff is the quality of the arrangements, production
			and performances. The direction has always been same and shall remain that way.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which plans do you have about the band in this days? Is there any new album on the way?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yes, we are currently working on the material for a full-length album and it will probably be released
			sometime in the autumn of 2002. It is still untitled and contains five songs that all together last for
			about 60 minutes.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Have you ever give any live performances? And where?
		</p>
		<p>
			We did two shows in Gothenburg during the spring of 2001 when Martin Claesson was in the band. We weren't
			very satisfied with these gigs though and when Martin left the band a couple of months later we decided
			to continue as a studio band.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which ways do the band use to contact with their fans? How are the reactions about the band and music?
		</p>
		<p>
			Through email. We get alot of fan-mails from visitors of both our mp3.com page and official website and
			we try to reply as many as possible. The reactions so far are very positive and alot of people are
			ecstatic about our music.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which bands do you listen mostly Niclas? Do these bands effect your music? Because I saw your music
			archive on your web page and it is a really huge and rich archive. I also know that you're a great fan of
			Katatonia.
		</p>
		<p>
			I listen to alot of different bands and Katatonia are one of them. It feels rather meaningless to mention
			any of the other bands that i listen to since they are so many. I do not consider myself a die-hard
			Katatonia fan but I like their style and so far every album they have recorded. I guess every band that I
			listen to (and like) affects the music that I am involved in.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who prepares the web page of the band? I think it hasn't got enough information for the bands...What's
			your idea?
		</p>
		<p>
			I am the webmaster of our site and I think it contains enough information. I mean there's no point in
			providing too much information cuz that just makes the page messy.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do other members and you have any other interests? How do you like to spend your time?
		</p>
		<p>
			Yeah, we have other interests even though music occupies alot of our time. I mean personally I am
			involved in three active bands and these demand alot of time. As if this wasn't enough I am studying for
			a master degree in computer science. The remaining hours are in my case spent with my girlfriend or some
			other friends. Both me and Micce are very into snowboarding and skiing.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			I will be very glad to see the band having a live performance in Turkey as a fan of you. Especially whole
			performing the song " eternal autumn". Do you think about the idea coming in Turkey? Do you know anything
			about here?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well, when the day comes when we decide to start playing live again we will ofcourse consider the thought
			of coming to Turkey.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Thanks again for answering my questions. Do you want to add something to say at last?
		</p>
		<p>
			Check out our mCD "where dreams turn to dust", which should be out in the stores by now, and stay tuned
			for our full-length.
		</p>
	</item>
	<item author="Jack Odel" zine="Metalbite webzine" date="011121">
		<p type="question">
			Nicke could you first tell the viewers of this interview a bit about Forest of Shadows and the early time
			of you starting out?
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows was founded by me as a solo-project back in 1997. In may 1998 the first demo "The
			Silent Cry" was released and some weeks after that, multi-instrumentalist Micce Andersson joined the
			band. We released a teaser of our "new sound" in 1999 titled "Promotion-CD 1999" and it gained quite good
			critics so we decided to start rehearsing and seeking some new members for a live-setting. In the Autumn
			of 1999 Martin Claesson joined on guitar and the three of us plus some session-members did two gigs in
			2000 before Martin left the band and me and Micce decided to go for the studio-band thing for awhile
			since we weren't all to satisfied with our live-performances. During the time as a "live-band" we
			released the teaser "Promotion-CD 2000" and wrote the material for the upcoming demo "Where Dreams turn
			to Dust" which we released in the autumn of 2000. Some month after this release we inked a deal with the
			new label "Molded Skull" who were to release our demo as a mCD. But things didn't go as planned for the
			label and in April 2001 they wrote and recommended us to find another label. And so we did and ended up
			with Rage of Achilles (the new promise among labels) and they released our mCD "Where Dreams turn to
			Dust" on the 29th of October 2001 and that's pretty much where we are right now...
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Why metal? Why not pop or grunge? Is there anything specifically particular that attracted you to metal?
		</p>
		<p>
			The main reason why FoS became a metal-band is that metal was more or less the only genre that mattered
			to me when I founded the band back in 1997. The most imortant thing about FoS being a metal band is the
			creative freedom which ofcourse has limitations but still makes it possible to develop a quite original
			and personal sound without to much effort. Since Micce joined in 1998 we have oped our sound more and
			more away from standardized doom-metal towards some kind of utopian FoS-sound. Where we are right now
			metal is more of a founding layer and a powerful way of expressing something that might as well be pop,
			ambient or whatever.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Forest of Shadows covers a vast musical spectrum and is impossible to define within an existing genre of
			metal? You happy with that?
		</p>
		<p>
			Personally I'm very happy with that. There are both good and bad sides about having a label sticked on
			your music. The good thing is that you get alot of easy promotion which can be quite handy. I mean if you
			get to know about a band that sound like one of your favorites then you'll probably check that band out.
			The bad thing is that people don't listen to what the music really has to offer provided that it has
			something to offer.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			With the countless musician changes that Forest of Shadows have gone through it must have been an awful
			weight upon your shoulders to hold all Forest of Shadows responsibilities for a quite a proportion of
			time. Any thoughts?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well most of these persons were just in the band for some weeks. The only person that's not in the band
			any more that really mattered is Martin Claesson. Being the founding-member I have had and still do have
			alot of responsibillity that FoS stays on the "right path" and continues to represent that specific
			feeling that makes it FoS. Since I'm not all that keen on dictatorshit I try to share the responsibillity
			as much as possible though.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			With the release of the MCD "Where Dreams turn to Dust", the press reaction was one of joy and
			excitement, were you happy with amount of support the MCD received?
		</p>
		<p>
			I don't know if the mCD as such has gained that much support. The most important channel of promotion has
			been the songs on mp3.com without which we would never have reached as far as we have done. Maybee what
			the press wrote made people visit mp3.com but if that's the case then it's not just thanks to the mCD.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What can you tell us about the soon to be released album?  You said it possesses the same style as music
			as "Where Dreams turn to Dust", but a bit more 'well-done', care to elaborate at all?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well most of the material that is to be used for the upcoming full-length was written during the
			WDTTD-period so in that sense it's quite similar to the mCD. One of the songs is actually taken from the
			very first demo as well. What I meant by more "well-done" is that this time we know that the stuff is to
			be released which we didn't when we recorded WDTTD and thus it feels more motivated to put as much effort
			as possible in the process. It will also be more "well-done" since we have had plenty of time to really
			analyze the material and get into it in order to get the best out of it. Another important thing is that
			while the mCD was more or less written by me alone this album shows more of a cooperation between me and
			micce.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			On the new album. Are there any album titles that you have brewing in your mind at the moment or is it
			still an opened question?
		</p>
		<p>
			We haven't even started to think about it so I would say it's a still an opened question indeed.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is the recording of the new album going well?
		</p>
		<p>
			So far we just been playing around with the material so we haven't really recorded anything that is to be
			used. But I would say that the entire process is going quite according to plans.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			With influences from Katatonia and an excellent cover of 'Rainroom' do you draw you inspiration from the
			earlier Katatonia albums ("Dance of December Souls" and "Brave Murder Day") or more of the newer
			Katatonia albums ("Discourage Ones" and "Last Fair Deal Gone Down")?
		</p>
		<p>
			Even though both me and Micce adore Katatonia and especially their legendary album "Brave Murder Day" we
			are far from trying to sound like them. The main influence we have got from them is their way of making
			simplistic and still VERY powerfull music which is most evident on BMD. I think the BMD-style is more
			suitable for FoS than the newer stuff.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			You must be so happy that Rage of Achilles signed you up.  Are things working out ok as far as
			distribution and promotional activities? As I read in your biographical information that they have a real
			interest in Forest of Shadows and that must really make it easier for you in terms of creative
			directions.
		</p>
		<p>
			When we were contacted by Rage of Achilles for the first time we didn't know anything about them apart
			from the fact that another band in which I play, Shubend, was signed to them as well. But soon they
			started to show up in alot of zines and alot of their bands recieved good reviews especially Cult of
			Luna, which is a band both me and Micce like alot. Still the best thing about Rage of Achilles is that
			they care alot about us and give us creative freedom. The only ones that seems to fuck up the process is
			the distros, who are slow as hell, and I guess I can't blame Rage of Achilles for that. To conclude we
			are VERY happy with the fact that Rage of Achilles signed us.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What CDs are spinning in your CD player at the moment?
		</p>
		<p>
			"A Fine Day To Exit" - Anathema, "Promotheus" - Emperor, "Director's Cut" - Fantomas and "Dreadful Hours"
			- My Dying Bride
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			The metal scene is one that is constantly fluctuating between trends.  Mid to middle-late 90's there was
			the big jump of symphonic black metal bands. Late 90's and up until now there seems to be a large surge
			of melodic death metal.  What are your thoughts on things and how they stand at the moment? Any
			predictions to how the metal scene in Europe will change?
		</p>
		<p>
			There will always be trends in music and I don't see anything bad about it. It makes the trendy genre
			grow and most of the time it grows into something good. I believe that symphonic black metal is as big
			today as it has ever been. I would rather call it symphonic metal or something though cuz to me symphonic
			black metal is pretty far from true (tm) black metal like mayhem, darkthrone and burzum. Well actually I
			don't care much for thoose labels anyway. Over to my predictions... hmm... well I think (and hope) alot
			of bands will become more pretentious which means that there will be more "art-metal". 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Being a My Dying Bride fan, and having My Dying Bride influence Forest of Shadows, are you happy My Dying
			Bride returned to the sound of "Turn Loose the Swans"?  And what do you think of "The Dreadful Hours"?
		</p>
		<p>
			Well in my opinion "The Angel and the Dark River" is almost as good as "Turn Loose the Swans" which means
			that I didn't really mind weather they returned to their roots or not. In my opinion they never really
			left their path apart from on "34.788%" which in my opinion doesn't really represent what MDB should be
			about even though it's a good album. About "The Dreadful Hours" then... well I like it alot especially
			since it shows a couple of new directions that are quite interessting.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which band would you most like to tour with, and why?
		</p>
		<p>
			If we start playing live again we will try and do something different and not just play... it will
			probably be more of an art thing or something. Anyway, if that is the case then the other bands we tour
			with need to fit in such an arrangement and the only band that I can up with right now that fit are Shape
			of Despair.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Has press promotion (like www.metalbite.com) helped much with Forest of Shadows or more www.mp3.com?
		</p>
		<p>
			There is a big difference between how mp3.com and the press promote us. The amount of promotion we get
			from the press depends on what the press writes while mp3.com is more connected to the music since they
			do promotion by playing our music. mp3.com has helped us more than we ever could dream of. I mean there
			were days when we had about 1000 downloads/day and judging from the huge amount of fan-mails we have
			recieved at least some of thoose who downloaded the songs loved what they heard. Still a very good review
			in a huge zine could easily beat 1000 downloads/day since most people are enslaved by what others think.
			And finally I wouldn't mind getting more reviews like the one you did :)
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where do you see Forest of Shadows five years down the track?
		</p>
		<p>
			Forest of Shadows will definately exist in five years but I have no clue what we will sound like or who
			will be involved apart from me.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Finally, I thank you very much Nicke for this interview and Forest of Shadows for their excellent metal
			music.  Would you like to say anything to anyone specifically or generally?
		</p>
		<p>
			And I thank you Jack for a great interview (and a great review as well) and I would like to tell everyone
			to check out our mCD "Where dreams turn to Dust" which is out now and finally I would, on behalf of
			Forest of Shadows, like to thank everyone that has supported us and downloaded our songs from mp3.com.
			THANKS ALOT!!!
		</p>
 	</item>
	<item author="Black Widow" zine="Nightshade promotions" date="001102">
		<p type="question">
			Who are the members of your band and what is their instrument?
		</p>
		<p>
			Niclas Frohagen - Vocals, guitar, synth and programming; Micce Andersson - Bass, guitar, synth, violin
			and programming.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Where do you hail from?
		</p>
		<p>
			Gothenburg, Sweden
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How long have you played together?
		</p>
		<p>
			The band has been a two-piece since the summer of 1998 so figure it out.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How did you meet?
		</p>
		<p>
			Thru a common friend.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How do you categorize yourselves, or do you?
		</p>
		<p>
			We prefer not to but the audience demands some kind of label so we usually categorize us as dark-metal.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Who have been your influences in music?
		</p>
		<p>
			In alphabetical order: Anathema, Jan Johansson, Katatonia, My Dying Bride, Opeth and Shape of Despair.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Have you released a CD?
		</p>
		<p>
			We are to release our first "real" album, the EP "where dreams turn to dust", sometime before the end of
			this year (2000). Previous to that we have released some demos.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Do you tour? If so, where can we find you next?
		</p>
		<p>
			No
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Which member of your band is the press hound?
		</p>
		<p>
			Me, Niclas Frohagen
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Tell me your favourite band story.
		</p>
		<p>
			I guess that would be from our first gig when our session bass-player didn't show up due to an accident
			and we had to find a new one and rehearse the set with him in a couple of hours. Due to the	circumstances
			it went pretty well but still it was very weird.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Is there anything in the works that you can share with us?
		</p>
		<p>
			We are writing some new songs and enhancing some old demo-songs for a coming full-length album.
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			How was the band named?
		</p>
		<p>
			The band was named back in 1997 when it was my (Niclas Frohagen) solo-project. The Forest of Shadows was
			supposed to symbolize the life I was (and am) living. 
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			What year did this band first come together?
		</p>
		<p>
			1997 as a solo-project of mine (Niclas Frohagen)
		</p>
		<p type="question">
			Thank you for visiting Night Shade, we'll look forward to seeing you again in the near future. Night
			Shade wishes you the best of luck and the darkest of shadows.
		</p>
	</item>
</interviews>
