<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO8859-1" ?>
<news>
	<archive name="main">
		<item title="among the dormant watchers to be released in december 2018 on inverse records" date="1809020">
			After almost ten years in production, the third full-length "Among the Dormant Watchers" is now scheduled
			for release in December 2018 on Inverse Records.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe nominated: best doom metal album 2008" date="090208">
			"six waves of woe" has been nominated as best doom metal album 2008 at www.metalstorm.ee with the
			motivation: Four years after the majestic "Departure", Sweden's best kept Doom-secret Forest Of
			Shadows returns with another tear-jerking, emotionally draining masterpiece. "Six Waves Of Woe"
			continues the base elements present	on "Departure", but is more than just that. More mechanical and
			industrial than the debut and also more to the point, the album emits a devestation glow of isolation
			and coldness. Can you handle this much heartless music?
		</item>
		<item title="re-releases" date="090125">
			I am currently preparing some re-releases of "where dreams turn to dust" and "departure" that will be
			released thru firebox. Both albums will include some old remastered songs as bonus tracks. More info
			will be presented here within the coming weeks.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe" date="080909">
			"Six Waves of Woe" is now a closed chapter. It was mastered by Minerva Pappi at Finnvox, Finland some
			week ago and the result has been sent to Firebox together with the case-layouts. All that remains now
			is the actuall release which is scheduled for the 29th of October this year. If you haven't already
			noticed, two songs from "six waves of woe" are available for previewing, one at myspace and one at
			firebox's webpage. Check them out if you haven't.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe" date="080608">
			After more than three years of composing, recording and mixing I now consider "six waves of woe" finished
			or at least ready for mastering. All that's left now before I leave it in the hands of the label is to 
			finish up the case-layout. The release-date is currently being discussed and I think we can expect the
			album to be out this autumn/winter. Stay tuned for mp3-samples that will be posted here and on myspace and
			for more details about the release-date.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe" date="080330">
			Finally, all the vocals have been recorded and I'm currently arranging it all to something nice. At the
			same time I'm finishing the final polishing and adding the last pieces to bring the songs together. I will
			soon start pre-mastering the songs while waiting for the details about the release, that when and how it
			all will happen. I'll let you all know as soon as it gets settled and also stay tuned for thoose teaser
			samples.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe" date="080220">
			Just felt that I needed to let you all know that the album is still progressing. I have recorded most
			vocals but I guess there is still some work to do before I am satisified. One or two songs are near
			completion though so I might put up a teaser sample quite soon so stay tuned for that.
		</item>
		<item title="six waves of woe" date="070711">
			Having completed all the lyrics for the upcoming album I also gave it a name, or at least a working-title - 
			"six waves of woe". More information about this can be found in the discography section where I will 
			write about its progress from this day on until the release.
		</item>
		<item title="katatonia tribute again ...and more" date="070130">
			So, I finally got some copies of the katatonia tribute both on DLP and DCD. Nice. If you are a fan of
			katatonia and especially their earlier works I would really recommend you to check it out
			(http://www.northern-silence.de/). I'm still working on the previously mentioned new stuff and it's
			progressing slow but well. I hope to be able to give you all some more information about this soon.
		</item>
		<item title="katatonia tribute and more" date="060826">
			I just saw some updates about the katatonia tribute and the final call is that it will be out on the
			12th of December. It will be released both on DCD and DLP and have a total playtime of over 100
			minutes. While I'm writing I might as well confirm that the band is still alive despite lack of
			updates. I'm working on some new material and have been doing so for quite some time now but I don't
			want to give away any offical details about anything since I might not live up to it.
		</item>
		<item title="katatonia tribute" date="051111">
			Northern Silence seems to have had some problems with arranging the katatonia tribute but now things
			are coming together and the planned release-date is set to beginning of 2006. Forest of Shadows will
			appear on the album with "rainroom", which also can be found on the '99 promo.
		</item>
		<item title="where dreams turn to dust" date="051102">
			The release-date for the re-release of "where dreams turn to dust" has been set to the 23rd of November.
		</item>
		<item title="where dreams turn to dust" date="050903">
			A remastered digipak version of the mCD "where dreams turn to dust" will be released by Firedoom. The
			actuall	release-date hasn't been decided yet but I'll post it here on the website as soon as I know.
		</item>
		<item title="where dreams turn to dust" date="050619">
			I'm preparing a re-release of the mCD "where dreams turn to dust" since it has run out of stock at most
			distros. Also the company that used to be responsible for it (Rage of Achilles) has gone out of
			business and thus won't be able to make a second press. I'll get back with more information like
			release-date and which label that will take care of the release.
		</item>
		<item title="departure voted best album of 2004" date="050214">
			Departure has been voted as the #1 album of 2004 at "Lost Stats Domain" (http://www.zenial.nl).
			At the same site Forest	of Shadows is currently voted 2nd best metal band of all time :)
		</item>
		<item title="rainroom cover on katatonia tribute" date="050214">
			The katatonia cover "rainroom", originally found on the '99 promo, will be featured on a katatonia
			tribute which is to be released during early 2005 on northern silence.
		</item>
	</archive>
	<archive name="site">
		<item title="moving to github" date="260705">
			This site is now hosted by github and may be getting some renovations further on
		</item>
		<item title="among the dormant watchers added to discography" date="181205">
			"Among the Dormant Watchers" has been added to discography with lyrics and information.
		</item>
		<item title="new interviews" date="181119">
			Two new interviews have been added.
		</item>
		<item title="minor facelift" date="180919">
			New visuals to match the new album: "Among the Dormant Watchers".
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="150614">
			Added some more reviews of "where dreams turn to dust".
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="090907">
			Added the entire demo "the silent cry" from 1998 in mp3-format.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="090617">
			Added the russian press of "departure".
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="090107">
			Added some more reviews of "six waves of woe".
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="081214">
			I added some reviews of "six waves of woe" and some fresh interviews.
		</item>
		<item title="biography" date="081016">
			The biography section has now been updated and exposed. This means that the entire page is now up.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="081001">
			The discography section has now been updated and exposed. I hope to be able to finish the rest within
			the	next week or so.
		</item>
		<item title="facelift" date="080909">
			As you might have noticed the webpage has been given a major facelift to match the new album. You may
			also notice that the current page doesn't offer as much as it used to and that's because it's simply
			not finished. Still I decided to put it up in it's current state to present at least news and contact
			information. The rest will be put online any day during the coming weeks.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="080608">
			Added the album-cover for "six waves of woe" and some information about the album.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="080330">
			Added the latest progress of "six waves of woe".
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="070711">
			Information about the upcoming album "six waves of woe" has been added to the discography section. From
			this day on until the release this page will preset the progress of the album.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="070130">
			Added the compilation "december songs (a tribute to katatonia)" to the discography section.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="060326">
			Added a review of "where dreams turn to dust" from the metal observer
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="060119">
			Added a review of "where dreams turn to dust" from imhotep
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="050914">
			Added the remaster of "where dreams turn to dust" to the discography section.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050903">
			Added some reviews.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050619">
			Added some interviews.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050424">
			Yet another interview has been added.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050324">
			Another interview has been added.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050322">
			Two interviews and one review has been added.
		</item>
		<item title="contact" date="050316">
			Added links to the distributors of "departure", "conquest for the empire" and "where dreams turn to
			dust".
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050313">
			Loads of interviews from 2000-2005 has been added.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050310">
			Alot of old reviews has been added. Coming up shortly will be loads of interviews and articles.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050307">
			Reviews of "departure" from terrorizer and close-up has been added as well as some old reviews of
			"where dreams turn to dust".
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050305">
			More reviews of "departure" has been added. Old reviews of "where dreams turn to dust" and the promos
			are coming up shortly as well as interviews and articles.
		</item>
		<item title="press" date="050301">
			The press section is now open and it and at this stage it includes some of the many reviews of
			"departure". More reviews of this album as well the older albums will be added in the coming days. I will
			also try and add some interviews and articles quite soon.
		</item>
		<item title="discography" date="050227">
			Alot of downloadables such as mp3's and case-layouts has been added. More will be added once I get
			some more space.
		</item>
		<item title="biography - pictures" date="050227">
			I have added some pictures from the 1999 photo-session.
		</item>
		<item title="biography - pictures" date="050224">
			I have added some pictures from the 2002 photo-session.
		</item>
		<item title="biography - members and pictures" date="050217">
			It is now possible to view the member profiles and some of the band pictures. The rest of the pictures
			will be up within a week or so.
		</item>
		<item title="biography - history" date="050217">
			The biography section has now been enabled but is restricted to the history sub-section. Information
			about members as well as the photo gallery will be up shortly.  
		</item>
		<item title="new site" date="050214">
			The new site is finally up. It's not 100% finished though but I will try and have all the features
			up within a month or so.
		</item>
	</archive>
	<archive name="related">
		<item title="shub-end" date="041112">
			I have left shubend since I don't have any time or energy to invest in that band. Dan and Martin will
			continue making music together though but under the name "genesis of pain".  
		</item>
	</archive>
</news>
