<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO8859-1" ?>
<reviews>
	<album name="among the dormant watchers | cd 2018">
		<item author="Jordan McEvoy" zine="PureGrainAudio" date="181219" rating="8.5/10">
			<p>
				Sweden is rife with doom, melancholy, and despair, mixed with beautiful melodies - and Forest of Shadows are no exception. A staple band during the boom of death-doom bands, they soared through the ranks with their blend of emotionally pulling lyrics, and are now on their third album, Among the Dormant Watchers. A decade after Six Waves of Woe is a long time for a band to wait to revive, which makes one wonder how the record will sound and whether the group have managed to retain their original sound, or taken a new direction entirely. As arguably one of the biggest surprises of 2018, the release of Among the Dormant Watchers brings a tingle of excitement in the ears of any death/doom fan.
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows have picked up a number of new influences and styles along the way during their break, the most noticeable of which are melody-driven folk passages and elements of post-rock to accompany their blend of atmospheric black metal and doom. The incorporation of post/progressive rock into their sound makes for a multifaceted and immersive listen. The clearest example of this is on their single “Drowned by Guilt”, which depicts Niclas Frohagen observing his own death by drowning (his inspiration for the song came from a dream of this), before zooming out to a third person perspective on death and the effect it has on those close to him. It’s a dark insight into the effects of death and one that people do not consider sometimes, which easily makes it a standout on the album. Slowing the pace significantly in comparison to opener “Self Inflicted Torment”, you feel the despair pouring out of the band in “Drowned by Guilt” and it works beautifully.
			</p>
			<p>
				The addition of an acoustic guitar at multiple points brings a layer of complexity and variety with it, breathing new life into “Dogs of Chernobyl”. It focuses more on the melodic death side of their sound, while bringing progressive guitar passages into the mix, demonstrating what they’ve learned works with their sound during their break. The song breaks for a minute midway through, with a lulling acoustic guitar passage that breaks the repetition before Niclas’ growls chime back in and the funeral march returns. Slow, crushing riffs follow underneath the same melody that permeates throughout the track, yet engulfed by a different riff each time. It’s arguably both the strongest track to come from Among the Dormant Watchers, and one of Forest of Shadows’ best efforts yet.
			</p>
			<p>
				After something as intense as “Dogs of Chernobyl”, “We, the Shameless” brings an unexpected calm. A simple electronic intro preludes a soft guitar followed by Niclas’ first instance of clean vocals on the record. The lyrics “Self-proclaimed masters of a dying world” and “We spill the blood as we see fit” strike a chord and makes you think about the world we live in today and how we treat it. Bringing further diversity to the record is “Lullaby” – a soft acoustic palette cleanser on an otherwise (mostly) heavy album. It offers a soothing atmosphere before the monolithic “Yours to Devour”, which is another contender for the standout track on the record. It’s a behemoth reminiscent of the classic death/doom blend Forest of Shadows came to be known for. The blissful fusion of slow, sombre riffs and keyboard passages with the following soft, clean vocal passages over the 14-minute long finisher tie off the album brilliantly.
			</p>
			<p>
				What is amazing about Forest of Shadow’s latest record is how beneficial their break from releasing new material has been. In such a vast time scale, we can see their sound remaining true, yet malleable to external influences as seen with the inclusion of post-rock and even electronica. Their expansion to new horizons has felt like a continuation from their previous record, Six Waves of Woe, and they’ve just carried on where they left off but bigger and better. It’s safe to say that with Among the Dormant Watchers, Forest of Shadows have triumphantly returned. A devastatingly beautiful listen from start to finish, it comes full circle through loss, fear, and despair, and reinforces their place high in the ranks of atmospheric doom metal.
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="six waves of woe | cd 2008">
		<item author="Brett Buckle" zine="The Metal Crypt" date="090202" rating="4/5">
			<p>
				A couple of years back I discovered Forest of Shadows through their debut long player Departure
				and really enjoyed their drawn-out Katatonia influenced style of doom. It has taken four long
				years but finally I have their new CD Six Waves of Woe, an album which sees Niclas Frohagen,
				Forest of Shadows' only member, take a decided turn towards the Gothic Metal side of things. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Typically I'm not a huge fan of Gothic Metal, but I do enjoy it when it is done well, and here
				Forest of Shadows has dropped a heavy and memorable slab of doomy goodness that I just can't help
				but enjoy. Kicking off with an intro of muted synthetic toms and quiet guitars, it isn't long
				before Niclas kicks it with some seriously crushing guitars that rumble under some simplistic but
				oh so sweet melodies that sets the pace for the album. The obvious comparison here is Draconian
				and their brand of massive Doom/Goth, and influences from bands like Paradise Lost, especially in
				the guitar melodies. The Katatonia worship of Departure is still present but a bit more
				understated, with the main tip of the hat being the vocals which are still quite reminiscent of
				Jonas Renske, but even after toning it down a little you need only listen to "Pernicious" to hear
				an homage to the veterans of depressive metal. However, unlike the Katatonia frontman's somber
				vocal styling's, Niclas Frohagen also has a deep Death growl that he pulls out to devastating
				effect, lending the already weighty sections of the album even more heft. There are some clear
				post-metal influences present as well, most notably in the ending of "Self Destruction" and
				"Deprived" but they are incorporated into the Gothic doom of the album well and never jar you out
				of that perfectly gloomy mood. The drums are all done by machine and it is pretty obvious too,
				with the programming being largely utilitarian and lacking in frills, and while it suits the
				music, there is that element missing that a good drummer can bring to an album. 
			</p>
			<p>
				There is a lot of variation within each track and the album as a whole, and while not as lengthy
				as those on Departure, the tracks all have great stories to tell, shifting effortlessly between
				crushingly heavy and calmly serene. The keyboards provide the basis of the melodies, and whether
				it be those 70's style Progressive Rock keyboards or the more typical orchestral varieties, they
				are always there with just the right sound and just the right presence. The impetus of the album
				is supplied expertly by the bass and drums as they push each track forward in an 8th note pulse
				that should be familiar to fans of the genre and when it gets heavy, Six Waves of Woe absolutely
				crushes with rhythm guitars, bass and keyboards adding together to swamp the listener in a wall of
				sound that remains clear throughout though due to the flawless production that highlights the
				integral nature of each instrument. 
			</p>
			<p>
				In Six Waves of Woe Forest of Shadows has produced a heavy and memorable platter of doom-laden
				Gothic Metal that should greatly please fans of both genres. It is one of those albums that just
				keeps getting better over time as the subtleties in that huge sound become unraveled over multiple
				listens, so don't write this one off after one or two listens because by the tenth you will be
				hooked. Recommended.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Robert" zine="metal-norge.com" date="090124" rating="9/10">
			<p>
				Da Forest of Shadows eminente debut, «Deptarture» kom i 2004, erindrer jeg at jeg ble uhørt
				begeistret. Bandet mestret å blande minimalistisk trip hop / elektronika med storartet doom på en
				så treffende måte at det var bare for meg å ta av seg hatten. I all begeistringsrus, slo jeg også
				av en prat med Niclas Frohagen, en meget hyggelig type med en svært forsvarlig holdning til god
				musikk. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Etter slippet av «Departure» har det vært veldig stille fra Forest of Shadows, det ble en
				re-release av miniskiva «Where Dreams Turn To Dust» i 2005, og ei låt på en Katatonia-tribute, men
				utover det skulle det gå fire år før det dukket opp nytt fra Forest of Shadows. Vi skriver 2009,
				og det er med nyervervet begeistring at jeg kan konstantere at plate nummer to fra Forest of
				Shadows er minst like velutviklet, velskrevet, stemningsfull og god som forgjengeren.
				Modningsprosessen har åpenbart gjort musikken godt, der oppskrifta fra forrige gang, med
				elektronika, doom og post rock-tendenser er rendyrket. Det er lett å høre at dette er Forest of
				Shadows, med det langt mer profesjonelt i denne omgang - produksjonen er tyngre, lydbildet er mer
				gjennomarbeidet og trommeneprogrammeringen sitter som et skudd. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Renvokalen var muligens aberet for mange på førsteplata, og det kan meldes at de drøyeste
				utskeielsene er tonet ned et par hakk, og vokalen generelt høres langt mer stødig og moden ut.
				Generelt sett er antageligvis en av de største forandringene at låtene er kortet ned, og
				komposisjonene er litt mer stødig. Der de i forrige omgang dro ting litt vel langt på enkelte
				låter, er moderasjonens kunst blitt tatt i bruk på en langt mer subtil måte her. Det er virkelig
				godt å høre et band som ikke gjør noen kompromisser, men arbeider over en lang periode med gode
				låter - driter i alt som heter suksess og image men kjører på med kvalitet. Et av de beste platene
				i 2009 for min del.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Euthanatos" zine="Global DOMINATION" date="090119" rating="8/10">
			<p>
				I felt that, beginning a new metal year here at GD, I really wanted to start things off with a
				great album, but I didn't feel I had any great albums in my hands. Fortunately, I received a
				message from a good friend in which he stated his favorite albums of 2008. At the top of that list
				was this album, Forest of Shadows' "Six Waves of Woe", which I then checked out and was
				consequently blown away by. Not only had I never heard of the band (this is only their second
				album anyway), but "Six Weaves of Woe" is a terribly wrist-slashing title. And when the band
				supposedly plays doom metal, an awful sense of impending boredom filled me. I was wrong; while
				Forest of Shadows do play a slow-paced doom, the appropriate clean vocals, occasional old school
				growls and fascinatingly stunning melodies make this quite a find. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The instrumental got me from the get go; everything is perfect, just the right amount of
				brutality (not too much) and soothing passages (not too gay). I know this kind of comparison has
				been done way too many times, but mix a little Swallow the Sun and Katatonia and you'll definitely
				be real close to what Forest of Shadows does. But they're also really original, which is
				incredibly surprising as we're talking about doom metal here. Actually, I wouldn't even call this
				doom metal. There isn't a hint of despair here, apart from some furious growls every now and then.
				No, the atmosphere is much more haunting, in the sense of eerie surreality. Did that make sense?
				No, I didn't think so.
			</p>
			<p>
				True, the vocals, unlike the melodies portrayed by the instruments, might take a little getting
				used to. Somewhere between whining and honest sadness, after a while you'll soon grow accustomed
				to them, and even begin to notice that nothing else would fit.
			</p>
			<p>
				So, yeah, not all "Best of 2008" lists are as lame as ours here at GD. Lucky for us, eh?
			</p>
			<p>
				The cover: Beautiful landscape, haunting as the music.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Shane Wolfensberger" zine="Teeth of the Divine" date="090115">
			<p>
				Surviving in the underground for over ten years, one-man entity Forest of Shadows has delivered
				some honest and passionate work. The sentimental value of Nicals Frohagen's music is undeniable
				and this sophomore release continues his intimate path.
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows is a dark/doom metal project. Fans of meaningful music such as Novembre, Swallow
				the Sun, and Katatonia will find home in Six Waves of Woe though nothing here reaches the
				technical heights of those bands. Each song on this disc starts pretty tame with meek and docile
				vocals reminiscent of Mikko Kotamaki from Swallow the Suns more somber moments and Jonas Renske of
				Katatonia, only to climax with distorted guitars and low, violent growls. Where the first
				full-length Departure existed with 20 minute opuses, Six Waves of Woe shortens its execution
				somewhat and gets to the point quicker, which isn't saying too much considering most of these
				songs average at over six minutes.
			</p>
			<p>
				The upgrade in songwriting is something very noticeable from the debut as well. Though the formula
				works well my only complaint is that these songs do not have much to distinguish between them.
				They all follow the same build up pattern and after four or five listens I still can't remember
				one song. Another example of this comes in the continuous riding of chords. Niclas crafts
				effective songs but there isn't much substance after five minutes of riding chords. I would love
				to see Forest of Shadows become a full band and gather more texture. There is so much that can be
				done with his brand of dark music.
			</p>
			<p>
				All in all this is a very solid album from a pretty stable project on Firebox. For a one-man band
				this is pretty mature stuff, simple yet effective. If dark doomy music is your thing I would
				definitely check Six Waves of Woe out. I just don't believe its going make anyone wet their pants.
				See for yourself.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Pedro Azevedo" zine="Chronicles of Chaos" date="090115" rating="7.5/10">
			<p>
				The first time I heard Forest of Shadows was back in 2001, when Rage of Achilles released their
				_When Dreams Turn to Dust_ EP. Niclas Frohagen's solo project has since signed to Firedoom Records
				and released a full-length titled _Departure_ in 2004, which I missed. 2008 sees Forest of Shadows
				back in the fray with _Six Waves of Woe_, and without the benefit of having heard its predecessor
				_Departure_, the overall style on this release turned out to be quite different from what I
				expected.
			</p>
			<p>
				Compared to the early doom/death days of _When Dreams Turn to Dust_, _Six Waves of Woe_ features a
				significantly different approach as far as both the less oppressive guitar and drums, and also the
				vocal style, which is now predominantly clean. The album starts with the warm melodies and
				melancholy of "Submission", which serves as a good introductory number thanks to its crescendo
				structure that doesn't quite reach its predictable climax. That kind of intensity is kept on hold
				until the next track, "Selfdestruction", which again starts all soft and quiet, with even some
				electronic touches fleshing out the sound. The build-up isn't as good as before, but at about one
				third of the track, the heavier climax led by death growls is quite effective and paves the way
				for the general style of _Six Waves of Woe_.
			</p>
			<p>
				As the album progresses, it becomes evident that the focus lies more on the quiet and melodic than
				the heavy and epic, but the mix generally works well -- "Moments in Solitude" being a good
				example. The formula does get repetitive however, and the compositions are generally morecompetent
				than remarkable. _Six Waves of Woe_ should be quite capable of providing some enjoyable listens
				for fans of melodic doom/death, and does deserve special mention for being a one-man project given
				how well crafted it is, but it is not a truly outstanding record.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Laura Wiebe Taylor" zine="Exclaim!" date="09????">
			<p>
				When Sweden's Forest of Shadows cite Katatonia, Rapture and Cult of Luna as musical influences it
				comes as no great surprise, at least not after more than a few minutes of listening. Like many
				melodic doom albums, Six Waves of Woe describes itself well. Though the aptness of the record's
				title takes a while to emerge, eventually the slow, insistent momentum knits waves and woe
				together into an evocatively gloomy picture. At first it seems like Forest of Shadows could be
				aimed toward a post-rock anywhere but gradually ambient outlines get filled in with heavier,
				darker strokes. Mournful, undistorted vocals give way to growled laments, electronic tones sink
				beneath thick, dirge-y riffs and the album's funereal pace slips briefly into a driving pulse.
				Forest of Shadows may have little official output to show for more than ten years of work but
				Niclas Frohagen has used his time well, turning a revolving door project into a solid solo venture
				and transforming the promise of potential into the delivery of expert execution.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="King of Pain" zine="No Filler Music" date="081119" rating="78/100">
			<p>
				It's always nice to see a band alter and grow their sound in a positive and forward thinking way
				and that is precisely what Forest of Shadows have done. Until now Forest of Shadows was highly
				dedicated to maximizing the gloom factor in their music by maintaining a fairly consistent sombre
				sound throughout their prior album 'Departure'. On 'Six Waves of Woe' they have largely removed
				themselves from the obligatory Black Metal cookie monster vocals and employed a clean sung
				strategy interwoven with Swallow the Sun/Dark Tranquillity like deep growls throughout the entire
				album. The instrumentals now gently build throughout each track and complement the new lyrical
				style quite well. The overall sound maintains its doom like nature however the music as a whole is
				more interesting and littered with engaging crescendos. Forest of Shadows has capitalized on the
				elements that work so well for Swallow the Sun and My Dying Bride and put their own spin on them
				to form a great Doom Metal album.
			</p>
			<p>
				'Six Waves of Woe' is perhaps not the most original Doom Metal album that I've heard but I think
				it's a good progression for the band that will ultimately lead them to further develop a
				tremendous sound. The albums production is miles ahead of its predecessor and the instrumentals
				feel more confident and polished than before. 'Six Waves of Woe' is a strong album that presents
				some unique concepts and intelligent song writing that any Doom fan will no doubt enjoy.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Iván C" zine="Friedhof Online Magazine" date="090108" rating="7.25/10">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows, nombre tipiquérrimo donde los halla, es el proyecto de un sueco afincado en
				Estocolmo llamado Niclas. En tiempos pasados el proyecto era una banda, donde él era el almamater
				de la misma. Pero tras numerosas demos Niklas tomo en solitario las riendas de Forest Of Shadows
				(FOS) y aquí tenemos la segunda obra completa editada por el sello finés Firebox Records.
			</p>
			<p>
				En ''Departure'', álbum predecesor del que hoy nos ocupa, la música de FOS era un común y sencillo
				Doom Metal repleto de melancolía muy en la onda de sus compatriotas Katatonia (época Brave Morder
				Day) con grandes pinceladas de los todopoderosos My Dying Bride. Sin embargo en este "Six Waves Of
				Woe" el sonido del proyecto adquiere matices novedosos que desarrollan numerosas bandas en la
				actualidad. Estas nuevas sonoridades a las que me refiero le acercan al sonido de bandas como Cult
				Of Luna. De todas formas son solamente eso pizcas, diferentes intensidades que le dan a algunas
				partes de los seis temas que componen este trabajo, un aire diferente al de la mayoría de bandas
				que practican el Doom Metal más melancólico. Por lo demás este trabajo posee todas las directrices
				esperadas en una banda de estas características como pueden ser Saturnus o Novembers Doom. Punteos
				de guitarra repetitivos que producen una melancolía casi inmediata, voces más fuertes intercaladas
				con otras limpias, letras depresivas y una base rítmica en su mayor parte de tempo lento y
				monótono. 
			</p>
			<p>
				La composición de los temas está bastante bien, no te va a sorprender pero cumple casi en su
				totalidad y gracias a esas partes diferenciadas a las que me refería anteriormente, el trabajo
				tiene un carácter original, por lo que algo de frescura encontraras en este disco. En definitiva
				''Six Waves Of Woe'' es un buena puesta tanto para los que disfrutamos de esta vertiente del Doom,
				como para alguien que busque un ligera brisa de cambio en el género. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Cedric" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="090108" rating="100%">
			<p>
				This is the only 100% I have ever given to an album, and it's worth it.
			</p>
			<p>
				This is the best release I've heard in 2008, and it completely took me by surprise. While
				Departure was an amazing mix of electronica, doom metal, and minimalism, and this formula is still
				here, the tightness of the songwriting has increased exponentially.
			</p>
			<p>
				The first thing you notice when comparing this to Departure is the song lengths. Frohagen has cut
				down the lengths of songs significantly. There are no 20+ minute songs on here, which doesn't mean
				they don't reach the epic levels of catharsis, it just means they reach it quicker than before.
				Every song starts differently, but there's a clear build to climax in every one of them, with
				beautiful electronic almost Massive Attack-like interludes in between the heavy sections. Niclas'
				vocals have matured a lot, too. He was never a wailer, but his voice fits the music perfectly in
				their melancholy and slow, droning phrasing. His death vocals are thicker, more punishing here.
				The introduction of the harsher vocals in "Self Destructive" will hit you like a brick wall.
			</p>
			<p>
				It's clear what he has been listening to in the meantime. I definitely sense a clear influence
				from Cult of Luna and other post metal bands. The songs are solo-less, and there's no unnecessary
				wankery. Everything serves a purpose, and the layers complement each other seamlessly. By
				layering keyboards, electronic drums, heavy guitar and bass and occasional acoustic guitars with
				an almost 70s aesthetic in the keyboard production, he manages to create a thick atmosphere in
				every song.
			</p>
			<p>
				Surprisingly, the bass plays a huge role on this album, and you can hear it guide the music along
				in every song. This is where the Cult of Luna comparison really works, as it guides the music in
				that clear 8th note pump sway that COL possess.
			</p>
			<p>
				Every song on this record is an epic of its own, and even after 20 listens since I got it, it has
				not yet become tiring. For fans of Katatonia, Cult of Luna, My Dying Bride, and Jesu, this is
				recommended highly!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Schwermetall" date="090107" rating="9/13">
			<p>
				Der Schwede Niclas Frohagen, der Forest of Shadows alleine gründete, holte sich ein paar
				Mitstreiter für seine Band, nur um nach ein wenigen Veröffentlichungen wieder alleine dazustehen
				und das zu machen, was er gerne macht. Musik ohne jeglichen Kompromiss.
			</p>
			<p>
				So könnte man ganz kurz die Geschichte der 1997 gegründeten Band erzählen. Nach der Demo "The
				Silent Cry" und den zwei Alben "Where Dreams turned to Dust" und "Departure" nun der neueste
				Streich des Doom-Metalers. Wohl gemerkt, Metal ist nur in Form von fetten E-Gitarren dabei und
				nicht in Form von Hass und Aggression. Auch Partylaune verbreitet "Six Waves of Woe" mit nichten.
			</p>
			<p>
				Die Scheibe ist allerdings auch nicht so depressiv, langsam und tief wie jene vieler anderer
				Musiker in diesem Genre. Melancholisch ist das Wort, das mir beim hören der Töne von Keyboard,
				verzerrten wie akustischen Gitarren, Bass, Schlagzeug und dem meist cleanem Gesang, der sich aber
				gerne in den schnelleren Parts der Lieder in kraftvolles und tiefes Keiffen wandelt, einfällt.
				Eine Mischung aus depressiv und fröhlich. Vor allem der Gitarrensound wirkt bei den fast ständig
				vertretenden Melodien recht froh und munter, was der clenane Gesang aber schnell wieder auflöst
				da er eher traurig klingt.
			</p>
			<p>
				Als einschläfernd bezeichnen kann man eigentlich nur den ersten und den letzten Track. Dazwischen
				ist alles in Mid-Tempo gehalten und wartet nur zwischendurch mit gefühlvollen Zwischenstücken auf,
				die einen Mental runterziehen, nachdenklich stimmen, aber auch sogleich wieder vorbei sind.
				"Pernicious" ist ein gutes Beispiel dafür. Mein Lieblingsstück ist jedoch "Selfdestructive", das
				recht sanft beginnt und wirklich traurig rüberkommt, bevor dann die verzerrten Gitarren und
				festem, aber immernoch cleanem Gesang einsetzten und damit eine Hochstimmung fabrizieren, welche
				nach kurzer Zeit in einen Kraftakt mit tiefem Gegrowle gipfelt. Dieser zieht sich eine Weile hin
				und steigert seine Intensität ständig, bevor er wieder komplett verfällt und ein ruhiges Ende
				bietet. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Die Musik ist zum Teil wirklich ergreifend und wirkt sehr ausgereift, für meinen Geschmack könnten
				aber noch mehr und extremere Gefühlsausbrüche stattfinden. So hört man sich doch relativ schnell
				satt an dem guten Rundling.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Scott Ward" zine="Sea of Tranquility" date="090105" rating="4/5">
			<p>	
				Niclas Frohagen is the man behind Forest of Shadows. In fact, he is Forest of Shadows. This one
				man band from Stockholm, Sweden has come up with a very forceful and gripping piece of gothic/death
				metal on this his second album. Six waves of woe weaves an intricate web of eerie atmospheric
				music wrapped around the death metal growls and somber clean vocals of Niclas. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The front cover of the CD depicts a lonely desolate shoreline that Niclas says is a place of both
				happy and sad memories from his childhood. The music that he produces may very well have taken
				root in that very spot. Like a cold gust blowing off the water, his music hits you with a chilling
				quality that digs deep down into your being. If nothing else, this album will make you reflect
				upon yourself and if like me, make you realize that there is a time and a place for loneliness
				too. 
			</p>
			<p>
				I think that this is a true solo album for a reason. It is a piece of art that can best be
				described as music to be appreciated while alone. This is the best way to get swept into the world
				that Frohagen creates for you. While much of the music could be called depressing, it does give
				you a sense of release. That is the power of music when done by someone with as much talent as
				Niclas. 
			</p>
			<p>
				For someone who can appreciate what he is trying to do here, this album is filled with some
				extremely mind boggling tales. The song "detached" is an epic piece where Frohagen's death metal
				growl is something that rakes the nerve endings that the bombastic music has laid bare. On
				"moments in solitude" he constructs a sonic landscape that is as stark as the name implies. Using
				clean vocals this time, Niclas creates a picture of someone on the edge. Life and sanity are
				fragile and he will make you feel what its like to be on the borderline.
			</p>
			<p>
				This is an album that should appeal to a wide variety of metal lovers. It should also be one that
				the goth crowd will eat up too. Lastly, if you are a connoisseur of great atmospheric music, this
				album is a must have.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Thomas Björling" zine="Close-up #107" date="081220" rating="6/10">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows är ett svenskt enmansprojekt bestående av Brommasonen Niclas Frohagen, och har
				ett antal släpp sedan tidigare i ryggen. Six Ways Of Woe är det senaste alstret, och det börjar
				otroligt bra. Inledande spåret Submission och dess efterföljare Selfdestructive består av malande
				Callisto- och Cult Of Luna-mörker - tung, suggestiv och otroligt mörk posthardcore. Tyvärr förtas
				stämningen märkvärt i och med de tre efterföljande spåren. Tempot dras upp, mörkret byts ut mot
				rensång och helt plötsligt låter allt som Katatonia. Inget fel på Katatonia, men Forest Of Shadows
				låter fortfarande som allra bäst när tempot dras ner och tyngden får fritt spelrum. Som tur är
				räddar det sista, tio minuter långa, eposet Deprived biffen med sin tyngd, svärta och dynamik.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Thomas Björling" zine="Sundsvalls tidning" date="081220">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows är ett svenskt enmansprojekt bestående av Brommasonen Niclas Frohagen, och har
				ett antal släpp sedan tidigare i ryggen. Six Ways Of Woe är det senaste alstret, och det börjar
				otroligt bra. Inledande spåret Submission och dess efterföljare Selfdestructive består av malande
				Callisto- och Cult Of Luna-mörker - tung, suggestiv och otroligt mörk posthardcore. Tyvärr förtas
				stämningen märkvärt i och med de tre efterföljande spåren. Tempot dras upp, mörkret byts ut mot
				rensång och helt plötsligt låter allt som Katatonia. Inget fel på Katatonia, men Forest Of Shadows
				låter fortfarande som allra bäst när tempot dras ner och tyngden får fritt spelrum. Som tur är
				räddar det sista, tio minuter långa, eposet Deprived biffen med sin tyngd, svärta och dynamik.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="NorthWar" zine="Kronos Mortus" date="091218" rating="9.5/10">
			<p>
				All I can say is that Niclas Frohagen is such a great man. He established Forest Of Shadows in
				1997 as a solo project, and he recorded 2 demos and 2 promos with session musicians and those were
				already a work of a genius. The first album 'Departure was released in the fall of 2004 which was
				absolutely awesome. This recent release 'Six Waves Of Woe' is just as strong as his previous works
				were.
			</p>
			<p>
				It starts with the enchanting 'Submission'. Its deep melancholic and barren darkness reminds me of
				the greatest bands such as Katatonia, Opeth or Shape Of Despair. The sound is excellent and now we
				can say that the work of Niclas is well-matured.
			</p>
			<p>
				The atmosphere is funereal, we are always about to cry and judder as it drags us slowly with this
				uneasy feeling. It's like when we hopelessly grab our last chance that we don't even trust.
			</p>
			<p>
				The atmosphere of 'Selfdestructive' is not so different but it doesn't have to be, this music
				isn't about diversity. However, we can hear some interesting "visual" sounds here which makes this
				music greater. I really like Niclas's voice, it reminds me of Renkse from Katatonia a bit. Beside
				the clean vocals we can hear deep growls also which makes the atmosphere more depressive. We can
				hear some memorisable melodies within the long and slow guitar themes and there we can feel the
				pain, suffer, bitterness and sorrow absolutely.
			</p>
			<p>
				We continue our journey on the abandoned paths in 'Detached' and 'Moments in Solitude'. These
				tracks are full of feelings, Niclas made two absolutely painful songs. The quality of the last two
				songs is also high and it's true for the whole album, each song is perfect and well-performed.
				It's a high-quality album which is highly recommended for everyone, you should also not to skip
				this effort!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Rock and metal domain" date="081128" rating="4/5">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows was founded as a solo-project in the autumn of 1997 by Niclas Frohagen. After
				having recorded the demo "the silent cry", multi-instrumentalist Micce Andersson joined the band.
				Together they reinterpreted and polished up the old material and released it as promotion material
				both on cd and online at mp3.com, all with the intention of attracting a record deal. Putting
				songs on mp3.com turned out to be a winning concept and for a couple of week's forest of shadows
				dominated the metal charts. The English company "rage of Achilles" (cult of Luna, mistress) had
				noted this and offered the band a record deal. In 2001 the mCD "where dreams turned to dust" was
				released and soon afterwards the work on a full-length album began. During its production, Niclas
				and Micce started drifting apart, not as friends but in terms of musical direction. This resulted
				in that Niclas finished the album, later on titled "departure", on his own. As if the separation
				wasn't bad enough "rage of Achilles" went out of business just as the album was finished.
				The record deal was handed over to finnish label "firedoom" who not only released the album but
				also offered a deal for yet another album. This time things went more smooth and in 2008, after
				three years of slow progression, the album "six waves of woe" was finished.
			</p>
			<p>
				The first track 'Submission' starts of with a very slow downbeat of a keyboard part then
				eventually springs into life. The track is a mix of keyboard, guitars and slow drumming beats.
				Then on the 2:40 mark vocals kick in and the tempo of the song picks up. So far judging by this
				track the music is very experimental with a traditional rock/metal riffs thrown into the mix. The
				vocals are very distorted and sometimes spaced out, while throughout the track the music shifts
				from very slow to a very upbeat tempo.
			</p>
			<p>
				The second track 'Self-destructive' pretty much starts off from where the last track kicked off.
				Keyboard effects start this track off with slow guitars while this time around vocals are clear
				and softly spoken. Then the music shifts into a more progressive hard metal feel showcasing what
				the band can bring to the table great stuff. Vocals do get heavier and shift towards some death
				metal/doom styles.
			</p>
			<p>
				The third track 'Detached' starts off with a more direct feel to it while the previous track
				assaulted our ears with some death/doom riffs this track on the other hand starts off with a prog
				feel. The track soon changes however incoarapting the doom side of things. With thunderous and big
				thick walls of riffs followed by some equally impressive breakdowns you can't help but smile after
				listening to this track Brilliant.
			</p>
			<p>
				The forth track 'Moments In Solitude' Starts off with a full assault of riffs, what this band
				offers so far is the ability to mix things up on a huge scale effective and at the same time
				genius. The track is a 9:30 minute lesson of what you can do by mixing elements of prog, doom,
				metal, rock and even death the results are breathtaking.
			</p>
			<p>
				The fifth track 'Pernicious' starts off with a more industrial metal feel to it breaking down to
				more slow melodic beat downs with slow tempo drums and then erupting again into the more heavier
				doom side of things. The only disappointing side to things is the lack of quality solos but to be
				honest it's a type of record that doesn't need them it's just a straight forward no-nonsense feast
				of Doom/Metal songs.
			</p>
			<p>
				The last track 'Deprived' is the longest track on the album clocking in at 10:30 minutes long. The
				track gets more bizarre and experimental with every riff and note played. Vocals are clean and
				somewhat slower and more direct this time around, so far the track is a slow burner then erupts in
				glorious fashion.
			</p>
			<p>
				Overall then I can't find many faults with this album. This is an album that really will appeal to
				both metal and doom heads with glorious prog elements to it and mixtures of death and clean vocals
				this a must buy. And for the album to be recorded by one person is something to be proud of as
				well.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Dario Adile" zine="Silent Scream" date="081119" rating="7.5/10.0">
			<p>
				Taken in its right verse, the new album of Forest Of Shadows can give wide satisfactions. The
				biggest merit of "Six Waves Of Woe" is that of succeeding in reaching an ideal synthesis between
				the two faces of the same medal, that of doom/gothic metal. In short: instrumentally speaking the
				scores this one man band writes are slow and heavy mostly, revealing the huge influence they have
				from the historical bands of the field like, for example and just to mention the closest, My Dying
				Bride. But it's also true Forest Of Shadows have the brightness not to exaggerate, not to let go
				some depressive chocking excess, they keep our attention always high and fill us with melancholia
				without making us lose our senses. We're in front of square riffs with no compromises, then, but
				be aware this album is quite intelligible, thanks to the melodic scores which are not entrusted to
				the lead guitars only, but also to a clean and painful vocal approach that recalls the next to
				last Lacrimas Profundere. If you think depressive doom is too burdening, but dark metal too light,
				here's "Six Waves Of Woe": the ideal for your needs.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Lord Obirah" zine="Heavyhardes.de" date="081119">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows waren ursprünglich als Ein-Mann-Projekt von Niclas Frohagen konzpiert. Niclas
				holte sich aber recht schnell verschiedene Mitstreiter ins Boot, nur um nach einigen Lineup-
				Wechseln letztendlich wieder allein dazustehen. Nun zieht er Forest Of Shadows also wie
				ursprünglich geplant allein auf und legt mit Six Waves Of Woe sein zweites Album vor.
			</p>
			<p>
				Darauf zelebriert Niclas sehr düsteren Doom Metal. Die Songs sind allesamt sehr opulent arrangiert
				und knacken teilweise die zehn-Minuten-Marke. Irgendwie müssen bei insgesamt sechs Tracks ja knapp
				48 Minuten Spielzeit rausspringen. In dieser Zeit webt Niclas eine feine melancholische Melodie
				nach der anderen und kreiert genau die richtige Stimmung, die zur derzeitigen Wetterlage passt.
				Düster und bedrohlich walzen die Riffs voran und werden hin und wieder durch einige
				Keyboardeinsprengsel ergänzt. Dazu gesellt sich tiefer Growlgesang, wie man ihn von Swallow The
				Sun oder ähnlich gelagerten Combos kennt. Aber auch vor cleanen Melodien verschließt sich Niclas
				nicht, verglichen mit den Growls kommen diese aber eher selten zum Einsatz. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Und das ist meiner Meinung nach auch gut so, denn der Klargesang ist weit nicht so überzeugend wie
				die Growls und läuft mir nicht wirklich gut rein. Ansonsten ist Six Waves Of Woe genau der
				richtige Soundtrack für diese Jahreszeit und sollte alle Fans von frühen Anathema, My Dying Bride
				oder erwähnten Swallow The Sun mehr als begeistern!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Harry" zine="Metal Temple" date="081201" rating="2.5/5.0">
			<p>
				FOREST OF SHADOWS is not new in the music industry. This one man band is "alive" for over ten
				years. But, to tell you the truth, this is the first time I come across him and his doom-
				atmospheric Metal.
			</p>
			<p>
				The Sweden-based band's history passed through hundreds of waves. During those eleven years,
				they've released a demo, a mini CD and their debut album. After the demo Niklas joined forces with
				Micce Andersson, but he left the band just before the mini CD "Where Dreams Turned To Dust" came
				out. Until that time, many musicians passed from the band's lineup, but probably Niklas decided to
				move along alone. So he recorded his debut album "Departure" in 2004 after having to find a new
				label since Rage Of Achilles Records went out of bussiness.
			</p>
			<p>
				So here we are with his second effort "Six Waves Of Woe". From the four older songs I have
				listened to in order to judge, as far as I can do, the new album, well, I can't find any huge
				changes in the way that he composes music. The production is for sure better. As for the music
				itself, I can say that it is somewhere between KATATONIA, SWALLOW THE SUN and CULT OF LUNA. The
				way that the compositions are building up is not bad, but on the other hand, I believe that they
				don't have that "something" that will make them distinguish from other bands' songs. Even though I
				do have my feet on earth and I know that it's almost impossible to write something unique and
				innovational in the dark doom Metal field, you have to give that something in your work. 
			</p>
			<p>
				"Six Waves Of Woe" is far from saying it's a bad album. You will listen to some nice ideas and
				Niklas did make a step forward, but I believe he has to do something to put more inspiration in
				his work. Oh, and do something with the clean vocals. If my ears are in good shape after the two
				live shows during the weekend, he has to work a lot on those.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Adrian" zine="NOIZZ webzine" date="081201" rating="7.75/10.00">
			<p>
				Segundo larga duración para el proyecto de este sueco llamado Niclas Frohagen, quien está detrás
				de FOREST OF SHADOWS. Aunque en el pasado la banda contó con algún miembro más, en la actualidad
				es el propio Niclas quien se encarga de todo, desde la composición de los temas hasta la grabación
				de todos los instrumentos. Para este nuevo álbum, editado por el sello finlandés Firedoom Music
				(Firebox), se lo ha tomado con paciencia y ha pasado tres años trabajando que han dado como
				resultado este "Six	Waves Of Woe" que impregna con su melancolía otoñal.
			</p>
			<p>
				Tiempos lentos y melodías sombrías sumergen al oyente en una profunda y desesperante, a la par que
				atrayente, atmósfera de melancolía. Lo cierto es que con cada escucha esta sensación de
				somnolencia otoñal que provoca el drama sonoro de FOREST OF SHADOWS, se hace cada vez más y más
				adictiva. Para ello cuenta con unos eficaces ritmos Doom, melodías oníricas de teclado, guitarras
				sombrías, voces limpias y voces de ultratumba... vamos elementos típicos dentro del Doom Metal, o
				Melancholic Metal como pone en su hoja promocional. De todas formas en este trabajo se diluyen
				influencias muy dispares que van desde los sonidos ambientales hasta el Doom más áspero, el Metal
				y el Gothic Rock actual, todo ello muy bien mezclado para no perder la esencia que caracteriza a
				FOREST OF SHADOWS, que no es otra que la melancolía. Algunas de las referencias sonoras que
				enseguida vienen a la cabeza cunado se escucha este trabajo son principalmente las de KATATONIA o
				SHAPE OF DESPAIR. Y es que a lo largo de los seis temas que componen este "Six Waves Of Woe"
				pasamos de las melodías delicadas al desgarro más sombrío y lúgubre sin apenas darnos cuenta.
				Temas lentos, profundos, atmosféricos,... dramáticos en definitiva.
			</p>
			<p>
				Si te gustan los discos impregnados en oscuridad y melancolía que combinan dulzura y crudeza este
				disco no te defraudará. Llámalo Doom o Melancholic Metal, da lo mismo puesto que lo que aquí vas a
				encontrar es drama en estado puro.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Iskharian" zine="Schwarze-News.de" date="081124" rating="8/10">
			<p>
				Nach vier Jahren Funkstille seit dem letzten Album "Departure" und dem mehr als gelungenen
				Coverbeitrag "Rainroom" auf der Katatonia-Tribute CD "December songs" hat Forest of shadows
				Mastermind Niclas Frohagen den von mir lange erwarteten Nachfolger "Six waves of woe" über Firebox
				veröffentlicht. Und was soll man sagen? Die Wartezeit hat sich mehr als gelohnt.
			</p>
			<p>
				Hatte "Departure" noch so diverse Längen, was Songaufbau und Abwechslung betraf, gelingt es dem
				Schweden mit "Six waves of woe" genau diese Fehler auszumerzen und ein durchwegs spannendes und
				vor allem ein bis aufs Äußerste melancholisches Klangwerk zu erschaffen, wie es nur selten in
				dieser Intensität gelingt. So bewegen sich die sechs Songs zwischen der erschütternden Traurigkeit
				Antimatters und einer Wehmut, welche ich bisher nur im Black Metal erfahren durfte.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Submission" beginnt mit ruhigen Percussions und einer träumerischen Gitarrenmelodie, um mit
				Einsetzen des Schlagzeuges und des schrammelig verzerrten Basses die Wiege für Herrn Frohagens
				zerbrechlich wirkenden aber dennoch wunderbar klaren Gesang zu betten. Die Melodie zu Beginn
				fliesst durch den Song und verändert sich immer weiter, bis zu ihrem absoluten Höhepunkt an
				Intensität, bei der man am liebsten vor Freude über diese atemberaubenden Klänge hemmungslos in
				Tränen ausbrechen möchte.
			</p>
			<p>
				Hiermit ist dann auch die Weiche gestellt für "Selfdestructive", welches dort weiter macht, wo der
				Opener aufhörte. Der Aufbau ist ähnlich, erst ruhige perkussive Töne, um dann mit den ersten
				Growls des Albums den Hörer immer tiefer in seinen Bann zu ziehen. Und auch hier dominiert eine
				durch Keyboards unterstützte wiederum herrlich wehmütige Melodie den Achtminüter und ebenso wird
				der Spannungsbogen wieder komplett ausgereizt, um das Lied so ruhig wie es begann enden zu lassen.
			</p>
			<p>
				Nahtlos schließt "Detached" an, diesmal weniger auf einen Höhepunkt ausgerichtet, sondern immer im
				Stimmungswechsel zwischen Ruhe und Sturm der Gefühle. Etwas weniger eingängig, wie die
				voranggegangenen Songs, doch nicht minder begeisternd, schafft man es doch hier Katatonia
				einfließen zu lassen ohne abzukupfern.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Moments of solitude" geht gleich in die Vollen und legt mit treibendem Drumming und kräftigen
				Growls einen weiteren Höhepunkt des Album vor. Die ruhigen Passagen erinnern bisweilen an Swallow
				the sun, was man durchaus als großes Kompliment verstehen darf. Gegen Ende wird das Stück immer
				ruhiger, die Einsamkeit nimmt einen immer mehr gefangen und kein Ausweg scheint in Sicht bis zum
				Schluss nur noch leise Töne dem Leben des Stückes ein Ende setzen.
			</p>
			<p>
				Das kürzeste Stück "Pernicious" ist vielleicht das schwächste Stücke des Albums, könnte es doch
				auch auf einem aktuelleren Album von Katatonia stehen. Hier merkt man dem cleanen Gesang Niclas
				Frohagens langsam seine Grenzen an. Es fehlt einfach der Ausdruck und die Kraft in seiner Stimme,
				wie es ein Jonas Renkse mit Bravour zu erfüllen vermag. Man hat auch langsam das Gefühl dem Album
				geht etwas die Luft aus, auch wenn man mit "Deprived" noch einmal ein richtig gutes Stück bieten
				kann, welches wieder elegant zwischen ruhiger Schönheit und harter Eleganz pendelt und das Album
				mit Percussions zu seinem Ende zu führt.
			</p>
			<p>
				Der Kreis schließt sich und man ist wieder an der selben Stelle, wie zu Beginn und man versucht
				von Neuem sich mit den "Six waves of woe" in tiefste Melancholie entführen zu lassen.
			</p>
			<p>
				Fazit: Ein wunderbares Album voller mitreißender Melodien, perfekt in Szene gesetzt durch Ton und
				Verpackung. Wer mit den im Review genannten Bands etwas anfangen kann, sollte auf jeden Fall mehr
				als nur ein Ohr riskieren und sich das Album zulegen. Für eine höhere Bewertung reicht es aber
				(noch) nicht, da das Album gegen Ende doch nicht mehr ganz die hohe Qualität der ersten beiden
				Tracks halten kann.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Autothrall" zine="From the Dust Returned" date="081101" rating="7/10">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows released a good debut in Departure a few years back, and this sophomore effort
				shows an increase in both maturity and depth to Niclas Frohagen's brand of swelling, transcendent
				doom. Consider that this is the work of a single man and you'll be even more impressed.
			</p>
			<p>
				Six Waves of Woe is a pretty direct title; each of these six songs is an emblem of sadness upon a
				tear-stained, frozen landscape. "Submission" takes off with some very minimal atmosphere,
				percussion and some light guitar chords breeding a somber theme, then picking it up with driving
				gothic doom and the man's sad, clean vocals. "Selfdestructive" once again starts things out
				slowly, but very catchy, until crushing you with its weight. Though his clean vocals are
				effective, I vastly prefer his growling which kicks in with this track. "Detached" is another song
				in roughly the same formula, but I was most pleased with "Moments in Solitude" which just starts
				out directly with a wall of soaring doom and downward spiral of melody. "Pernicious" also cuts
				straight to the chase, another of my favorites here. The closer "Deprived" has a similar format to
				the first few tracks but it's also quite good. As far as lyrics, well...we have an expression 'qq
				a little more' in online gaming, and this would probably apply to these very depressing words. But
				for the style of music they fit beautifully.
			</p>
			<p>
				You truly can't lose here if you are a fan of the crushing gothic death/doom of early Anathema,
				Paradise Lost, or My Dying Bride. But Six Waves of Woe will likewise appeal to fans of the more
				driving, melodic style of Katatonia, Rapture or Daylight Dies. Either way, you win (or lose, it's
				doom after all). Recommended to ruin those last few warm, sunny days of your year. Unless you live
				where it's warm all year round, in which case...fuck you!?
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="departure | cd 2004">
		<item author="Utku" zine="Sonic Splendour magazine" date="050925">
			<p>
				Last time I listened to Shape Of Despair, I was about to faint. That type of slow, obscure doom has
				got a blood-draining impact on my metabolism but Forest Of Shadows is another story. Departure
				comprises one of the most minimalist, depressive and monotonous possible musical expression of all
				times, nevertheless dull is the last adjective I would employ in this review. The band manages to
				sound milder and to my perception comes close to Plan E inbetween those compact and conventional
				doom riffs parade. No problems in terms of being accessible and listenable as long as you are sure
				to catch up the right mood. Still this album might be fatal for those who equate listening to metal
				with driving an F1.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Undercraft" zine="Metal Storm" date="050723" rating="9/10">
			<p>
				The record lasts more than one hour. It only has 5 songs. Art booklet is on white and black. Well,
				I'm pretty sure this isn't Grindcore, but Doom Metal. Forest of Shadows is a Swedish one-man project,
				although in the past it had band members, they came and went, and at the end mastermind of the
				project, Niclas Frohagen stood alone, and composed this "Departure," the first full length of Forest
				Of Shadows. Music is somber, dark, gloomy, slow, and aggressive, filled with anguish, loneliness,
				despair, desperately looking for something. someone. Songs are quite long, clocking between 10-15
				minutes each, but they have a strange bipolarity, a acceptable duality that makes them quite
				enjoyable all through their length, id est, they don't get boring. Let's take for example, opener
				track, "Sleeping Death" begins slow, with wailing vocals, a gloomy piano and percussion in the back,
				this goes for about 7 minutes, and then the guitars and the growls break the tranquility of the first
				half of the song. Second part is harsh, but melancholic, Forest Of Shadows never looses the dramatic
				touch in their music, whether is a slow part or a harsh one. "November Dream" Follows the same
				architecture of the previous song, weepy vocals and slow melancholic parts, followed by a growl
				outburst but always maintaining the sorrowful atmosphere. " Bleak Dominion" is a excellent
				instrumental song, no vocals and no lyrics to express the misery, the music speaks for itself. "Open
				Wound" is a catchy song, with more rhythm and melodies than the previous ones, the lead guitars marks
				a catchy line all through the song. Last and title song "Departure" is a pounding track, with
				excellent arrangements and a beautiful growling section, a hymn to the wretched. Forest Of Shadows
				offer us an album filled to the brim of despondency, sorrow and many other tragic feelings, while
				compositions are quite simple, the music works perfectly to bring you down in a matter of seconds.
				This album is a masterpiece. So, be warned, prepare to be doomed.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Cryptic Madness" date="050601" rating="6/6">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows nous revient après une très longue attente. Après un véritable chef d'oeuvre de
				trois pistes, ce duo, maintenant devenu one-man-band, nous produit une vraie perle. Ça prend du cran
				pour sortir un truc de la sorte après seulement un mcd et quelques démos... c'est une évolution très
				marquée. On voit que pour Niclas il fallait déjà sortir des sentiers battus. Enfin un souffle de
				renouveau sur un style parfois trop redondant.
			</p>
			<p>
				FoS nous offre donc ici un disque de cinq pistes mais d'une durée de plus d'une heure. Fini le doom
				traditionnel, on passe maintenant à un doom original mais gardant toujours cette si belle touche de
				mélancolie que FoS a su exercer sur ces précédentes sorties. Le son est très top, la basse hyper
				présente. La sonorité est tout simplement grandiose.
			</p>
			<p>	
				Ce qui nous marque dès le départ est l'utilisation des keyboards et autres bruits électroniques. Le
				début du disque avec « Sleeping Death » nous met immédiatement dans l'ambiance et dans la nouvelle
				lignée du disque. Ça prend plus de huit minutes avant de voir l'élément métal arriver. Mais c'est
				tout simplement sublime. Une belle progression avec le rythme simple, une guitare sèche et une voix
				claire. La voix claire est utilisée à plusieurs moments sur ce disque qui rend le tout encore plus
				mélancolique, mais il ne faut pas oublier les bonnes parties doom. La voix est toujours aussi
				guturale et triste. Les guitares qui sont accompagnés par le clavier augmentent l'atmosphère
				grandiose et irréelle du disque. Le clavier est très présent sur le disque. Par moment pour faire une
				boîte à rythme, à d'autres moments pour accompagner les guitares. L'utilisation du piano apporte
				également son lot de tristesse au disque. Le rythme du disque est plutôt lent et le bout le plus 
				rapide est à la toute fin du disque. Chaque piste ressort du lot.
			</p>
			<p>
				Enfin, pour certains la déception fût grande. J'ai même vu des gens, ici sur CM, qui ont vendu le
				disque après une seule écoute. L'utilisation d'éléments électroniques ainsi qu'un doom traditionnel
				légèrement mis de côté ont sûrement fait peur à ces derniers. Pour ma part, étant un véritable
				amateur de musique électronique ainsi que de musique ambiante, je ne peux qu'apprécier ce subtile
				mélange avec un doom des plus mélancoliques. FoS a toujours été pour moi un des meilleures groupes
				de Doom dès ma première écoute et continura de le rester. Ne tombant pas dans le cercle du doom
				traditionnel et morne, Niclas a su bien guider sa musique et transmettre une personnalité bien
				distincte au tout. Un groupe qui promet, qui nous frappe par sa grande maturité. Trois ans d'écart
				avec le dernier album... si c'est le temps que ça prend pour avoir une musique de qualité, je suis
				prêt à m'armer de patience.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Black Hole" zine="Les Accros du Metal" date="050601">
			<p>
				Forest of shadows est le projet solo du suédois Nicolas Frohagen. Cet homme orchestre délivre un doom
				très lent et pathétique non sans rappeler Reverend Bizarre avec plus de richesse dans les harmonies
				musicales mais en proposant un ensemble moins percutant car relativement stéréotypé. Sleeping Death
				est assez interminable à démarrer et chanté très linéairement. Heureusement vers la moitié de ses
				presque 17 minutes, les riffs s'alourdissent et une voix death psalmodiée vient hanter l'atmosphère
				conférant à la fin de ce titre un intérêt bien supérieur à celui du début. November dream enchaîne
				avec les mêmes accents. Le chant manque singulièrement de puissance et est couvert par des harmonies
				de guitare très mélancoliques. Là encore, il ne s'agit pas d'un travail inintéressant mais quel
				intérêt y a t'il à faire durer des morceaux jusqu'à l'infini.L'instrumental Bleak Dormition ne dure
				que 5 minutes ce qui est appréciable et propose des apports au clavier d'un assez joli effet.A partir
				d' Open wound, on se dit que l'on a déjà entendu ce morceau précédemment tant il s'inscrit dans la
				ligne de ce qui a déjà été entendu avant. Cette fois ci, il se termine interminablement ce qui est
				paradoxal mais tellement vrai. Departure est un chouia plus rapide et, oh miracle ! opère quelques
				changements de rythme. Mais bien sûr, cela n'a rien à voir avec du metal prog. Ah et puis toujours ce
				chant laconique sous mixé ce qui est dommage car les harmonies de ce titre sont plutôt sympathiques
				par rapport aux autres morceaux.Vous l'aurez compris, il ne s'agit pas d'un album qui va
				révolutionner le genre mais, pour les fans de doom, il y a moyen d'y trouver cependant son compte.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Shan Siva" zine="Battle Helm" date="050410">
			<p>
				FoS remind me heavily of In The Woods, with its heavy atmospherics coupled with a guitar driven core.
				However, FoS isn't a band as much as its the 1 man project of one Niclas Frohagen who plays all
				instruments, sings, composes, records and engineers. What I like about 'Departure' is its great
				variety in sounds from the use of violins to mellotrons to a djembe - which are successfully
				integrated into the death like sound to create the sad yet passionate music that is FoS. Its like the
				musical expression of autumn with its darkening colours,death and decay as trees shed their leaves
				which fall to amass on soggy forest paths - yeah, I see where you're coming from Niclas. And I
				appreciate it.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Benjamin Dreßel" zine="bloodchamber.de" date="050404" rating="10/10">
			<p>
				Soloprojekte werden ja zumeist von Menschen gemacht, die in Bezug auf ihren musikalischen Weg
				keinerlei Zugeständnisse und Einschränkungen haben wollen. Der künstlerisch freie Geist muss sich
				entfalten, ohne dabei durch andere Bandmitglieder behindert zu werden, oder von ihnen in den
				Gefühlsausbrüchen eingeschränkt zu werden. FOREST OF SHADOWS aus Schweden ist ein solches Projekt,
				mit dem Mainman Niclas Frohagen keinerlei Kompromisse eingehen wollte. Herausgekommen dabei ist
				"Departure", ein einstündiges Werk tiefster Tristesse, Trauer, Hilflosigkeit, Verzweiflung,
				Dunkelheit, und doch einem Schimmer Licht in all dem düsteren Grau.
			</p>
			<p>
				Herr Frohagen hat ein Faible für lange Stücke, was sich mit einem Blick auf die Tracklist leicht
				nachvollziehen lässt. Und in der Tat ist kein Stück außer dem Instrumental "Bleak Dormition" kürzer
				als zehn Minuten. Doch in diese ewig scheinende Zeit verpackt der Schwede so dermaßen viele Gefühle
				und magische Momente, die den Hörer in fast schon beängstigender Weise berühren, dass so etwas wie
				Langeweile nicht im Traum aufkommen könnte. Diese vertonten Gefühle bestehen aus getragenen,
				wunderschönen Melodien, die einen zugleich in die tiefsten Abgründe drücken als auch mit einer Träne
				der Hoffnung verweilen lassen. Der schüchterne cleane Gesang steuert dazu einen gewaltigen Teil bei,
				wohingegen die mit Growls unterlegten Passagen einem Ausbruch gleichkommen, der allen Schmerz von
				einem nehmen soll, den die Welt einem so auferlegt. Kleine elektronische Spielereien wie ein paar
				nette Loops (nichts großes, nur ganz subtil eingestreut) versüßen einem dabei die Ruhe vor dem Sturm,
				sozusagen in den ruhigen Passagen, die auf "Departure" eine durchaus große Rolle einnehmen, und dabei
				so wundervoll träumerisch melancholisch kommen, wie man es sonst nur von wenigen Bands gewohnt ist.
				Die endgültige Atmosphäre kommt durch den immer wieder gerne gehörten Hall Effekt, der in diesem Fall
				nicht übertrieben vorhanden ist, aber dennoch sowohl Tiefe als auch Dramatik, als auch Epik
				versprüht. Songwriterisch werden hier die erhabensten Momente aus Death Doom, und Epic Doom
				miteinander verknüpft, und zu unvergesslichen Hymnen verpackt, deren Verdaulichkeit insgesamt
				vielleicht etwas leichter sein dürfte als in extremeren Bereichen des Genres, trotzdem aber immer
				sämtliche Wurzeln dieser Musik beinhaltet.
			</p>
			<p>
				Mit diesem Werk hat Niclas Frohagen bewiesen, wie gut ein Soloprojekt funktionieren kann, wenn man
				wirklich keine Kompromisse eingeht. "Departure" ist vertontes Gefühl - wie eine Reise durch immer
				wiederkehrende Phasen der Emotion. Und dabei so wunderschön und doch verhängnisvoll. Diese Platte
				muss man fühlen. Mehr als nur ein Highlight am verhangenen Himmel der Neuveröffentlichungen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Dave" zine="clonemetal.dk" date="050319">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows har siden ca. 1997 rumsteret rundt på nettet, hvor de via adskillige demoer lagt ud
				på hedengangne mp3.com manifesterede sig som et lovende, men ikke synderligt originalt doom-metal
				band. Jeg skriver "de" i ovenstående, for selvom Forest of Shadows i dag er et enmands-band kun
				bestående af svenske Niclas Frohagen, har der før i tiden været flere medlemmer indover. "Departure"
				er bandets første fuldlængde album og tilblivelsen har ikke været helt ligetil. Flere afbrudte
				studiesessions, skriftende medlemmer, omarrangerede og omskrevne numre plus et enkelt pladeselskab
				der gik konkurs har forsinket albummet der oprindeligt skulle have været ude i 2002 som opfølger til
				bandets første egentlige EP "Where Dreams Turn to Dust" fra 2001.
			</p>
			<p>
				Alt dette har dog ikke været forgæves for Forest of Shadows, for musikken på "Departure" vidner om et
				noget mere modent og selvstændigt band, end hvad man før har hørt fra den kant. Åbningsnummeret
				"Sleeping Death", der strækker sig over 16 minutter, er en stærk opvisning i monotoni drevet lige
				akkurat så langt ud som nummeret kan bære. Der indledes dæmpet med Rhodes piano og minimalistiske
				trommer, der næsten vækker minder om Portishead og Antimatter, og udvikler sig derfra langsomt med
				mere og mere guitar og growlet vokal. Guitarens monotone riffs kan minde om ældre Katatonia og
				musikken opbygger på mange måder en lignende depressiv og hypnotisk stemning.
			</p>
			<p>
				Hvor bandets musik i gamle dage ofte bød på violin og tværfløjte er det tangentinstrumenter som
				Rhodes, piano og mellotron der farver lyduniverset på denne plade. Dette er med til at give musikken
				en mere tidløs og næsten tilbagelænet karakter der klæder den godt. Hvis musikken bliver ved at med
				at udvikle sig i en mere selvstændig retning er jeg sikker på at næste album bliver fantastisk i
				stedet for bare rigtig rigtigt godt. Og lad os så håbe på at vi ikke skal vente lige så længe på det
				denne gang.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Shadow" zine="Harm Magazine" date="050318" rating="7/10">
			<p>
				On Departure, Niclas Frohagen is acting as a one man band by playing everything being heard. He's
				also responsible for the recording and mixing. The compositions are his even if Micce Anderson
				co-wrote a lot of the material included.
			</p>
			<p>
				It took nearly four years to bring this album to life which got re-written three times. Departure is
				made of four long songs and a short instrumental "Bleak Dormition" (5:18). How long are the others?
				Well, lasting anywhere from ten to seventeen minutes and even if I'm a fan of doom and usually don't
				mind those long lasting pleasures, I must say I found that, at times, the compositions got a bit
				boring and over lasting. Maybe due to their predictability because what we have is good doom with
				shifts from melodic / calm passages and clean vocals to heavier mode and the usual death vocals that
				go with it. The mood could be calm, ambient, sad, and dramatic to quite intense in the heavier
				moments. Some nice keyboard and a few acoustic guitar parts have been included. Even if the sound
				production is excellent, we can hear scratches on every composition. Samplings or a default on my
				copy I don't know but one thing for sure is that it is annoying.
			</p>
			<p>
				The info sheet says this : "the simplistic and monotonous expression has moved to another level". If
				you want a good but monotonous doom metal album, Departure is where to begin your search.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="In Extremis" date="050310">
			<p>
				Au royaume du one-man-band, la Scandinavie a toujours eu une place de choix. Catégorie doom mélodique
				et dépressif, ce projet de Niclas Frohagen (suédois de son état) sort ce premier album après un mcd
				qui aura vu le jour chez Rage of Achilles en 2001. Très atmosphérique et minimaliste, saupoudré
				d'influences folk scandinaves, ce doom ne propose rien de vraiment excitant. Pourtant le bonhomme
				n'hésite pas à utiliser avec parcimonie quelques instruments inappropriés d'habitude comme le
				mellotron, le djembe, les samples au milieu d'un enchevêtrement de piano, violons et flûte beaucoup
				plus traditionnels quant à eux. Mais l'ossature principale de la musique de Forest of Shadows tient
				dans ces guitares imposantes qui prennent une place gigantesque. Paradoxalement pas vraiment de
				riffs décoiffent l'auditeur comme chez Cathedral ou Reverend Bizarre, mais plutôt des guitares
				utilisées en nappes atmosphériques. Et c'est bien là que le bas blesse. Ce qui rend pénible et
				plombe l'écoute de ce disque, ce sont ces ambiances éthérées hyper nombreuses qui cassent le rythme
				de l'opus. Les trop rares exceptions où l'intensité soudainement décolle sont très vite tempérées
				par des passages d'une étouffante monotonie dignes d'un My Dying Bride sous prozac. Le chant a beau
				être assez varié entre death-growls et un style plus plaintif à la Anathema, rien n'y fait
				malheureusement. On reste dans un état proche du coma.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Undercraft" zine="Metal Storm" date="050221" rating="8.7/10">
			<p>
				The record last more than one hour. It only has 5 songs. Art and booklet is on white and black. Well,
				I'm pretty sure this isn't Grindcore, but Doom Metal. Forest of Shadows is a Swedish one-man project,
				although in the past it had band members, they came and went, and at the end mastermind of the
				project, Niclas Frohagen stood alone, and composed this "Departure", the first full length of Forest
				Of Shadows
			</p>
			<p>
				Music is somber, dark, gloomy, slow, and aggressive, filled with anguish, loneliness, despair,
				desperately looking for something. someone.Songs are quite long, clocking between 10-15 minutes
				each, but they have a strange bipolarity, a acceptable duality that makes them quite enjoyable all
				through their length, id est, they don't get boring.
			</p>
			<p>
				Let's take for example, opener track, "Sleeping Death" begins slow, with wailing vocals, a gloomy
				piano and percussion in the back, this goes for about 7 minutes, and then the guitars and the growls
				break the tranquility of the first half of the song. Second part is harsh, but melancholic, Forest
				Of Shadows never looses the dramatic touch in their music, whether is a slow part or a harsh one.
			</p>
			<p>
				"November Dream" Follows the same architecture than the previous song, weepy vocals and slow
				melancholic parts, followed by a growl outburst but always maintaining the sorrowful atmosphere.
				"Bleak Dominion" is a excellent instrumental song, no vocals and no lyrics to express the misery,
				the music speaks for itself. "Open Wound" is a catchy song, with more rhythm and melodies than the
				previous ones, the lead guitars marks a catchy line all through the song. Last and title song
				"Departure" is a pounding track, with excellent arrangements and a beautiful growling section, a
				hymn to the wretched.
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows offer us an album filled to the brim of despondency, sorrow and many other tragic
				feelings, while compositions are quite simple, the music works perfectly to bring you down in a
				matter of seconds. So, be warned, prepare to be doomed.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Robert Sun" zine="Mirgilus Siculorum" date="050210" rating="7.5/10">
			<p>
				A sved Forest Of Shadows '97-ben alakult, az eltelt evek alatt tobb EP-t es promo-CD-t
				megjelentettek, viszont a Departure az 1. nagylemeze "zenekar"-nak, amit jelenleg Niclas Frohagen
				alkot egymaga. Az 5 dalos, 60 percet meghalado lemezre Niclas jatszott fel minden hangszert es a
				produceri munkakat is egymagaban vegezte el. A korabbi anyagokon a Forest Of Shadows folk elemekkel
				gazdagitott doom/death metal-t jatszott, sokszor a korai Katatonia-t juttatva eszembe. Stilust most
				sem valtott Niclas, de azert formalodott a zeneje. A nyito Sleeping Death elso 8 perce az
				Antimatter-t idezi a maga ambient-es, mar-mar elektro-s megoldasaival. Persze aztan bejonnek a
				riffek, a hangulatos gitarszolok, igy tudatva velunk, hogy a Forest Of Shadows a hatasok ellenere
				megmaradt metal zenenek. Niclas hangja is fejlodott az eltelt evek soran, annak ellenere, hogy nem
				egy hangszalakrobata, igyekszik minel jobban kihasznalni az adottsagait. A korai anyagokat gazdagito
				hegedu sajnos nem kapott helyet a lemezen, viszont a hangzast sok helyen gazdagitja a zongora, a
				rhode, a djembe es a mellotron, es a death/doom riffeken kivul most is jelen vannak az akusztikus,
				folkos gitartemak. Nem egy konnyu hallgatnivalo a Departure a maga 10-15 perces dalaival, de akik
				szeretik a massziv, de melodikus doom/death metal-t, azoknak szinte kotelezo ez a vegletekig
				kidolgozott lemez beszerzese.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="KS" zine="Masterful Magazine" date="050210" rating="10/10">
			<p>
				Pewnie kazdy zna takie przyslowie jak "twardy orzech do zgryzienia". O ile pierwsze wydawnictwo
				Firedoom, mowa o Aarni, bylo dla mnie niczym kokos, to "Departure" (plyta równiez nielatwa w
				odbiorze i poczatkowo odpychajaca) jest przy niej jak fistaszek w tej swojej mientkiej skorupce.
				Forest of Shadows to projekt niejakiego Niclasa Frohagena grajacego na wszystkich instrumentach i
				spiewajacego piosenki. Ma on juz na swoim koncie mini - album "When Dreams Turns to Dust" wydany w
				2001 roku przez Rage of Achilles, a "Departure" to pierwszy pelny album tego projektu. Piec utworów
				i ponad godzina muzyki - jak sie domyslacie sie, Forest of Shadows nie wycina grinda. Plyta ta to
				wrecz esencja smutku, lecz bez zadnego lalusiowania. W obecnych czasach natrafienie na klasowy,
				dolujacy i heteroseksualny przede wszystkim album nie jest rzecza latwa, wiec rodzynki takie jak
				"Departure" ciesza tym bardziej. Forest of Shadows to przede wszystkim emocje, którymi wrecz ocieka.
				Trudno ta muzyke rozkladac na czynniki pierwsze i podniecac sie np. riffem do kawalka takiego, gra
				basu w srakim i kanonada perkusyjna w owakim. Zawartosc tego krazka bardziej bowiem chlonie sie, niz
				slucha. Twórca "Departure" nie uniknal rzecz jasna wplywów, gdyz na tym albumie mozemy uslyszec echa
				wszystkiego, co najsmutniejsze. Niclas bardzo ciekawie polaczyl klimaty znane z muzyki typu
				Antimatter, Virgin Black czy Autumnblaze z innym biegunem rozpaczy: Unholy, My Dying Bride itd.
				Poczatkowo nagle przejscia z jednej stylistyki do drugiej dosc mocno mnie razily, niemniej jednak
				juz w polowie plyty zrozumialem, ze ma to sens, bo nie pociaga to za soba zmiany klimatu.
				Jakkolwiek by nie dywagowac, to i tak wychodzi na to, ze Forest of Shadows jest wyjatkowym tworem.
				Abstrahujac juz od tego, ze wiekszosc nagranego kiedykolwiek "klimatycznego" metalu umie stworzyc co
				najwyzej klimat wiejskiego wesela (vide polska scena), to "Departure" zachwyca nie dlatego, ze
				poziom "konkurencji" jest zalosny. To wyjatkowa plyta i milo by bylo, jakby ten projekt na stale
				wpisal sie w kanon gatunku. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Hawk" zine="The Metal Observer" date="050207" rating="9.5/10">
			<p>
				At first, I thought our Alex wants to kidding me with this "Departure" CD from FOREST OF SHADOWS.
				"Why does this clown send me Dark Wave-CD?", were my first thoughts. The opener "Sleeping Death"
				starts with clean, wailing vocals, a monotonous, clumsy drumming and gloomy piano parts and the
				first six minutes are very dragging until the tempo then starts to increase slowly. It sounds partly
				like a mixture of AMORPHIS in their "Tales From The Thousand Lakes" period, DREADFUL SHADOWS and
				PARAMAECIUM.
			</p>
			<p>
				This is also the direction for all five tracks. Sluggish, gloomy, haunting and very calm parts
				change with brutal Metal elements and serve for an incredible tension. This album isn't very
				diversified but it's damn intense. There are some similarities to LAKE OF TEARS milestone
				"Headstones", just listen to the instrumental "Black Dormition", just beautiful.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Open Wound" is a song, which could also please some OPETH fans. Not to forget is the title track,
				a fantastic hymn to darkness, just divine!!! 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Fjordi" zine="Tartarean Desire" date="050206" rating="7.5/10">
			<p>
				It would be so easy to think Forest Of Shadows is just another band in the nowadays ever growing doom
				metal scene... However, for a weird reason beyond my comprehension Firebox Records has made it again;
				definitely these guys know the essence of the business -to sign good bands-, and their taste
				recruiting new jewels is amongst the best on the face of Earth. In the last times they have split the
				label in Firebox and Firedoom; it´s pretty clear what we´re going to find in the last of these: doom
				metal, and I´d say doom metal at its best. One of these fine doom acts is Forest Of Shadows. Their
				brand of music,	if not original, is at least beyond cliches and dead typical patterns. Here we have a
				band quite competent and brave: a release consisting of five tracks lasting around 61 minutes is bold
				in these commercial times, to say the least. I must admit I thought they were Finnish and funeral
				doom, since	most of the depressive bands in the Firebox roster are based there and play that sort of
				music. In fact they are Swedish, or he is Swedish, since we´re talking about a one-man band.
				Moreover, it´s not exactly funeral nor ultra slow doom what they play, despite in some moments the
				atmosphere has quite a few things in common with Shape Of Despair and co. I mean, in "Departure" one
				really can find those solid, funeral march-like, chord sequences with growls conducting the pace. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Anyway, other passages are far away from those moments. Mellower parts with soft voice, emotionally
				loaded, make this album more varied and those listeners unwilling to check the classic Skepticism
				stuff could really appreciate this band. The first song is very significant when describing the music
				of Forest Of Shadows: long songs (yes, for this opening track lasts for 16 minutes...), deeply dour
				but charming at the same time, providing variation in the right measure. If you remember Katatonia´s
				"Brave Murder Day" third song, "Day", with that neo-gothic hazy melancholic feeling, you can make
				yourself a picture of the starting minutes of "Sleeping Death", that run in the same vein. Then, the
				wrath of powerful crushing doom riffs appears, riffs devotees of the most depressive bands on Earth.
				And the last part of the song is very Katatonia-inspired, taking things from "Brave Murder Day" and
				"Sounds of Decay" era but also paying attention to the softer period shown in the subsequent albums.
				The sound in fact reminds heavily to Katatonia, too... Funnily enough, the vocals are as well "more
				than inspired" by Mikael Åkerfeldt -the growls- and Jonas Renkse -the clean lines-... Definitely, a
				correct band that, despite its lack of originality, demonstrates good taste creating melodies and
				songs. Katatonia nostalgic fans who miss their growlings and raw guitars will probably love this one.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Georges" zine="Pull the Chain" date="050201">
			<p>
				First off, even though you're calling this «Departure» doom metal, it's in no way akin to the
				depressive doom insanity that acts as Ater or Majesty brightly conjured almost a decade ago. For my
				opinion, Forest Of Shadows music may be regarded as funeral slow paced death metal with lotsa
				depressive dark metal, the whole coupled with some electronics surroundings. Niclas Frohagen (the
				man behind Forest Of Shadows) already recorded a first MCD on Rage Of Achilles Records and creates
				throughout the five very long tracks of this album (for a total playing of more than an hour) some
				melancholic soundscapes that will delight our most depressive readers. Prepare to be sent into the
				pit of despair with this «Departure»...no hope, no spark of life, heavy, slow to medium tempo, a
				variety of vocals (which includes tons of spoken parts) and above all negative emotions portrayed
				in a convincing manner. Sweden is the european number one in the suicidal category...and I guest
				things shall not improve with this Forest Of Shadows. Good in its genre.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Bloody Vampire" zine="Planet heavy Metal" date="050129">
			<p>
				Düster und traurig zieht der Schwede Niclas Frohagen mit seiner Band Forest of Shadows durch die
				Landschaft. Ein schönes Stück melodischen Doom Metals ,welches von Fans ruhig angetestet werden
				kann...
			</p>
			<p>
				So... Mit dem neuen Album der Schweden Forest of Shadows wage ich mich nun auf den weit verzweigten
				Weg des Doom Metals. Zwar verleibe ich mir schon ziemlich oft verschiedenste Platten von My Dying
				Bride ein, jedoch habe ich mich wohl noch nie mit so intensiv mit Melodic Doom befasst.
			</p>
			<p>
				Doch, ich muss sagen , Departure ist ein Stück Musik geworden, welches mich wirklich aüßerst positiv
				zu überraschen vermag. Zuerst einmal besteht alles nur aus einer einzelnen Person. Nämlich Niclas
				Frohagen. Dieser hat sämtliche Instrumente eingespielt, jedes Stück komponiert und auch noch den Mix
				und die Produktion selbst übernommen. Gerade da dies alles so wunderbar gelungen ist, gebührt dem
				Schweden ein riesiges Lob.
			</p>
			<p>	
				Obwohl die hier gebotene Kost nicht gerade leicht verdaulich ist. Schon	der erste Track Sleeping
				Death haut mit seinen über 14 Minuten mächtig rein, verzaubert den Hörer aber durch die
				melancholischen Gesangparts und das Klavier, welches diese Endzeitstimmung nur mehr	unterstreicht.
			</p>
			<p>
				Zur Mitte hin wartet gerade dieses Stück mit einer völligen Wandlung auf. Die Cleanen Vocals werden
				mit tiefen Growls getauscht und das zu Beginn dominierende Keyboard wird durch eine
				nervenbahnenzerfetzende Gitarre ersetzt. Bereits hier kann man den Songnamen perfekt mit dem
				musikalischen assoziieren. Der Tod erwacht langsam aus seinem Schlaf und entblößt dann seine wahre
				Fratze. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Das Nächste Stück November Dream verhält sich auch ca. 4 Minuten ruhig, wird dann aber auch zum
				aufbrausenden Midtempo Kracher. Und wieder diese Stimmung. Man kann schon fast sagen, jedes der 5
				Stücke schafft es mich in eine komplett andere Stimmung zu versetzen. Dazu wird auch in einem nicht
				geringen Maße die geniale Instrumentierung beigetragen haben. Neben einem Klavier finden auch noch
				mehrere klassische Instrumente einen Platz, die sich mit den zeitweise eingesetzten Samples aber nie
				in die Quere kommen. Am Ende gibt's auch noch ein Lob für das arg coole Cover Artwork. Also an alle
				Doom Jünger. Die Scheibe konnte mich in allen Belangen überzeugen , vielleicht euch ja auch? 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Michael Blenkarn" zine="Terrorizer" date="050101" rating="7.5/10">
			<p>
				Four years after their debut EP, Forest of Shadows return with an intriguing full-length. Balancing
				the aching, minimal electronic frailty of Antimatter with trance-inducing doom and odd walzing
				sections, mainman Niclas audaciously pushes human tolerance for repetition to the brink with riffs
				cycling endlessly over and over, in a manner that either lulls or infuriates, depending on mood.
				Happily, the gamble is usually a succesfull one and the electronic, piano-led moments in particular
				convey an affecting sense of despair. If anything, the walzing, vaguely folk-inflected moments that
				pop up now and again are the only detractive influence on the record, sounding slightly too
				melodramatic and consequently contrived. If the balance had been trimmed to the most effective
				elements - the laidback and doom parts - and if those sections hadn't been as consciously redolent
				of FOS's Katatonia and Antimatter influences, Niclas would have undoubtly delivered an excellent
				album rather than simply a very god one.				
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Leer Mond" zine="haternal.com" date="050102" rating="9/10">
			<p>
				Vorrei che tutti potessero godere di questo gioiello nato e partorito in Svezia e prodotto dalla ex
				Firebox, che, come sapranno gli esperti del settore, è stata (e a quanto pare continua ad essere)
				una fucina di capolavori Doom.
			</p>
			<p>
				Niclas Frohagen suona tutti gli strumenti su questo primo full lenght della band di Stoccolma.
				Immaginate una perfetta commistione tra le parti pulite, lente ed elettroniche di Opeth, le chitarre
				a cascata assolutamente coinvolgenti di Katatonia, un funeral doom disperato e che dilata la sua
				potenza in ogni nota, il dolore di My Dying Bride e lavori più moderni come quelli di Cult of Luna
				per esempio. Tutto ciò assemblato alla perfezione, con un'ottima produzione e delle vocals da
				brivido. Voce pulita, bassa, trascinata, triste si adagia sulle maliconiche note della chitarra
				acustica e prepara, come se fosse un presagio, alla esplosione improvvisa. Assicuro una sensazione
				di disorientamento. Nella prima traccia, "Sleeping Death" possiamo rinvenire la struttura base delle
				quattro liriche che compongono "Departure" (considerando che "Bleak Dormition"è una strumentale).
				Una parte più malinconica in cui clean vocals si legano a passaggi che mi ricordano gli stacchi
				acustici di Akerfeldt e soci per poi passare da un istante all'altro ad un funeral doom che
				semplicemente, se stai male, ti fa stare peggio.Una cassa di risonanza degli stati d'animo di ognuno
				di noi. Non nego di avere mutato umore dopo la fine della prima traccia.
			</p>
			<p>
				La voce, in growl potentissimo e dilatato mette ancora più in risalto le chitarre che danno la
				stessa sensazione di sofferenza sperimentata con l'ascolto di Renske e compagni all'apice della loro
				produzione. E'una spirale di tristezza in cui non puoi evitare di rimanere intrappolato. E'il dolore
				sordo e straziante di un'implosione dell'anima che non piange ma si contorce.
			</p>
			<p>
				Non voglio aggiungere altro, vorrei solo consigliare l'acquisto a tutti, anche a chi crede di non
				amare tutto quello che si lega al mondo del doom. In questo caso sono certa non potrete rimanere
				indifferenti.
			</p>
			<p>
				ed ora la controanalisi del criptico Yeah:
			</p>
			<p>
				Passo falso per la Firebox/Firedoom proprio alla fine dell'anno. Dopo qualche avvisaglia data da
				uscite poco convincenti come Necare e The Eternal l'etichetta finlandese ci regala il debutto di
				questa one man band che definire derivativo è dire poco. Uscito per la sussidiaria Firedoom (e
				francamente vista la proposta mi chiedo perché, visto che codesta sottoetichetta è stata creata
				proprio per le uscite più estreme), il nostro vichingo ci propina sessanta e rotti minuti di
				clonazioni di Opeth e Katatonia, purtroppo senza originalità alcuna. Cinque i pezzi presenti, sempre
				in bilico tra citazioni Katatonia (sia i più vecchi che quelli dell'ultimo corso.quelli più 'dark'
				per intenderci), vocals ora darkeggianti ora aggressive e ora pulite (con un'intonazione a mio
				parere non convincente), e pezzi troppo simili l'uno all'altro che fanno sembrare il cd un'unica
				traccia intervallata da molteplici cambi di tempo ed atmosfere che, onestamente, tutto sono tranne
				che doom, visto che spesso e volentieri tastiere, arpeggi e arrangiamenti strizzano molto più
				l'occhio al gothic (senza voce femminile, beninteso) che al doom vero e proprio (c'è qualche pezzo
				più aggressivo e condito da distorsioni e doppia cassa, ma onestamente non ha la profondità per
				essere definito doom, almeno a mio parere). Assieme a My Shameful considero questo cd la delusione
				dell'anno relativamente al catalogo Firebox, etichetta che in passato ha prodotto cose veramente
				pregevoli per il genere che amo.
			</p>
			<p>
				Un lavoro 'clone' per inguaribili appassionati delle band citate e nulla più, i ricercatori di
				lentezza e disperazione è meglio sperino nel 2005 e nelle prossime uscite Firedoom: Torture Wheel e
				Pantheist; nel frattempo consiglio a Niclas Frohagen e Sami Rautio (menti rispettivamente di FOS e
				My Shameful) di prendersi una pausa di riflessione o di trovarsi assieme e scambiarsi qualche idea;
				chissà che non ne tirino fuori un capolavoro... la stoffa non manca, dopotutto.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Laetti" zine="Metal Inside" date="041231">
			<p>
				Böse kommt das Cover daher, oldschool scheint das Bandlogo - doch schon der Schriftstil von
				"Departure" zeigt, dass man bei dieser Band zweimal hingucken muss, bevor man sie einmal einordnen
				kann. Auf den ersten Blick spielen FOREST OF SHADOW ellenlange Doom-Monster mit der einen oder
				anderen Länge, auf den zweiten Blick offenbaren Songs wie "Sleeping Death" interessante Wendungen
				und Tücken; Ecken, die nicht ganz zusammen passen und ein gehöriges - Achtung! - Pop-Potential.
				"Schuld" daran ist die normale Singstimme von Niclas Frohagen, der ganz allein FOREST OF SHADOW ist.
				Mit dem abschließenden und Titel-Track "Departure" schafft er es zum Schluß noch mal, tiefe
				Depressionenn und Weltuntergangsstimmung wie die Genre-Vorreiter OPETH oder am extremeren Ende MY
				DYING BRIDE zu verbreiten, bis dahin sind über 4/5 der Zeit eher eine ausgewachsene Melacholie, und
				da darf der junge Mann gern weiter drin versinken. Ergo: Nix für Tage, an denen man 200% Verachtung
				braucht, aber für die gesunde Dosis Weltschmerz super geeignet und weniger Kalorien als eine Tafel
				Bitterschokolade.
 			</p>
		</item>
	 	<item author="Daniel Kvarnström" zine="getmetal.com" date="041216" rating="3/5">
			<p>
				Coca-Cola, chips och öl. Nu finns även doom metal i lightvariant...
			</p>
			<p>
				Niclas Forshagen heter hjärnan bakom detta dystra projekt. FOREST OF SHADOWS 
				domedagsmusik skiljer sig en del från andra band i genren. Mer melodiöst, men 
				samtidigt lika tungt och släpigt. Bitvis gillar jag verkligen det här även om 
				det tenderar att bli aningen tjatigt. Låt er inte luras av att det skivan blott 
				rymmer fem stycken kompositioner. Låtarna är så pass långa att det med råge blir 
				en fullängdsplatta. Ni som gillade debuten "WHERE DREAMS TURNS TO DUST" (2001) 
				kommer förmodligen inte att bli besvikna. Jag kan tänka mig att det här kan 
				tilltala de flesta som gillar tyngre atmosfärisk musik även om "DEPARTURE" inte 
				kommer platsa på någon årsbästalista. Ett ganska medelmåttigt släpp som 
				förmodligen skulle gått mig förbi om jag inte fått skivan som ett brev på 
				posten. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Sir Lord Doom" zine="Metal District" date="041212" rating="9/10">
			<p>
				Düstere Schatten legen sich bedrohlich über das Land. Nebel raubt uns die Sicht. Die Umgebung
				scheint unwirklich und angsteinflößend in diesen Tagen des Winters. Und genau in diese Zeit passt
				eine Band wie Forest of Shadows aus Schweden bestens hinein. Wie kann man sie bezeichnen? Doommetal
				ist dabei, Dark Wave ist dabei, Deathmetalelemente sind dabei. Mastermind Niclas Frohagen liebt es,
				zwischen den Extremen zu pendeln, bricht majestätisch wuchtige Passagen mit durchdringenden
				melodischen Leadgitarren fast abrupt ab um Platz zu schaffen für gemächlich fließende, ruhige Momente
				mit unverzerrten Klampfen und klarem Gesang. Und all das nur, um wieder auf eine jener zermalmenden
				Stellen im Song zuzusteuern, die Dich mit ihrer doomigen Allmacht in Grund und Boden stampfen und
				das gerne auch mal in mittlerem Tempo, nicht immer nur monoton kriechend. Dabei schenkt Niclas dem
				Material einen sehr ausgeprägten eigenen Charakter und somit einen hohen Wiedererkennungswert. Und
				gerade die Gitarrenmelodien sind so eindringlich, überwältigend emotional, schmerzhaft schön und
				dabei schon fast heroisch anmutend. Die CD hat den Tiefgang, der mir oft bei den ganzen Deathdoom -,
				Funeraldoom - und Gothicmetalsachen fehlt. Es ist pure Magie, die Dich zu durchströmen beginnt, die
				Deine Seele vom Körper trennt und Dich hinfortreißt, tief hinein in eine Dimension der
				leidenschaftlich zelebrierten Dunkelheit. Firebox haben sich nicht bei jeder neuen Scheibe mit Ruhm
				bekleckert, hierbei aber schon. Gebt Euch einmal dieser superben Melancholie hin und Ihr vergesst
				die graue Realität. Forest of Shadows sind Liebe und Schmerz pur.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Avenger" zine="Blooddawn.de" date="041212" rating="5/5">
			<p>
				Manchmal hat man als Schreiberling Scheiben im Player, die man schlichtweg genial findet, aber nicht
				dazu in der Lage ist, das Gehörte in adäquate Worte zu fassen. Und genau ein solches Werk ist
				"Departure". Bei FOREST OF SHADOWS handelt es sich um ein Ein-Mann-Projekt, bei welchem der Schwede
				Niclas Frohagen sämtliche Instrumente seiner Kompositionen selbst eingespielt sowie komplett
				aufgenommen und produziert hat. Einzig und allein das Mastering wurde von Finnvox-Mika erledigt. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Eröffnet wird dieses Meisterwerk episch-melodischen Doom Metals von "Sleeping Death", einem fast
				siebzehnminütigen Klangkunstwerk, das leise und nackt beginnt - lediglich ein spartanischer, zäher,
				elektronischer Beat á la MASSIVE ATTACK wird von einem Klavier und Niclas' fragiler Stimme umwunden,
				und in den ersten Minuten baut sich eine Spannung auf, die unerträglicher nicht sein könnte. Erst
				nach fast acht Minuten entlädt sich diese Tension in einer erlösenden, schreienden, breiten, aber
				dennoch harmonischen Gitarrenwand, die dermaßen überwältigend über den Hörer hereinbricht, dass
				dieser erst einmal mit feuchten Augen , schwer schluckend, da sitzt und dieser Energieeruption
				hoffnungslos ausgeliefert ist. Niclas' morbide Growls verstärken diesen Effekt ungemein, und ich
				möchte Herrn Frohagen zu einem der Besten seines Fachs erkiesen. Unfassbar, welche Emotionen durch
				simple Schallwellen ausgelöst werden können. Behäbig geht der Song in eine wehklagende, einsame
				Leadgitarrenmelodie über, die aber bald von einer wunderbaren Harmonie Gesellschaft geleistet
				bekommt und das grandiose Finale dieses ersten Liedes einläutet. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Das bildhafte, schwelgende und astral angehauchte "November Doom" weist anfangs eine ähnliche
				Dynamik auf, und hin und wieder entsteht eine Atmosphäre, die man in ähnlicher Form auch auf dem MY
				DYING BRIDE-Überalbum "Turn Loose The Swans" finden kann. Im Midtempopart dieses Stücks werden auch
				latente Erinnerungen an ganz frühe PARADISE LOST wach. Nach diesem erdrückend tragisch-
				melancholischen Epos, welches sich auch jenseits der Zehnminutengrenze befindet, lässt man uns erst
				einmal mit dem hochmelodischen und ruhigeren Instrumental "Bleak Dormition" nach Luft ringen. Ein
				perfektes Wechselspiel zwischen Hoffnungsschimmer und völliger Niedergeschlagenheit stellt "Open
				Wound" dar. Beklemmende Schönheit, depressive Tristesse... schillernde Farben erscheinen, und kaum
				hat man sich an ihnen erfreut, verschwinden sie in fadem und düsterem Grau... Alles wird zu Nichts...
				Im Nichts ist ein Etwas unermesslich viel... Nicht unähnlich ist auch der abschließende Titeltrack
				angelegt, der die Laut/Leise-Dynamik des Albums ein wenig extremer ausreizt und sämtliche Merkmale
				des Gesamtwerkes noch einmal perfekt miteinander vereint. Leise klingt "Departure" aus und lässt
				einen in der Kälte dieser lebendigen, aber doch toten Welt zurück... 
			</p>
			<p>
				Ein großes Stück Musikkunst. Ein verdammt großes Ausnahmewerk. Ich dachte ja nicht, dass es noch
				kommt: das Album des Jahres 2004. Dieses.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Desibeli.net" date="041203" rating="4/5">
			<p>
				Sleeping death on huono valinta levyn aluksi, se on liian pitkä kaltaisekseen, eikä siitä jää mitään
				mieleen. En voi kuitenkaan tuomita levyä enää kuunneltuani loputkin kappaleet. Kokonaisuus on ihanan
				masentava, ja pidän valtavasti laulajan kuiskaavasta äänestä, joka ei mene möristessäkään pilalle.
				Tätä on mahtavaa kuunnella itsekseen kotona kynttilän valossa tai sitten hiljaisena taustamusiikkina.
			</p>
			<p>
				Vaikka mieleen nouseekin hetkittäin Swallow the Sunin tuotanto, ei se pilaa levyä miltään osin.
				Täysiä pisteitä en kuitenkaan anna, sillä Open Wound on ainoa biisi mikä ei jää jossain vaiheessa
				junnaamaan paikoilleen, vaan sen jaksaa kuunnella alusta loppuun asti. On hienoa, että tällaista voi
				saada aikaan aivan itsekseen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Tom Orgad" zine="Maelstrom" date="041201" rating="6.5/10">
			<p>
				The good:
			</p>
			<p>
				- By featuring long periods of a repetitive weaving of gentle, mellow soundscapes based on recurring
				patterns of electronica-oriented keyboards, bass lines and gentle programmed drums, accompanied by
				sobered, mildly anguished vocals The music of Forest of Shadows conveys emotions of expressive
				bleakness, dark humility and excruciated desperation.
			</p>
			<p>
				The bad:
			</p>
			<p>
				- Some of the elements, while good, do ring of cloning of noted doom metal bands that came before. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The ugly:
			</p>
			<p>
				- Departure moves from bitter honesty to bitter mediocrity.
			</p>
			<p>
				The review:
			</p>
			<p>
				In its second release, Forest of Shadows presents an interesting example of a stylistically divided,
				intentionally genre-defying piece of art. While on certain fields the Finnish one-man band Niclas
				Frohagen (although it should be noted that it involved additional members in the past, one of which
				also contributed to the compositions on Departure) manages to create a unique, singular and
				absorbing effect upon the listener, whenever attempting to balance its obscurity and establish a
				coherent correspondence with defined, enclosed musical style, their creativity and justification as
				a creative unit is drastically diminished, proving the flaws that may stem from a forced, unnatural
				maintenance of a commitment to a standard musical current.
			</p>
			<p>
				The music of Forest of Shadows conveys emotions of expressive bleakness, dark humility and
				excruciated desperation. As typical to the well familiar doom metal genre, the emotional spectrum
				delivered by their creations is well past the stage of hope or militant struggle, saddeningly
				admitting its ever-stagnant submergence in the mire of nostalgic hopeless yearning. The band applies
				two main means in order to fulfill their artistic agenda: first, and favorably, most tracks feature
				long periods of a repetitive weaving of gentle, mellow soundscapes based on recurring patterns of
				electronica-oriented keyboards, bass lines and gentle programmed drums, accompanied by sobered,
				mildly anguished vocals. This array of sonic articulation perfectly depicts the aforementioned
				emotional state: self-aware, sorrowful dimness, realizing its lack of possibility to evolve or
				locate a shard of salvaging hope or anticipation to dent the eternal frame of prevailing murkiness.
			</p>
			<p>
				However, while excelling at the above described expressional activity and managing to achieve a
				cohesive, cohesive piece of vain yet genuine manifestation, the band had apparently been overly keen
				of maintaining a certain measure of loyalty to theitr probably originating metal roots.
			</p>
			<p>
				Therefore, each track also includes passages of the well known, thick keyboard orchestrations,
				growling vocals and heavy guitar layers, attempting to generate a deep and lush space of
				encompassing, hypnotizing, tortured environment. Unfortunately, also being determined not to harm
				the coherency and inner unity of the inner structure of the compositions, these parts are
				characterized by rhythmical and harmonic traits very similar to the ones on the quieter, calm
				pieces - and, therefore, being highly reminiscent of the greatly cloned and nowadays banal standards
				similar to old doom metal bands.
			</p>
			<p>
				Now, while the mellow parts contain, as already noted, a touching sense of tranquil, restrained
				authenticity, the latter parts rarely raise beyond the expected. Indeed, at times they do feature an
				interesting harmonic timbre, but these cases are not frequent nor significant. While surely
				possessing the rare, powerful prowess of protruding one's emotional screening by applying a singular
				manner of expression, whenever stepping into a defined context, acknowledging the stylistic
				narratives, Forest of Shadows move from bitter honesty to bitter mediocrity.
			</p>
			<p>
				So, the quality of Departure is inconsistent and hard to determine. Still, if a bottom line must be
				phrased, it appears that the better, original parts on the album do entitle it being worth a listen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Obliveon" date="041124" rating="8/10">
			<p>
				"Where Dreams Turns To Dust" war in den Tiefen seiner Doom-Abgründe und seiner todtraurigen Melodien
				brilliant, "Departure" ist es (leider) nicht, was nicht heissen soll, dass das erste Fulltime-Album
				des Schweden Niclas Frohagen eine herbe Enttäuschung wäre. Vielleicht liegt es auch daran, dass mit
				"Sleeping Death" ein extrem sperriger und der zugleich längste Song des Albums als Opener gewählt
				wurde, dass sich der Zugang zu "Departure" dermassen schwierig gestaltet. Zudem sind die Violinen,
				die noch einen grossen Teil der einmaligen Atmosphäre von "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" ausgemacht
				haben, einem verstärkten Einsatz von Samples und Orgelsounds gewichen, die das Klangbild Forest of
				Shadows' entscheidend mitverändert haben. Natürlich bestimmen Emotionen und der durchweg
				melancholisch düstere Tenor auch "Departure", doch die erdrückende Schwermut, die den Reiz des
				Vorgängers geprägt hat, ist nicht mehr ganz so präsent und weiter in den Hintergrund gerückt. Zudem
				fehlen die brillianten Gitarrenmelodien, die sich zwar vereinzelt noch ihren Weg aus der Düsternis
				bahnen, doch eher den Akkorden aus Moll haben ergeben müssen und so an die musikalisch nicht ganz so
				glückliche Entwicklung Katatonias erinnern. Nichtsdestotrotz sind das instrumentale "Bleak
				Dormition", November Dream" oder das Titelstück "Departure" grossartige Songs, nur eben nicht mehr
				ganz so mitreissend und bewegend wie in der Vergangenheit. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Toni Peltola" zine="Noise.fi" date="041123" rating="4/5">
			<p>
				Ruotsinmaalta tulee taas erittäin herkullinen annos tyylikästä musiikkia. Ainakin jos herkullisuus
				merkitsee sinulle synkkyyttä ja ahdistusta, sillä tätä Forest of Shadows tarjoaa reilun satsin. Tämä
				yhdenmiehen bändi on ollut toiminnassa jo vuodesta -97 lähtien, mutta debyyttialbuminsa se on saanut
				julki vasta nyt. Aikaisemmin tältä Niclas Frohagenin luotsaamalta bändiltä on ilmestynyt Where Dreams
				Turn to Dust -MCD. Herra Frohagen juottaa musiikissaan yhtyeen Antimatterista muistuttavan kylmän
				koneellisen äänimaailman ja My Dying Bridestä muistuttavan goottilaisen melankolian. Miehen
				säveltämät synkkyyden sinfoniat ovat pelkistetyn minimalistisen sysimustia kylmyyden
				manifestaatioita, jotka kuitenkin yllätävät moniuloitteisuudellaan. Kappaleet ovat keskipituudeltaan
				noin 15 minuuttisia, joten niiden sisäistämiseen vaaditaan astetta kovempaa panostamista. Toisaalta
				biiseissä vallitsee niin tehokkaasti mukaansa imaiseva tunnelma, ettei biisien kestoa oikeastaan
				huomaa. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Departure on surumielisen haikea levy, jota kuunnellessa tuntee olonsa helposti masentuneeksi.
				Maailma kaatuu päälle -fiilikset ovat väistämättömiä, mutta kaikesta melankoliasta huolimatta
				Frohagen on luonut hyvin kauniin ja rauhoittavan levyn, joka yhdistää kuoleman makaaberiin
				onnellisuuteen. Forest of Shadowsin sanoma on selvä: elämä kuihtuu. Nauttikaa siitä niin kauan kuin
				se kestää. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Aruzz" zine="Foreshadow" date="041120">
			<p>
				To say it upfront, this is the first time I face the music of Forest of Shadows. Maybe I should be
				condemned for not being familiar with their mini-album "When Dreams Turn to Dust" as I heard only
				good opinions about it. Anyway, 'Departure' was scheduled for a release through the band's previous
				label Rage of Achilles, but after the company shut down not so long ago, this Swedish one-man
				project signed to Firebox and the label's sub-division Firedoom has just released the full-length.
				Although Forest of Shadows is solely driven by Niclas Frohagen, the material for 'Departure' was
				co-written by another ex-member Micce Anderson who was in the band between 1998 and 2002. So, the
				album is now quite old, being released 2 years after it was finished. Niclas, however, re-arranged
				all the songs in the last two years. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Surprisingly enough, this is not standard modern doom metal one may think. I opened wide my eyes
				when the first tunes of the opening 'Sleeping Death' followed... The smile appeared on my wicked
				face - hey, this is really bleak trip-hop a'la Portishead or Antimatter. Being a great fan of that
				kind of musical art, 'Departure' immidiately appealed to my taste. But, to clear things out, this
				album is not a trip-hop one. Most of the material is obviously doom-oriented. Quite melodic, still
				mainting the funeral touch, switching from deep brutal blasts to mellow guitar passages with clean
				vocals. 'Departure' is for sure a doom metal album, but somehow different from recently proposed by
				other modern doom artists. Throughout all five lengthy songs featured on this album, a spirit of the
				aforementioned artists is present and I guess this is what makes 'Departure' quite special, unique
				and original. I would call it a crossover between modern funeral doom/death metal and trip-hop or to
				say it more straight - a mix between Shape of Despair and Antimatter. 'Departure' is not breath-
				taking, but definitely worth checking out and leaving great expectations when it comes to the next
				opus by this fine Swedish artist. 
			</p>
			<p>
				If this is doom metal of the XXI century, which we can call a MODERN one, than I am all up for it
				and wish to be pleased with more such offerings. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Mika Roth" zine="Desibeli.net" date="041118" rating="3/5">
			<p>
				Kotimainen Firebox lafka on luonut itselleen uuden alamerkin, jonka nimi on linjaa vetävästi
				Firedoom. Tämän upouuden merkin alle on tiensä löytänyt myös ruotsalainen Forest Of Shadows, joka
				jäi taannoin levy-yhtiöttömään tilaan kun sen edellinen isäntä Rage Of Achilles otti ja keikahti
				nurin. Toisen epäonni on, kuten useasti sanottua, toisen onni, ja Forest Of Shadown nappaaminen
				antaakin mukavasti alkuvauhtia uudelle merkille. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Departure levyn kesto kääntyy päälle tunnin, mutta biisejä siltä ei löydy kuin viisi. Aikamoisesta
				hautajaissaatosta on siis tällä kertaa kyse. Kiekon mukana tulleessa saatteessa musiikkia kuvaillaan
				melodiseksi doom metalliksi, mikä ei kyllä kerro läheskään koko totuutta. Ensinnäkin ilmaisu on
				hidasta, reilusti perusdoomia hitaampaa. Tämän lisäksi kerronta käy tunnelmiltaan välillä hyvinkin
				herkissä ja hauraissa sfääreissä, vaikka hetkittäin metallihelvetti räjähtääkin päälle.
				Majesteetillisiin mittoihin kasvavista teoksista nousee väkisinkin mieleen kotimaisen Swallow The
				Sunin synkkyys, toisinaan meno on taas miltei Anathemamaista maalailua. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows on tätä nykyä yhden miehen, sen perustajan Niclas Frohangenin visio. Välillä
				Ningizziassakin Frohangenin kanssa musisoinut Micce Andersson on käynyt vähän auttelemassa, mutta
				Departure on silti kiistatta vain ja ainoastaan maestron levy, alusta loppuun saakka. Näin ääretön
				lohduttomuus kaipaisi mielestäni totaalisempaa ilmaisua, sillä nyt pitkät pimputtelujaksot syövät
				runttausvaiheiden voimaa tuhottomasti. Aivan kuin tässä ei oltaisi osattu päättää pitäisikö tehdä
				raskas doom vai kevyehkö ambient/dark metal levy. Lopputulos ei ole oikein kumpikaan näistä, ja se
				lopullinen pointti jäi ainakin meikäläiseltä hieman pimentoon.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="vampster.com" date="041117">
			<p>
				Doom ist bekanntlich langsam. Dies scheint sich im Falle von FOREST OF SHADOWS auch auf die
				Entstehungsgeschichte des Albums "Departure" niedergeschlagen zu haben. Denn wie ließe es sich
				sonst erklären, dass das Album vier Jahre an Entwicklungszeit verschlungen hat. Um nicht die ganze
				"Schuld" auf das schleppendste Genre des Heavy Metals zu schieben, soll auch darauf hingewiesen
				werden, dass "Departure" dreimal umgeschrieben wurde, mit Micce Anderson ein wichtiger Bestandteil
				der Band ebendiese verlassen hat und somit Niclas Frohagen ganz alleine das künstlerische und
				organisatorische Zepter der nunmehrigen One-Man-Show schwingt. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Und weil wir gerade vom "Schwung" sprechen: von diesem ist nicht sonderlich viel gegenwärtig.
				"Departure" ist ein schwerfälliger, mächtiger Koloss düsteren Doom Metals, der sich zusätzlich
				Teilen des Dark und Death Metals bedient und Erinnerungen an alte MY DYING BRIDE-Scheiben aufkommen
				lässt. Die hauptsächlichen Bausteine dieser unüberwindbaren Wand aus Schwermut sind sowohl die
				akustische als auch die elektrische Gitarre, die sparsam von anderen Instrumenten wie Piano,
				Mellotron oder diversen Samples ergänzt werden. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Etwas im Hintergrund versteckt sich der Gesang, der ebenso wie das gesamte Album auf zwei
				verschiedene Arten in Erscheinung tritt. So werden die ruhigen, still dahinsiechenden Passagen
				voller Melancholie mit cleanen, etwas schwachbrüstig anmutenden Vocals verhalten ins Mikrofon
				gehaucht, während die anderen Teile dieser Traurigkeit entfliehen wollen, indem sie den
				Seelenschmerz voller Wut und Verzweiflung herauszuschreien versuchen, was mittels der Growls auch
				gut zur Geltung kommt. Unterstützung in diesem Wechselspiel des Tempos und des Härtegrads erfahren
				die Vocals durch die angesprochene Arbeitsteilung von akustischer und E-Gitarre oder der Abwechslung
				von elektronischen oder gar keinen Beats mit denjenigen des Schlagzeugs, das in Doublebass-Passagen
				auch für verhältnismäßigen Elan sorgt. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Die fünf Songs, die auf "Departure" zum Besten gegeben werden, sind im Übrigen im Durchschnitt
				zwischen zehn und fünfzehn Minuten lang und greifen jeweils auf einen ähnlich gearteten
				Spannungsaufbau zurück: Ein melancholischer Beginn leitet den Song ein, Tempo und Aggressivität
				steigern sich allmählich bis sich letztendlich die ganze Verzweiflung Luft verschaffen muss. Somit
				ist die Variabilität - oberflächlich betrachtet - nicht den Stärken des Albums hinzuzurechnen, doch
				ist es auch nicht die Intention des schwedischen Künstlers sonderlich progressiv zu Werke zu gehen,
				sondern viel mehr ein Album zu schaffen, das den Hörer berührt, um ihn an der Melancholie und
				Verzweiflung teilhaben zu lassen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Drew Ailes" zine="Metal Review" date="041117">
			<p>
				Departure marks the band's first full album after a lengthy and highly acclaimed EP and MCD for
				Sweden's Forest of Shadows. Originally beginning with one sole member, there's been a revolving
				lineup involving at least 7 people, but for this release, it's just the single man, Niclas Frohagen.
				Citing his influences on the website, Forest of Shadows plays a mixture of darkwave and doom ala
				Katatonia and My Dying Bride and meshes it with more modern doomy outfits like Cult of Luna through
				the use of thick and heavy guitar. 
			</p>
			<p>
				"Sleeping Death", the opening track which clocks in at 16:53, starts with more electronic elements
				and clean singing before successfully leaping to epic and full-sounding funeral doom with crushing
				growls. Everything's done so perfectly. The sorrowful crooning is on key, not overused, and pleasing
				in quality. Although the idea of such a long song may frighten some, with its acoustic melodies, the
				song could easily stretch to a half an hour without feeling redundant. While I'm sure many of you
				may shudder at the idea of electronics being incorporated into doom, you can lay your fears to rest
				as nothing ever comes across as banal or even slightly overbearing. This isn't an industrial/goth
				album. The shortest track on the album, "Bleak Dormition", is an instrumental that sounds slightly
				like Isis in the underlying guitar melody. "Open Wound" is based centrally around a slow and almost
				trip-hop beat before erupting into a grandiose movement with a choir full of rich keyboards.
				Mesmerizing double-bass drumming later enters and brings the song back to the initial verse. The
				song ends by winding down into anxious and sinister repetition before breaking back into the
				familiar beat mentioned before.
			</p>
			<p>
				In the under-crowded doom market, it's remarkable to come across such a genuine and heartfelt band
				that never ventures near the unfortunate sickening sentimentality that a lot of bands make the
				mistake of getting caught up in. Long, slow, and monumentally depressing, Departure is a must-have
				for doom lovers of all levels of experience. Take it from me - I'm not even a fan of this type of
				doom and I love it. 	
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Lake" zine="The Shadowshire Webzine" date="041117">
			<p>
				Schon mit seinem kleinen Debüt "Where Dreams turn to Dust" konnte Forest Of Shadows im Jahre 2001
				kleine Erfolge feiern, seitdem hat man von Niclas Frohagen, dem einzigen Mann, der im Augenblick
				hinter dieser Formation steckt, nur wenig vernommen. Fakt ist, dass der Mann trotzdem fleißig an
				seinem Album gefeilt hat, das er in der Zwischenzeit sage und schreibe dreimal überarbeitete. Im
				Sommer unterzeichnet er beim Firebox Unterlabel Firedoom, da, wo ich mir denke, er auch mit seinem
				neuen Werk "Departure" in bester Gesellschaft ist.
			</p>
			<p>
				Im Vorfeld daher liess man sich auf keine Experimente ein und heuerte Mastermind Mika Jussila als
				Produzent der Scheibe an. Freunde von melodischem Doom, der auch noch den bittersüßen
				melancholischen Geschmack mit sich zieht, sollten "Departure" alle beiden Ohren gönnen. Selten war
				man so fasziniert von dieser Mischung aus Melancholie und extremem Metal, obwohl der Opener
				"Sleeping Death" noch sehr ruhig herüberkommt. Melodische Bögen offenbaren einem ein Gefühl voller
				Depression und abgrundtiefen Verlorenseins. Die Gitarren fallen zum einem Teil begleitend aus,
				während sie im zweiten Teil zur Aggression mutieren. Dieses setzt man im passenden Song "November
				Dream" gekonnt fort, allerdings nicht mehr ganz so melodisch wie im Opener, dafür hat man den Grad
				an melancholischen Passagen erhöht.
			</p>
			<p>
				Da es nur fünf Songs sind (alle in Überlänge), kann man gezielt auf einzelne Songs eingehen. "Bleak
				Dormition" ist für mich das wahre Highlight der Platte geworden. Melodischen Doom Metal in
				Perfektion erlebt man hier vom ersten bis zum letzten Riff. Das Faszinierende hierbei ist noch, dass
				kleine Spuren von skandinavischem Folk mit eingebaut wurden, was der Schwede hier wirklich einfach
				nur atemberaubend integriert hat. Das Pianosolo am Ende des Songs sorgt für schweifende und traurige
				Gedanken. Der Titeltrack vereint gekonnt progressive Klänge mit Melancholie, die etwas später von
				stark riffigen und schleppenden Gitarren in allerbester Doom-Manier abgelöst werden. Dass man hier
				auch minimale elektronisch Einflüsse perfekt eingegliedert hat, zeugt eigentlich nur von der
				Genialität des Schweden.
			</p>
			<p>
				Um es noch kurz zu machen, spreche ich nach all der Lobhudelei die negativen Aspekte an - es gibt
				keine! Forest Of Shadows gelingt mit seinem Debütalbum ein weites Feld im Genre Doom abzudecken,
				bleibt aber immer mit melancholischen Zügen auf seiner Linie. Daher zähle ich "Departure" zur
				Pflicht für jeden, der in diesen tristen Tagen im Herbst auch akustisch die passende Musik zum
				Untermalen sucht. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Ruben" zine="Eternal Terror" date="041114" rating="5.5/6.0">
			<p>
				Dette var da litt av en overraskelse. Jeg klagde litt til Rune over at det var så lite doom for
				tiden og hva dumper han i mine hender? Joda, dette supre bandet som med "Departure" har kommet med
				en av årets beste doom utgivelser! La oss ta litt historie først. Forest of Shadows består i dag av
				en herremann som heter Niclas Frohagen og denne mannen gjør alt selv på Departure. Han startet
				bandet tilbake i 1997 og fikk med seg Micce Anderson i 1998, men han forsvant igjen i 2002. det skal
				dog sies at denne Micce har hatt en del å si i låtskrivingen til dette albumet da mye av materialet
				er gammelt. Materialet har selvfølgelig gjennomgått noen forandringer igjennom årene, men slikt
				skjer da. Bak seg har han tidligere bare en MCD som i 2001 kom på nå nedlagte Rage of Achilles. Når
				de gikk dunken så det en stund mørkt ut for Niclas, men Firedoom, for øvrig et underselskap av
				Firebox, var kloke nok til å snappe opp denne perla, heldig for dem det!
			</p>
			<p>
				Jeg ble mer eller mindre sjokkert da denne hadde snurret ferdig første gang i spilleren min. Jeg var
				lamslått, hva var det jeg nettopp hadde hørt? Dette var da mesterlig og deilig doom tenkte jeg da,
				men nå vet jeg at dette er mesterlig og deilig doom! Ikke få ganger har denne snurret og blitt
				elsket, det skal jeg love deg! Åpningslåten, "Sleeping Death" er en super start på platen og har en
				oppbygning som er så sinnsykt bra! Jeg får faktisk litt Antimatter/Massive Attack følelse av dette,
				ikke bare her i starten, men også flere plasser på skiva, når bandet roer det ned litt, jævlig kult
				faktisk! Uansett, "Sleeping Death" begynner veldig rolig med en sørgekledd vokal som passer musikken
				godt egentlig, før det hele brytes opp i tung, seig og melodisk doom med et melankolsk preg over seg.
				Neste låt ut heter "November Dream" og er også en fantastisk flott låt full av fantastisk flotte
				melodier, noe for øvrig hele resten av platen også er! Niclas bruker både en sår, melankolsk ren
				vokal og en mer typisk brølende death variant og mestrer begge ypperlig. Litt spesiell stemme på
				ham, men jeg synes den er flott og passer musikken godt. "Bleak Dormition" er en instrumental som
				klokker inn på rundt 6 minutter hvis jeg ikke husker helt feil. Denne er også fantastisk nydelig,
				dyster og tung kledd i en deilig melankolsk drakt. Nest siste låt ut heter "Open Wound" og er minst
				like bra som de 3 første. Jeg har så langt ikke noen ankepunkter på det Niclas har gjort. Her viser
				han nok en gang hvor bra hans stemme passer musikken, bare sjekk ut vokallinjene i 2. og 4. vers
				her, det er så sinnsykt vakkert! Dette er skikkelig deilig deppemusikk med tekster som vil drive en
				sørgende person til kanten av stupet. Jeg tror nok Niclas har hentet litt inspirasjon fra Aaron i My
				Dying Bride når det kommer til tekster, jeg ser en hvis likhet, men det skal jeg finne mer ut av.
				"Departure" avslutter denne plata og dette er vel dens svakeste spor. Den begynner ganske kult, men
				det kommer et parti midt i låten jeg finner litt intetsigende, men den tar seg kraftig opp mot
				slutten og der er den like sterk som resten av skiva. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Så, for å oppsummere snakker vi her kanskje om en av årets mest spennende doomskiver i form av
				"Departure" fra svenske Forest of Shadows. Er du glad i det dystre, mørke, melankolske og seige er
				dette et sikkert kjøp, dette er doom i sin beste form!!!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Themis Pamfilos" zine="Hellride Music" date="041111">
			<p>
				They say history repeats itself. Indeed! Remember the case of UK's Peaceville records that in the
				early nineties (and forth) started baptising slow melodic death metal bands as doom metal (e.g. MY
				DYING BRIDE, ANATHEMA etc.)? Well, something similar is happening today with Finland's Firebox,
				which has repeatedly presented bands that have very little or no relation to doom metal as such
				(e.g. WOODS OF BELIAL, THE ETERNAL, TYRANNY, PANTHEIST and so on). 
			</p>
			<p>
				Firebox recently founded a new sub-label under the name Firedoom, which would focus on doom metal.
				So here I am holding in my hands Firedoom's second release (FDOOM 002), a CD by a one-man-band under
				the name FOREST OF SHADOWS entitled "Departure". I read the press release, which described the style
				as "melodic doom metal". So I joyfully put the CD in the player hoping to listen to some melodic
				doom metal, as promised. Well, "melodic doom metal" my ass! FOREST OF SHADOWS play atmospheric dark
				depressive music with loads of keyboards and electronics, with clean (often almost spoken) vocals,
				which occasionally transform into death metal semi-brutal growling ones. There is no doom metal
				riffing present anywhere in this release. Instead violins, piano and samples are present, and
				actually a much better description would be ambient melancholic slow death metal fused with
				electronica. So doom metal fans don't get fooled, doom metal is something you definitely won't find
				in this release.
			</p>
			<p>
				Having cleared up the above, and definition and label issues aside, "Departure" presents some
				interest. But, not much. It is the second release of Sweden's FOREST OF SHADOWS, following after the
				debut mini-CD "Where Dreams Turn to Dust", released in 2001 by the now defunct Rage of Achilles.
				As I said, FOREST OF SHADOWS is not a real band, it is just a name under which Niclas Frohagen has
				chosen to release his music. He played (or programmed) all the instruments, signs or co-signs all
				compositions and lyrics, and handled the recording and mixing of the album himself. Having not
				listened to the "band's" 2001 debut release I cannot make any comparisons. But, in what Mr. Frohagen
				has certainly succeeded in these 5 songs that comprise this album (most having a duration of well
				above ten minutes), is creating dark melancholic soundscapes and a fragile bleak atmosphere. But not
				much more than that, and frankly to me this is not enough. Nothing beyond just a background music,
				as it can't grab or hold my attention. Yet, fans of MY DYING BRIDE, mid/latter period ANATHEMA or
				even KATATONIA this might (I said MIGHT) interest you, as this is where the main influences of
				FOREST OF SHADOWS come from.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Antti Klemi" zine="Imperiumi" date="041105" rating="8/10">
			<p>
				Jotenkin on loogista, että Forest of Shadows on yhden miehen, Niclas Frohagenin, yhtye. Departure on
				nimittäin äärimmäisen lakoninen ja depressiivinen doom-levy, jonka tekemiseen tarvitaan juuri yhden
				ahdistuneen ihmismielen visio. Ja Departurea kuunnellessa tulee selväksi, että Frohagenilla on tämä
				näkemys. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Departure on täysin Frohagenin säveltämä, sanoittama, soittama, nauhoittama ja miksaama teos;
				ainoastaan bändissä ennen vaikuttanut Micce Andersson on ottanut paikoin osaa pitkäsyiseen
				sävellystyöhön. Frohagen on selvästi kaivanut levylle intiimimmät tuntemuksensa. Departure soi
				kolkkona tuomiomarssina läpi elämän muistojen: joskus pysähdytään pehmeämmän hetken kohdalle,
				jolloin Antimatterin tyyliset kevyemmät rummut, pianot ja lähes klubimainen tunnelma valtaavat alaa,
				joskus taas ahdistus kasvaa askel askeleelta, sointu soinnulta, kunnes kaikki räjähtää mustaksi
				raivoksi ja tuskaksi Frohagenin toteavien laulujenkin muuttuessa turhautuneeksi karjunnaksi. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest of Shadowsissa on osa My Dying Bridea ja toinen osa Empyriumia. Mutta missä MDB on rakkauden-
				ja kuolemantuskissa vaikeroiva goottikirjailija ja Empyrium luontoa kunnioittava pohdiskelija, on
				Forest of Shadowsin ruumiillistuma enemmänkin karumpi ja yksinkertainen jokamies, joka omassa
				eristyksessään kävelee syksyisillä ja tuulten tuivertamilla pellonpientareilla. Maisema pysyy
				samana, jokainen askel on edellisen toisinto. Monotonisuus karsiikin paikoin Departuren
				vaikuttavuutta, sillä vaikka tämä ominaisuus tuokin esiin levyn ehdottomuutta, hamuaa kuuntelija jo
				seuraavan muiston luo. Parhaimmillaan Forest of Shadows onkin muuttaessaan musiikkinsa laineiksi,
				jotka tiivistävät paikoin tunnelman äärimmilleen, mutta osaavat laskeutua suvannoksi ja
				hengähdyshetkeksi. Open Woundin syntikoilla, rummuilla ja kitaravalleilla kerroksittain kasvava
				ahdistus on ehkä paras esimerkki tästä. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Departurea ei olisi parempaan aikaan voitu julkaista. Hienosti koottu instrumentaali Bleak Dormition
				vie keltaisten, jo maatuvien lehtien koristelemiin metsiin, kun taas nimikappale on kuin päivän
				pimentävä syysmyrsky. Departure ei täysin kestä yli tunnin pituuttaan, mutta muutoin levy on hieno
				osoitus siitä, kuinka yksilötasolla koetut ja julkituodut tunteet voivat koskettaa yleisellä tasolla
				monta loppujen lopuksi samoin tuntevaa ihmistä. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Martin Borg" zine="Close-Up" date="041101">
			<p>
				Enmansprojekt drivet av Stockholmsstationerade Niclas Frohagen med starka vibbar från band som
				Antimatter och Anathema, men även från Isis. Stilen är avskalad, monoton och enkel med långa
				pianopartier varvat med hårdare avsnitt. Framförandet är fantasilöst och arrangemangen visar att
				ensamvargen Niclas saknar förmågan att få flyt i övergångarna mellan mastodontlåtarnas olika partier.
				Jämfört med ovannämnda mästare är detta lekskola. Texterna, som egentligen är en och samma i alla
				låtarna, är sprängfyllda med den pubertala romantiserande melankolins målande bildspråk. En guldgruva
				för klichébingo.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Marcus / Jesper / Johansson / Sonny / Petterson" zine="Close-Up - soundcheck" date="041101" rating="5.4/10">
			<p>
				[Marcus Grahn] Den mysigt mörka och stillsamt dystra gothvarianten är som ett fem-i-tre-ragg:
				trevligast med ljuset släckt. Större variationsrikedom skulle höja tillfredställelsen
				ytterliggare. (6)
			</p>
			<p>
				[Jesper Hasselström] Det finns ungefär lika många strimmor ljus som korta låtar på detta depressiva
				alster. Väl utdraget emellanåt, men samtidigt saknas inte höjdpunkter. (6)
			</p>
			<p>
				[Daniel Johansson] Ofantligt långsam och omständlig stämningsmusik som pendlar mellan Leonard Cohens
				akustiska knarrande och kolsvart doom. Bitvis suggestivt, men mestadels bara långtråkigt. (4)
			</p>
			<p>
				[Sonny Jonasson] Episkt vemodiga klanger som likt spindelväv fångar mig i sin linda för att invänta
				ödet. Niclas Frohagen är ensam herde bakom denna femhövdade flock sånger. Tänk valium, tänk SWALLOW
				THE SUN. (7)
			</p>
			<p>
				[Mattias Pettersson] Så svulstigt och överarbetat känns det emellanåt att jag tvingas dra till med
				den nedvärderande beskrivningen "schlagerdoom". (4)
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Music Extreme" date="041101">
			<p>
				I have to give the award to this band for the "Most deppressive band of 2004". This is almost like a
				soundtrack to a suicide. Slow rhythms are the key element here and every note played here is full of
				sorrow, full of pain and melancholy that is soon transmitted to the listener. There is a big role
				for keyboards here that have managed to create sad chord progressions and arrangements over which the
				voices construct the melodies or the growls that are essential to achieve the climax of depressions.
				The guitars create slow riffs and also some melodies (that reminded me to early My dying Bride) that
				contribute to the overall melancholy. everything here is melancholy and the ood sound that the album
				has contributes with this overall feeling. If you have listened bands like Evoken you will like this
				band even if it is really different in style (but not on the deppressive feeling). A masterpiece of
				suicidal feelings.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Mordor Magazin" date="041031" rating="10/10">
			<p>
				Die Erfahrung sagt mir das alles was aus dem Hause Firebox kommt, generell gut, aber
				aussergewöhnlich ist. So die neue Scheibe des Schwedischen Melodic Doom Künstlers Nicolas Frohagen.
				Dargeboten werden fünf Songs in üblicher Doom Überlänge. Jedoch kachelt und knattert es hier nicht
				wie erwartet. "Departure" ist eine sehr sehr ruhiges Werk und lebt durch seine tollen Stimmungen. So
				bekommt man auf diesem Silberling zur Hälfte unverzerrte Gitarren, clean Gesang und wundervolle
				Keyboard Passagen zu hören. Die andere Hälfte lebt durch einfache verzerrte Riffs, die meist von
				tollen Gitarrenmelodien untermauert werden. Dazu gibt es natürlich tiefen Gesang, der das düstere
				Doom Image aufrecht erhält. 
			</p>
			<p>
				"Departure" ist im Gesamteindruck aber ein sehr verträumtes Werk, welches den Hörer in eine ferne
				Traum Welt entführt. Jeder Song ist für sich wunderschön und versprüht mystische Schönheit, wer sich
				gerne von der Musik tragen lässt wird hier sicherlich begeistert sein. "Departure" ist ein Album das
				sicherlich nicht nur Doom Fans anspricht, sondern ganz besonders von Dark Metal Fans oder gar Gothic
				Freunden angetestet werden sollte. Wichtig ist das man es gerne mystisch, melodisch und harmonisch
				mag. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Arnstein" zine="doom-metal.com" date="04????">
			<p>
				This CD sees the music moving completely away from the folk elements that were incorporated in mCD.
				So I guess you could say besides the music having grown even better in terms of song quality, the
				music hasn't changed all that much from the early releases. If anything the music has grown more
				majestic with its maturity.
			</p>
			<p>
				I see that reviewers before me claim the music isn't all that original and makes most of its fame
				based on the quality of the sound. I disagree. The emotion in the music is indeed similar to bands
				like Katatonia and Anathema, but the fact that the music crosses into both doom/death and doom/black
				does make it stand out as being original based on standing on the shoulder of more than one giant.
				Niclas also incorporates elements of his own, like dark blackish vocals that enter from time to time
				during the more intense moments of the music. The Empyrium style clean vocals still dominate though.
			</p>
			<p>
				What really makes me enjoy this CD isn't the slow and mellow moments, which the music has plenty of.
				It's the way that the music grows ever more intense as the track progresses, culminating in the
				majestic and powerful atmosphere which sends shivers through your body. Don't doubt for a moment that
				the music isn't depressive. It still is completely joyless in every way. Even the lyrics speak of the
				classic romantic doom scenario or the mourning lover who takes his own life.
			</p>
			<p>
				I conclude this review by saying this: fans of Katatonia and Niclas Forhagens' other band, Ningizzia
				should get hold of this release. If you just want high quality music like the melodic part of the
				doom/death subgenre often displays, then you should get it too. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Dajana" zine="Nocturnal Hall" date="04????" rating="8.5/10">
			<p>
				Das ist das perfekte Album, um den Winter nicht zu überleben! Nein, selbst an einem heiteren
				Sommertag dürfte Departure auch das sonnigste Gemüt in unendlich schwarze Tiefen ziehen. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Departure beginnt mit Sleeping Death, einem über 16 Minuten langen Song, dessen erste 8 Minuten an
				späte Ulver (insbesondere die Soundtracks) und sogar an Antimatter oder The Gathering erinnern,
				stilistisch gesehen. Ruhige Passagen, akustisch oder dezent elektronisch, leicht trippig bereiten
				das Gemüt sanft auf die seelische Apokalypse vor, die danach mit voller Wucht über einen
				hereinbricht. Ein wahres melancholisches Inferno aus doomig schleppenden Gitarrenriffs, die durch
				alle Moll Akkorde wandern, herzzerreißende Solos, Growls und cleaner Gesang lassen allen Schmerz der
				Welt fühlen, der die Seele in winzige Atome zu zersplittern droht. Auch Novembers Dream lindert nur
				bedingt die Wunden, denn bevor man sich erholt hat, wird man wieder in den Strudel abgrundtiefer
				Depressionen gezogen. Dieser Kreislauf aus sanften aber tot-traurigen Melodien, hypnotisierenden
				Riffs, Pianoklängen und infernalische Seelenpein verursachende Doom Passagen zieht sich durch das
				gesamte Album. Jedes noch so kleine Detail im Denken und Leben wird zu einer übergewichtigen Kraft,
				die einen nach unten zieht. Und das Ende ist jedes Mal ungewiss.
			</p>
			<p>
				4 Lange Jahre hat Multiinstrumentalist Niclas Frohagen gebraucht, um das Nachfolgewerk der 2001
				erschienen EP Where Dreams Turns To Dust in seine endgültige Form zu bringen und zu veröffentlichen.
				Frohagen hat das Album im völligen Alleingang erstellt und gestattete sich nur beim Endmix ein wenig
				Hilfe und Unterstützung. Nun, das Warten	hat sich gelohnt und Departure konnte zu keinem besseren
				Zeitpunkt veröffentlicht werden.
			</p>
			<p>
				Nichtsdestotrotz sei hier eine Warnung gegeben: wer sich psychisch gerade in einer labilen Phase
				befindet, sollte besser die Finger von Departure lassen. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Jens" zine="Walls of Fire" date="04????" rating="5/5">
	 		<p>
	 			Niclas Frohagen hat sich viel Zeit gelassen, sehr viel Zeit sogar. Satte drei Jahre gingen seit der
	 			überragenden "Where Dreams Turn to Dust"-MCD ins Land, bis der schwedische Multiinstrumentalist fast
	 			im Alleingang die fünf neuen Songs des ersten Longplayers "Departure" fertiggestellt hatte - Mika Jussila
	 			griff ihm lediglich beim Mastern unter die Arme. Aber die lange Arbeit zahlt sich aus, denn dieses Album
	 			ist richtiger Hammer!
	 		</p>
	 		<p>
				"Sleeping Death" beginnt langsam, beklemmend. Eine getragene Piano-Melodie und die finsteren Melodic-Vocals
				Frohagens erzeugen in Ergänzung einer zurückhaltenden Rhythmusgruppe wohlige Schauer. Mit langen
				Instrumentalparts und flüsternden Stimmen erzeugt der Song eine ungeheure Spannung, bevor nach fast acht
				Minuten grimmige Growls und tiefe Schlepp-Riffs einsetzen. Ein Wahnsinnssong, der sich auf epische 17
				Minuten ausdehnt, ohne langweilig zu werden. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Im Gegensatz zum letzten Output verzichtet Frohagen dieses Mal auf Flöten und Folkelemente. Stattdessen
				setzt der Kopf von Forest of Shadows auf künstliche Streicher und ein Melotron, wie im Intro zu "November
				Dream" zu hören. Das elfminütige Stück ist ein Paradebeispiel dafür, dass die neuen Songs viel
				abwechslungsreicher und weniger Death Metal orientiert sind. Frohagen operiert mit verstärkten Clean-Vocals
				im Kontrast zu seinen harschen Growls. "November Dream" jedenfalls basiert auf melodischen
				Doompassagen, die dann im Mittelteil von der Double-Bass und druckvollem Beckeneinsatz nach vorne
				gepeitscht werden, aber schnell mit akustischen Arrangements wieder zur Ruhe kommen. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Mit "Bleak Dormition" folgt ein verträumtes, mit Spannungsbögen verziertes Instrumentalstück. "Open
				Wound" ist sehr melodielastig, ja gar in Ansätzen schon hymnisch. Frohagen erschuf eine vielseitige,
				detailreiche und mit vielen Stimmungen ausgestattete Nummer. Das finale grande "Departure" schleppt sich
				förmlich ins Ziel, explodiert jedoch gegen Ende und wird sehr aggressiv. Ein grandioser Ausstieg eines
				noch bemerkenswerteren Albums. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Auf "Departure" wurden die Einflüsse von My Dying Bride bis Katatonia zurückgeschraubt. Forest of Shadow
				hat nun ein ganz eigenes Gesicht. Und das bringt die "Band" ganz nah an die Weltspitze des melodischen
				Dooms, respektive Gothic Metals. Zum Sterben schön.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Üriel" zine="Obsküre" date="04????" rating="6/10">
			<p>
				Niclas Frohagen, le one-man man suédois aux manettes de Forest of Shadows, n'est peut-être pas un
				inconnu pour tout le monde en France. Sa collaboration avec le musicien français Stéphane Peudupin
				ayant accouché en 2003 du premier album de Ningizzia, bonne galette à mi-chemin entre My Dying Bride
				et Empyrium. Dans un style voisin mais plus personnel et épuré de teintes folkloriques, Forest of
				Shadows présente son premier album après une floppée de démos et un EP sorti en 2001.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Departure" présente le visage sévère et buriné d'un doom orthodoxe, subdivisé en cinq blocs
				compacts, aussi homogènes qu'une longue histoire de famille mille fois contée à la chandelle. Et
				comme toutes les histoires usées, celle-ci n'arrive plus à électriser son monde qu'à travers ses
				rituels moments forts. Lesquels ne compensent plus la léthargie de riffs sincères mais élimés et
				suremployés, les vocaux sobres mais vite redondants, le prosaïsme essoufflé d'un style qui hésite
				trop - sa malédiction - entre lourdeur véritable et lyrisme aérien.
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows n'est pas Shape of Despair ou Esoteric, qui savent tourner la monotonie effective
				de leur musique en magie pure par un ensemble de conjectures favorables allant de la personnalité à
				un don de soi extrême. Victime tragique de ses longueurs et de sa mentalité trop modérée, "Departure"
				n'arrive jamais à sortir la tête du guidon. Dommage, l'indiscutable noblesse du style, l'excellence
				de "Open Wound" et de quelques belles esquisses cloisonnées dans le marasme des autres titres
				auraient mérité bien meilleur sort.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Timothy Golden" zine="Decoy Music" date="04????" rating="3.7/5">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows (an alias for Niclas Frohagen, who plays and/or programs every instrument here) is
				presented via Firebox's Doom-only offshoot, Firedoom, but actually isn't just doom metal. It's
				actually really dark, depressing rock with Massive Attack-styled slow electronica beats put in for
				good measure, combined with some doom. Not that this is a bad thing, it's just something that needs
				to get cleared up.
			</p>
			<p>
				Departure, the second album under the Forest of Shadows name, contains five songs that (with the
				exception of one) all exceed ten minutes in playing time. Within those ten-minute plus opuses, you'll
				find some chilling, atmospheric music that will either haunt you as you envision some chilling
				deathscapes in your head, or, put you to sleep. Only once in a blue moon does a guitar riff surface
				(it takes about eight minutes for the listener to be presented with one on the record), but when it
				does, it's usually accompanied by some nice, drawn-out death growling. 
			</p>
			<p>
				It turns out that Departure is just a depressing ride through the tortured being that is Niclas. He
				has an eerie voice when he tries to sing, and the recording quality on his vocals isn't really up to
				par with the rest of the instrumentation, but it's pretty easy to ignore since it fits with the
				music pretty well. The songs are really long, but it's better than the album is comprised of few
				songs that are really long rather than fourteen songs that are short and all carry the same theme
				and sound the same. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The best song here is the shortest, however. "Bleak Dormition" is the closest this album gets to
				being doom metal (although the mid-section of "Open Wound" is pretty doom-metaly). The guitars and
				drums have just the right amount of doom in them, and the vocals are nowhere to be found. It's just
				one of the nicest audible landscapes you're bound to hear -- if you listened to it while you were
				driving, you'd start seeing some creepy shit.
			</p>
			<p>
				The bottom line is that Firebox (Firedoom, whatever) puts out some quality stuff, and this release
				is no reason to think otherwise. Whether you're the casual slow-metal fan like myself, or a hardcore
				doomer, chances are you'll like this. If you're a fan of My Dying Bride or The Eternal, this might
				be your cup of tea. Hell, if you don't like it, the only thing you have to do is turn it off. But,
				chances are, you won't.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Nicolas Cañellas" zine="Executioner Zine" date="04????">
			<p>
				El sello finés Firedoom, dedicado a la edición de álbumes de doom metal edita el primer trabajo como
				larga duración de esta banda formada por un solo individuo, Niclas Frohagen. Desde que él fundara el
				proyecto en el '97 han pasado montones de músicos y ahora presenta esta obra en la cual él toca
				todos los instrumentos, lo ha compuesto todo, lo ha grabado y lo ha mezclado, casi nada...
				exceptuando el detalle de que Departure fué escrito a medias con Micce Anderson, músico que
				compartío la banda desde el 98 hasta el 2002. Centrándome en el disco, decir que con 61 minutos y 5
				temas hay disco para rato, de un contenido doom metal melódico alternado con unos interminables
				pasajes electro-acústicos instrumentales a modo "loop" que pasados 3 o 4 minutos como que sobran.
				Aparte, cuando empieza realmente el metal doomero alterna las típicas vocales graves rasgadas para
				con voces sensualmente claras dotándo el álbum de bastante atmósfera. Sintetizadores, guitarras
				acústicas y eléctricas, pero el feeling que desprenden estas composiciones no expresan ni tristeza
				ni desesperación, ni rabia ni dolor, si no que a mi entender en sentimiento de relajación acojedor.
				En definitiva, el trabajo real de doom metal muy bien, las partes repetitivas durante largos
				periodos la verdad que estropean el producto de forma considerable.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Caym" zine="Metal Land" date="04????">
			<p>
				Cet album composé en 4 ans a vu ses compositions arrangées, réarrangées et reréarrangées. tout cela
				pour arriver à un doom mélodique mélancolique, dépressif et complexe. Utilisant un certains nombres
				d'instruments et de dérives électroniques autour du noyau dur guitare, basse et batterie, l'auteur
				et unique interprète de "Departure" met en musique des textes sombres et poétiques. Et les
				passages beaucoup plus virulents de l'album accentuent encore plus cette sensation de mélancolie et
				de noirceur en y ajoutant de la violence ce qui donne à cet album une puissance et une ambiance
				étonnante. C'est à se demander comment Forest Of Shadows peut encore faire partie de notre monde
				(mais le fait il vraiment) en ayant ne serait ce que l'idée de composer une telle musique... Il n'y
				a que deux mots à dire: follement sublime!!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Skyklad" zine="The Metal Gospel" date="04????">
			<p>
				With having only 5 tracks but clocking in at slightly over 65 minutes and taking into consideration
				the label who released this, you can easily guess what this one man project from Sweden is offering:
				Moody Doom Death Metal. Niclas Frohagen, the man behind this massive vision, started FOREST OF
				SHADOWS in 1997 and the first release was a miniCD entitled "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" in 2001.
				Since that time this album has been in the works until finally being released at the end of last
				year. What you get is an extremely depressive slab of predominantly Doom Death Metal with
				melancholic clean vocals contrasted by traditional slow and deep Death growling. Atmospheric
				keyboard work wells up at just the right moments while other times mournful guitar melodies weave
				here and there. Use of instruments like rhodes, piano, mellotrone and djembe give this a lot more
				depth, adding perfectly to the atmosphere and mood created by the riffs and vocals. Normally I don´t
				mention lyrics but the last time I listened to this it was a snowy, cold day and I was awaiting my
				tea water to boil so I flipped through the booklet and read the lyrics to find that they are very
				well written and thought out, capturing the essence of the music quite fittingly. Each song
				successfully goes from being calm and somewhat tranquilizing to extreme and then often to being
				calmer again. Nice build-up in this manner. When I hear this it fills me with the urge to open my
				veins and pour my life away. To convey that kind of emotion is what I would call a success for any
				Doom Death band. Recommended listening: "November Dream" and "Departure".
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Volker" zine="Metalspheres Fanzine" date="04????">
			<p>
				"Departure" ist parallel mit dem neuen Album von Aarni die Premierenveröffentlichung von Firedoom
				Records, kürzlich erst aus der Zweiteilung des finnischen Labels Firebox entstanden. Während unter
				dem bisherigen Namen nun die anderen Metalsparten beherbergt werden, konzentriert sich Firedoom, wie
				der Name schon sagt, auf meist sehr spezielle Vertreter der langsamsten Gangart. Forest of Shadows
				haben dabei die Ehre, Teil eines feinen Programmes zu sein - genauer gesagt hat sie der Schwede
				Niclas Frohagen, der das Projekt seit 1997 bis hin zur Produktion weitgehend im Alleingang betreibt.
			</p>
			<p>
				In fünf allesamt finster betitelten und überlangen Stücken findet sich hier eine recht eigenwillige
				Interpretation doomiger Klänge, die minimalistische Klanglandschaften ebenso wie sehr schöne
				Melodien einschliesst. 61 Minuten Gesamtspielzeit sagen wohl schon aus, das hier für konventionelles
				Songwriting wenig Platz ist. Der 17minütige Opener "Sleeping Death" startet über die Hälfte der Zeit
				hinweg mit düsterer Monotonie, die ein wenig an die Platten von Penitent erinnert, sowie dezenten
				Elektronika im Stile von Antimatter. Wirkt etwas in die Länge gezogen, bis dann das Stück eine recht
				drastische Wendung nimmt, um fortan dem klassischen Doom/Death zu huldigen, verzweifelte Growls
				miteinbegriffen. Mit mehr Stimmungswechseln wartet dagegen "November Dream" auf, sanfte Vocals
				treffen auf wiederum harsche Ausbrüche, feine Gitarren-Melodien werden eingewoben, die Keyboards
				erinnern an Hymnen von While Heaven Wept und zwischendrin nimmt das Stück auch mal richtig Fahrt auf.
				Als atmosphärisches Highlight sei dazu "Open Wound" genannt, das durch seine ebenso traurige wie
				wärmende Atmosphäre genau das richtige für einen wehmütigen Blick aus dem Fenster an verregneten
				Januar-Tagen ist.
			</p>
			<p>
				Zwar ist "Departure" anfangs ein wenig an mir vorbeigeplätschert, aber wenn man
				sich in Ruhe mit dem Album auseinandersetzt, lassen sich lohnenswerte Entdeckungen machen. Frohagen
				erweist sich jedenfalls an allen eingesetzten Instrumenten als kompetent und schlägt sich auch als
				Sänger trotz einiger etwas dünner Clean-Parts ordentlich. Zum Aufstieg in den Doom-Olmyp reicht es
				allerdings auf Grund des mitunter etwas langatmigen Songwritings (noch) nicht.
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="where dreams turn to dust | mcd 2001">
		<item author="vk66" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="150102" rating="100%">
			<p>
				Can you imagine a soulful death/doom album? An album with an absolute sense of loss as if there's nothing else left to look forward to but a true sense of pain entwined in the coldness of a Swedish winter? Imagine the gloomy skies, the terrible snow, the coldness seeping in through your breath, in the cracks of your hands now weak and fragile due to the absolute devastation of your senses just by being human? Can you imagine that? The emotional despair of being in such a frame of mind, unable to comprehend why or how but just closing your eyes trying to introspect but end with no answers, each and every single time. That exactly is what the EP is all about. Where Dreams Turn to Dust is an overlooked doom/death masterpiece and must be one of the best kept Swedish secrets. This is pristine melodic doom/death and must be one of the best EP's of the genre. When was the last time you've heard of an absolutely emotional record in this genre of music? One can throw in Swallow The Sun's work as a point of comparison, yes, it will stand up to what Forest of Shadows offers on this release but where any material will fall short in comparison is the songwriting department. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The EP opens with Eternal Autumn, as the quiet enchanting flute solo wraps your senses, Niclas Frohagen's vocals kick in tattooing the pain of his voice on you, these are possibly one of the best and consistent vocals I've heard in this genre of music. The vocals truly represent the disappointment and immense pain of the lyrics, neither are these the best ones every written nor is there a significant literary value but what the lyrics succeed in doing is expressing the sadness at it's best and cohesively puts the agitation of a soul immersed in loss and lost in memories, example below - 
			</p>
			<p>
				Amidst withering leaves
				I had found my beloved
				Bloodstained and pale
				Falling into the forever
				So silent.
			</p>
			<p>
				Aware of my presence
				She turned towards me
				Her agonizing stare,
				one last breath and she whispered: Everything dies.
			</p>
			<p>
				Another aspect of this album that is most impressive are the vocals, when Niclas is singing the 3rd line from the above paragraph you actually notice the agony translating from the words and it being passed on. This is all across the album and makes for an absolute treat to the senses, you seldom see vocalists translating the written emotion through their vocals while the guitars support them with the most beautiful and consistent riffs. If one dissects Eternal Autumn, you'd probably count the riffs on your fingers but how well they've been arranged and built together with the drumming on this album is everything. The atmosphere as such engulfs you for every single moment; considering the shortest song on the album is 8:20 long, the band absolutely holds your attention every single second of every song and in all honesty leaves you begging for more. The tone of the guitars is an important aspect of this release, as much as the distorted sections sound in perfect harmony with the vocals creating the atmosphere, the clean parts are the most beautiful which truly add the gloom to the sadness. Slow, melodic and hurting.
			</p>
			<p>
				My favourite track of this EP is Of Sorrow Blue, as this is the band at it's melodic best. This song truly represents what Forest of Shadows is all about, most delicate acoustic parts adorn the passage between verses as the vocals disturb your notion of calm. The guitars are gentle and heavy, transcending slowly through the thick atmosphere which clears up to a beautiful violin solo. These transitions are done to perfection: imagine a glimmer of sunshine on a snowy day, the hope it brings, the momentary satisfaction it fills us with and leaves as quickly as it touched us pushing us back into the same abyss of never ending darkness. This is exactly what the band does to perfection. The depth in the vocals push what these songs sound to the next level, there's not an aorta of joy or hope, it's an outright descent into darkness and doubt. The sound on Swallow The Sun's The Morning Never Came album is the closest I can think of as a comparison,. Take that sound, slow it down in places, add the loneliness of a winter to it and drench it all in the pain of longing and we have this EP, an absolute masterpiece and a jewel amongst releases in this genre.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="HowlingMoom666" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="121020" rating="100%">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows is without a doubt one of the greatest doom metal bands in the world, competing for first place with Swedish doom metallers Draconian. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows is one of those bands that can bring you to the verge of tears with their music and lyrics even if you pretend to be the strongest fucker who roamed the Earth. You cannot resist the assault on your memories and tears keep falling against your will down to the floor. This is a great gift for a doom metal band in my view.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Eternal Autumn" is the best song on this ep. This should be the official doom metal anthem in all countries in the world. It's atmospheric and so damn well built without any gap in-between. The song flows smoothly for about 9 minutes and a half, a short period of time for such a masterpiece. This song should be 10 hours. I' m not sure you wouldn't want it to be 10 days after listening to it of course, if you are a doom metal fan or just an emotional music lover. The lyrics as presented on this site are chaotic without the needed punctuation marks, so you better follow them as the song flows on. This will lead you to the utmost experience. It will lead you to tears. 
			</p>
			<p>
				This band can manipulate the soul, at least mine. I dreamed about my dying girlfriend after listening to this song. I awoke crying, calling her in the middle of the night just to tell her how much I love her. Forest of Shadows made it. It brought me face to face with my fears, helping me to prevail over them. 
			</p>
			<p>
				You probably know very well, all of you, that doom metal is a genre that is quite narrow and deprived of originality sometimes. With "Where Dreams Turn to Dust" , Forest of Shadows succeeded what Draconian did with their demo "The Closed Eyes of Paradise"; to break the boundaries and bring something new to this old-fashioned genre. 
			</p>
			<p>
				"Of Sorrow Blue" is the next gem in line, gloomy and stern with something strange luring inside it. I would call this band's genre melodic doom metal. Their riffs are too well-crafted and not the peculiar, ordinary doom metal riffs. Their guitar sound is something near to a weeping violin. It has beautiful atmospheric parts with acoustic guitars and breaks of a splendor I cannot relate into words. 
			</p>
			<p>
				I gave them the maximum rating. I do not regret it.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="sharkbait" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="080512" rating="98%">
			<p>
				It isn't very often when an album hits me emotionally. Forest of Shadows does this very well in this EP. They aren't a generic doom metal band, I feel. This EP has some foreign sounds for the genre. Acoustic guitars are often added, same with other instruments (such as a flute in the song Eternal Autumn). These other instruments mix beautifully. Each song is very similar, but unique enough to enjoy. The atmosphere created is overwhelming at times. The song Wish got a hold of me the most. From the first second to the last, you are in a new world. A very beautiful, but sad, song. By the end of it, I am in tears almost every time. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The guitar is very good. It is very nicely written. Same goes for all of the other instruments. I absolutely love the vocals. He has a very nice voice that matches perfectly with this kind of music. The sound quality is good. The lyrics are nicely written, they're very poetic. Wish is the best song on this EP. Here's a sample of the closing lyrics; the highlight of the song:
			</p>
			<p>
				"...Still I dream, but now I know,
				I dream a lie, so I close my eyes and I sigh,
				A life of shattered dreams, I can no longer bear,
				I enter thee eternal sleep."
			</p>
			<p>
				The only bad thing about this album is that it can get boring near the middle of the last song. All three songs are fairly slow, which can make the listener feel like it's dragging on. Since it is slow, it is very relaxing.
			</p>
			<p>
				They definably stand out among other doom metal bands. This EP is my favorite recording out of the genre. I highly recommend this one.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="grimdoom" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="080503" rating="100%">
			<p>
				Spell binding and sheer brilliance are the only ways to describe this EP. The atmosphere of this album is nothing short of awe inspiring. The music hits you with a wall of hopelessness and beauty that you simply can't tear yourself away from. This is by far one of the absolute BEST Doomdeath Metal releases of all time.
			</p>
			<p>
				For starters, the production is ok but could have been better; but the three songs contained within don't suffer for it. The guitars are thick and moody. There is very little if any crunch in their sound; however, they do have some good mournful leads. The bass is more or less buried in the mix except for when it’s in an intro/outro or quieter moment in any of the songs. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The drums are bombastic, in an artsy way. The keyboards only add to the dense atmosphere created by the guitars. There is a flute and violin used to very good effect as well. The vocals are both clean and grim. The cleans are heavily accented and have some reverb/delay on them. The grim vocals fit the music perfectly and sound as though they have some reverb on them as well.
			</p>
			<p>
				Over all, the only true drawback is that this is just and EP instead of a full album. The originality and passion displayed on these three songs is breath taking. It’s a shame that its follow up was so lackluster. This is highly recommended to all!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Unsilent Storms" zine="Encyclopaedia Metallum" date="061010" rating="99%">
			<p>
				Every now and then in ones lifetime, one is presented with things that touch you so deep inside, for better or for worse, your life is 	changed forever. In a world so automated and predictable, listening to this 3 song ep by Forest of Shadows took me away from the daily task of life into a world all of my own, where I experienced music that brought me close to tears.
			</p>
			<p>
				In this ode to love, and having it taken away, the quality of both the music and the production are top notch. Where to start? How to describe this music that has me so enthralled and yearning for so much more! The music is so hauntingly beautiful, weaving in between acoustic guitar passages with clean vocals to deep growling vocals accompanied of electric guitar riffs that seem more like violins crying.
			</p>
			<p>
				“Where Dreams turn to Dust”, consists of 3 songs, the shortest clocking in at 8:22, one could thing this is a bad thing, when done in a cheesy predictable way a song this length could seem like an eternity, but when done with such class and beauty, it is not nearly enough.
			</p>
			<p>
				The first track is “Eternal Autumn”, as soon as it starts with its medieval flute intro, so hauntingly perfect, you almost feel like you are on top of the tower of a Castle hundreds of years ago, gazing away into a never ending forest, this is interrupted by a sudden lament, a love story told in 2 different voices, a clean one and a demonic growl which tells us the story of a women dying in her lovers arms to great effect, you can certainly feel the distress and agony of this man as his beloved dies in hi arms.
			</p>
			<p>
				Where Dreams Turn to Dust, closes out with 2 other very long songs, “Wish” and “Of Sorrow Blue” which is a whopping 11 minutes and 30 seconds long, and all I can think of as the last song fades into silence is I want more! It’s not enough! 
			</p>
			<p>
				If I had to compare this band to other bands for comparisons sake it would be October Tide, Katatonia, early Opeth and early Anathema. The majesty of Forest of Shadows though is precisely that. This work can stand proud next to the before mentioned giants music wise, concept wise and lyrics wise, it is well crafted melancholic doom metal that should be in every doom fanatics collection!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Hawk" zine="The Metal Observer" date="060316" rating="10/10">
			<p>
				As "Departure", the first long player of FOREST OF SHADOWS, had been so to my liking, I just bought
				the EP "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" as well. And I must say that it is even better. Three songs with
				a playing time of almost half an hour does not really give any illusions for potential radio hits
				(which would be delusional with a Doom band anyway). This EP also is pure melancholy, but packed into
				beautiful melodies, so that you can't stop listening to the songs.
			</p>
			<p>
				Opener "Eternal Autumn" captures the perfect mood of a grey autumn day. The song begins with the
				bittersweet sounds of a German flute, which could put you to sleep, if there was not this inimitable,
				heavy guitar melody coming in after roundabout a minute. And this gemstone of a melody leads you
				through the whole song, with little variations, slow, but with a purpose. A pity that after nine
				extremely entertaining minutes it already is over. But then it continues with "Wish", which for FOREST
				OF SHADOWS is quite varied. First of all the brutal vocals tear you from your dreams, while the
				fantastic harmonies soothe you again right away. And the cleverly incorporated clear vocals then give
				you the rest. Here you can feel excited and then relax again. The song sounds like a relief for the
				hopeless melancholic.
			</p>
			<p>
				At the end we have "Of Sorrow Blue", also a wonderful hymn to tristesse. This song, too, is borne by
				a brilliant melody, which rises more and more. The guitars flare up every now and then, but are always
				loosened up by acoustic guitars and piano parts, as well some violin. In between they surprise with
				some double-bass, just to slow down a lot towards the end. Old PARADISE LOST and AMORPHIS fans should
				get this masterpiece, if you see it, it is SO worth it!!!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Mikko Kuronen" zine="imhotep" date="051229" rating="7/10">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows have a marvellous flair for granting their music a languid pulse of living, one
				that compels you to step inside its serene maze of paleness and measure the gravity of time,
				something these laconic outruns of doom never take as a very important issue. The music of Forest of
				Shadows is parallel universe stuff - it takes you apart from whatever you were doing before the first
				euphonies rowed across the lake, escorting you to a Forest of Shadows reality: a world that - with
				its soul-starving plodding and glacial sincerity - hammers home another ice age.
			</p>
			<p>
				This sentiment is conveyed clearly enough on the solemn three tracks of "Where Dreams Turn to Dust",
				an MCD first released as a demo back in 2000, then rereleased as an EP a year later and now issued as
				a remastered digipak version following the success of last year's "Departure". What makes this work
				differ the most from "Departure" is that the remastering has not been able to sweep away all the
				murkiness of the sound, thus making "Where Dreams..." perhaps a bit of a heavier listen than the
				debut album. One point is deducted for the possibility of this being just a very clever shenanigan
				of slowing down Katatonia's "Brave Murder Day" and sticking a bunch of My Dying Violins on top for an
				effect of remarkable intimacy.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Nikki Sixx" zine="Metal Storm" date="050717" rating="9.2/10">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows. When I first listened to their EP "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" I remained
				speechless, I couldn't utter a single word or make a sound. The emotions that had overran me while
				listening to this brilliant 3-track EP where so many, so intense, so bleak, so heart-rending that I
				remained there where I was sitting lost in my own world of bitterness and pain. Forest Of Shadows'
				melodic doom/death metal is filled with intense emotions evoking a grey atmosphere as if you were
				lost in "a forest of shadows" mourning your beloved one or even mourning your very own self welcoming
				"eternal autumn" to your life.
			</p>
			<p>
				Through Forest of Shadows' music you can notice here and there some Katatonia influences whereas the
				clear melancholic voice of Niclas brings forth memories of Garm's (Ulver) chanting voice on their
				"Bergtatt"-"Kveldssanger" period. Forest of Shadows have their influences, as every band, yet they do
				not copy them and what they are doing is to harmonize in a unique way their influences with their
				personal ideas and emotions composing songs that will keep you chained in solitude drowned in their
				melodic doom/death metal.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Oh autumn hath arrived."
			</p>
			<p>
				"Eternal Autumn" echos and you start losing yourself there "where dreams turn to dust" with the
				nostalgic sound of the flute surrounding you. The melodic doomy guitar riffing makes you shiver with
				its emotional charge as Niclas' grunts surpass you like a wind carrying cries of pain and anger
				whereas the acoustic moments with acoustic guitar chords and Niclas' enchanting sorrowful voice drown
				you deeper and deeper in a sea filled with oblivious tears. The musical background is the ideal for
				such poetic lyrics telling about the loss of your beloved welcoming the "eternal autumn" in your life
				interpreted on the most descriptive way by Niclas Frohagen.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Awakened this dying season" grunts Niclas accompanied by the mournful guitar riffing as the
				following "Wish" begins. The guitar work is deeply inspired evoking a bleak atmosphere in the air
				accompanying Niclas' desperate grunts and heart-rending chanting voice singing lyrics of utter
				emotional bitterness, longing/wishing for someone to love and finally embracing the eternal sleep,
				the release of all of all the pain and sorrow "in this oh so dolorous life." "Of Sorrow Blue" leads
				the album slowly to its end. Everything consisting of this composition makes it a doleful opus; the
				mourning guitar riffing, the bleeding guitar chords, the wailing violin melodies that make you shiver
				whenever they enter the song, the imposing rhythm section and Niclas' utterly descriptive grunting
				voice and chants evoke the ideal grey autumn atmosphere, raging at times, wailing at others, for you
				to drown in a world of everlasting solitude and pain. 
			</p>
			<p>
				If you found it somewhere and didn't buy it you should kill yourself.
			</p>
			<p>
				"A life of shattered dreams I can no longer bear I enter thee eternal sleep."
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Oliver Vollmer" zine="metal-reviews.de.com" date="031105">
			<p>
				Die knapp halbstündige 3-Track-Scheibe der Schweden kommt zum Single-Preis in die Läden, was schon
				mal für ein gutes Preis-Leistungs-Verhältnis spricht. Auch die Mucke selbst ist kein Fehlgriff,
				wenngleich düsterer Depri-Doom seit Jahren aus der Mode ist. FOREST OF SHADOWS sind eine Art
				Light-Version von SHAPE OF DESPAIR mit starkem PARADISE LOST-Flair. Langsame Hymnen der Traurigkeit
				wurden ergo mit melancholisch-melodischen Leads verknüpft, die von bittersüßen Geigen schmachtend
				veredelt werden. Der Song "Wish" hat dann, neben der wirklich starken P.L.-Reminiszenzen auch eine
				deutliche Schlagseite an alte(!) KATATONIA. Schöner Sound für den Herbst, wenn man mit sorgenfaltiger
				Miene des Nachts auf dem Sofa sinniert, was hätte sein können. Leider ist "Of Sorrow Blue" recht
				statisch und dröge ausgefallen, so dass man sich "nur" die ersten beiden Songs leidend amüsiert. Ein
				ganzes Album in der Art dieser beiden Tracks wär allerdings geil.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="Cryptic Madness" date="030401" rating="6/6">
			<p>
				J'ai maintenant la chance d'être le premier à chroniquer cet album. Forest of Shadows est un
				excellent groupe de Doom, signé sur Rage of Achilles, qui m'ont tout de suite charmé par la pesanteur
				et l'émotion transmises par l'entremise d'une guitare enivrante et d'une voix déchirante.
			</p>
			<p>	
				Un mcd de 27 minutes... mais il vaut vraiment la peine. Simplement trois pistes qui sont tout trois
				excellentes. La première piste débute avec une légère flûte qui nous plonge soudainement dans
				l'atmosphère du disque. Les compositions et les riffs de guitare sont recherchés et accompagnent bien
				les bons cris graves. Les paroles sont aussi bien élaborées.
			</p>
			<p>	
				L'ambiance est tout à fait sublime. À chaque écoute j'en suis troublé. Un disque qui frise la
				perfection. Je ne peux que réécouter ce mcd en attendant la sortie d'un nouvel album.
			</p>
			<p>
				À acheter, à écouter et à apprécier.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="vampster.com" date="021223">
			<p>
				Nichts Neues unter dem blassen Mond. Was THY SERPENT und RAPTURE können, können auch FOREST OF
				SHADOWS. Sie alle mögen die alten MY DYING BRIDE, KATATONIA und ANATHEMA und machen heute dort
				weiter, wo diese Bands vor einiger Zeit aufgehört haben. Verdrießlicher, nachtfinsterer und
				grabeskalter Death-Doom-Metal scheint sich wieder größerer Beliebtheit unter den Skandinaviern zu
				erfreuen, was nicht weiter schlimm ist, solange so wunderschön tieftraurige Songs wie die von "Where
				Dreams Turn To Dust" das Ergebnis sind. Die drei Titel bringen es auf die stattliche Spielzeit von
				fast dreißig Minuten, und diese Länge brauchen die Songs auch, um ihre Wirkung zu entfalten.
				Herzergreifende Melodien, schwermütiger klarer Gesang und verzweifelte Growls im Wechsel sind die
				Basis für die Songs, selten klagt eine Violine oder trudelt eine zarte Flötenmelodie wie ein vom
				Herbst vergessenes Blatt im Winterwind durch die Gitarrenstürme. Neu ist das alles nicht, doch man
				kann kaum eindringlichere Musik in diesem Genre schreiben. Von lahmen Selbstmitleid-Epen ist das
				schwedische Duo weit entfernt, statt weinerlichen Einschlafstücken entrücken FOREST OF SHADOWS mit
				stellenweise verzweifelt-aggressiven Passagen und Doublebass-Dynamik in eine Welt, die schwarz und
				kalt ist, in der es aber auch Raum für Gefühlsausbrüche gibt . Die Klippen Lethargie und Kitsch
				umschiffen FOREST OF SHADOWS, und nehmen den Zuhörer mit auf das schwarze, kalte und dunkle Meer der
				Melancholie, über dem vereinzelt Sterne funkeln - Sterne wie diese drei Songs. Bleibt zu hoffen,
				dass sie nicht vor ihrer Zeit verglühen, denn das Duo hat sich mittlerweile leider getrennt. Niclas
				Frohagen will aber unter dem Namen FOREST OF SHADOWS mit Gastmusikern weitermachen. Es besteht also
				Hoffnung auf ein ganzes Album.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Oliver Vollmar" zine="BrightEyes" date="021223">
			<p>
				Die knapp halbstündige 3-Track-Scheibe der Schweden kommt zum Single-Preis in die Läden, was schon
				mal für ein gutes Preis-Leistungs-Verhältnis spricht. Auch die Mucke selbst ist kein Fehlgriff,
				wenngleich düsterer Depri-Doom seit Jahren aus der Mode ist. FOREST OF SHADOWS sind eine Art
				Light-Version von SHAPE OF DESPAIR mit starkem PARADISE LOST-Flair. Langsame Hymnen der Traurigkeit
				wurden ergo mit melancholisch-melodischen Leads verknüpft, die von bittersüßen Geigen schmachtend
				veredelt werden. Der Song "Wish" hat dann, neben der wirklich starken P.L.-Reminiszenzen auch eine
				deutliche Schlagseite an alte(!) KATATONIA. Schöner Sound für den Herbst, wenn man mit
				sorgenfaltiger Miene des Nachts auf dem Sofa sinniert, was hätte sein können. Leider ist "Of Sorrow
				Blue" recht statisch und dröge ausgefallen, so dass man sich "nur" die ersten beiden Songs leidend
				amüsiert. Ein ganzes Album in der Art dieser beiden Tracks wär allerdings geil.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="www.tiefgang-online.de" date="021223" rating="100%">
			<p>
				Düsteren Metal aus Skandinavien gibt es mittlerweile wie Sand am Meer, doch "Forest Of Shadows" sind
				dahingehend eine Ausnahme. Warum dem so ist versuche ich zu erklären. Es gibt wenige Combos die es
				auf Anhieb schaffen, den Hörer vom ersten bis zum letzten Takt zu fesseln und in eine Welt zu
				geleiten, in der er sich wiedererkennt. In dieser Welt leben die Schatten, dort ist das
				unbeschreibliche Leid, die Trauer zum greifen nah. Nach kurzem Erschrecken erkennt man, dass es sich
				hier nicht um Fiktion sondern um die eigene Gefühlswelt handelt. Die Band spielt ihre Melancholie
				voll aus, die sie sicher in sich haben muss um einen solchen Sound überhaupt umsetzen zu können.
				Nachdem man sich bewusst geworden ist um was es sich handelt, schliesst man beruhigt die Augen und
				geniesst den musikalischen Erguss, der durch leichtes Anheben der Körperbehaarung in Intensität noch
				verstärkt wird. Textlich erzählen die Schweden genau von dem, was man sich vor seinem inneren Auge
				gerade vorstellt. Die Grundemotionen Angst und Trauer werden hier nicht übermässig strapaziert,
				sondern sind ein grosser Bestandteil des Werkes. Nichtsdestotrotz erfüllt den Hörer auch Hoffung und
				Zuversicht, denn manches ist zwar von Schmerz geprägt, bedeutet aber dennoch nicht das
				unwiderrufliche Ende. Die Stimme ist sehr variabel und ergänzt hervorragend den episch/düsteren
				Sound. Instrumentell werden nicht nur dröhnende Gitarren und ein hämmerndes Schlagzeug verwendet,
				sondern es wird auch Platz für Flöten, akustische Gitarren und Geigen gefunden. Nachteil des Ganzen
				ist, dass es sich hier lediglich um eine EP von nur drei Tracks handelt und man viel zu früh wieder
				in die eigene Realität entlassen wird. Vorteil im Nachteil, die Gesamtspielzeit beträgt fast 30
				Minuten und dem Zuhörer bleibt ausreichend Zeit, bevor er die Reise in die Schatten der Wälder erneut
				beginnen muss. Das Label kommt dem interessierten Musikliebhaber entgegen und bietet dieses
				Meisterwerk zum Maxi - CD Preis an. Ich kann nur zum Kauf auffordern und auf den
				Veröffentlichungstermin Anfang nächsten Jahres verweisen, wo Forest Of Shadows ihr erstes Full
				Length Album präsentieren werden.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Kathy Shütte" zine="powermetal.de" date="021223">
			<p>
				Auf ein Neues hat die skandinavische Metal-Szenerie eine Band hervorgebracht: FOREST OF SHADOWS, die
				wie so viele andere Musikerkollegen aus der schwedischen Stadt Göteborg stammen. Nach der Gründung
				1997 durch Mastermind Niclas Frohagen und der Veröffentlichung diverser Demos und Promos, welche samt
				und sonders in Eigenregie produziert wurden, konnte das nach eigenen Angaben maßgeblich von Künstlern
				wie MY DYING BRIDE und KATATONIA beeinflusste Gespann 2001 einen Vertrag mit dem englischen Label
				Rage Of Achilles ergattern - ein Glück, denn sonst wäre uns die beeindruckende, epische Debüt-EP
				"Where Dreams Turn To Dust" wohl noch ein Weilchen länger verwehrt geblieben. Anfang 2003 soll dann
				ein komplettes Full-Length-Album folgen. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Wer denkt, dass mit den drei Songs der Scheibe nur ein relativ kurzes Hörvergnügen bevorsteht, den
				strafen FOREST OF SHADOWS gleich Lügen: Satte 30 Minuten Spielzeit weist "Where Dreams Turn To Dust"
				vor, und die haben es wirklich in sich. Jedes Stück entwickelt sich zu einem kleinen epischen
				Meisterwerk, welches den Bogen von atmosphärischer Melodik über herbstliche Trauerstimmung bis hin
				zu düster-doomiger Schwere spannt - da haben MY DYING BRIDE als Vorbilder schon mal gute Arbeit
				geleistet.
			</p>
			<p>
				Welche Band mit als Reflexionspunkt aber zusätzlich noch einfällt - und das besonders beim
				Eingangsstück "Eternal Autumn" - , das sind die Tiroler von GRAVEWORM. Ähnlich wie sie verknüpfen
				FOREST OF SHADOWS klassische Elemente wie Flöten- und Violinenmelodien oder auf der Akustikgitarre
				vorgetragene Passagen stimmig mit ihrem doomig gestimmten Gesamtkonzept und pendeln dazu wohltuend
				zwischen dem satten Grunzgesang und den cleanen Vocals von Niclas hin und her. Die Folge:
				Ohrenschmaus mit Garantie - das melancholische Eingangstück hat sich gleich nach dem ersten Hören
				als mein absoluter Favorit etabliert. Aber auch die nachfolgenden Tracks machen eine gute Figur:
				"Wish" legt gleich noch mal einige Tonnen mehr an Düsterschwere auf und verbreitet eine noch
				apokalyptischere Stimmung als sein Vorgänger - wenn auch nicht ganz so melodisch ausgearbeitet. Und
				"Of Sorrow Blue" präsentiert sich abschließend als eine Art Mischung aus den ersten beiden: Die
				klassisch-harmonischen Elemente und Einschübe rücken wieder etwas mehr ins Zentrum, wobei anfangs
				die "schwerere Schwere" noch beibehalten wird und im Verlauf des Stücks einer mit Doublebass-Auftritt
				gekoppelten Tempoerhöhung weicht, bis man schließlich den Song mit viel akustischer Gitarre und Geige
				sanft ausklingen lässt. Hach, wie schön... 
			</p>
			<p>
				Im Anbetracht des hohen musikalischen Niveaus dieser EP - deren einziges Manko darin liegt, dass der
				Sound etwas fetter und weniger höhenlastig hätte ausfallen können - bin ich schon ganz heiß darauf
				zu hören, ob der angekündigte Longplayer im kommenden Jahr das halten kann, was "Where Dreams Turn
				To Dust" verspricht. Wenn ja, dann steht uns Großes ins Haus... Ansonsten: Leute, für die sich eine
				Mischung aus MY DYING BRIDE und GRAVEWORM gut anhört, sollten sich diese Scheibe unbedingt zu Gemüte
				führen, genauso wie Liebhaber epischem Düstermetalls. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Anspieltipps: im Prinzip alle drei Songs, aber ganz speziell "Eternal Autumn".
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="MK" zine="obliveon.de" date="021223" rating="100%">
			<p>
				Verdammt, wann zuletzt haben mich nur drei Songs einer Band derart mitgerissen, wie die der Schweden
				Forest of Shadows? "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" ist ein monumentales und epochales Epos, das die
				Schwermut My Dying Bride´s mit den Melodien der frühen Katatonia verbindet und nicht weniger als ein
				unvergängliches Meisterwerk darstellt. Hier existiert sie noch, die unvergleichliche Tiefe, die
				Seele in der Musik, die mit jeder Silbe und jeder Note ihr Innerstes nach aussen kehrt und eine
				Gänsehaut nach der anderen erzeugt; die Schwermut, die der herbstlichen Jahreszeit so eigen ist und
				selten treffender besungen wurde, als in "Wish": "Awakened this dying season, such a beauty to
				behold, oh autumn hath arrived, a tragedy painted dead..."; das Bewusstsein, das uns befällt, wenn man
				den Eindruck gewinnt, das hier Künstler am Werk sind, die von ihrem eigenen Werk selbst ergriffen
				sind. Anfang nächsten Jahres erscheint das erste komplette Album der Band, gerade rechtzeitig, um
				möglichen Entzugserscheinungen vorzubeugen. Diese EP, die übrigens zum Maxi-Preis erhältlich ist,
				ist der Hammer!!!!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Janick" zine="music-scan.de" date="021223" rating="80%">
			<p>
				"Where Dreams Turn To Dust" heißt das erste Lebenszeichen von Forest Of Shadows. Die MCD enthält drei
				Songs; das ist nicht viel werdet ihr denken, doch diese drei Songs schaffen es auf eine Spielzeit von
				knapp 30 Minuten! Die Songs haben mich sofort in ihren Bann gezogen. Die beiden Schweden schaffen es
				eine wunderschöne düstere und melancholische Atmosphäre zu erzeugen. Das Tempo ist gedrosselt und
				verstärkt somit diesen Eindruck und lässt das Ganze zu einem epischen Sound verschmelzen. Die Jungs
				erinnern mich an My Dying Bride und an alte Paradise Lost zu seeligen Gothic-Zeiten. Die Stimme im
				cleanen Bereich dagegen erinnert mich manchmal an das warme und wohlig tieftönende Organ eines Johan
				Edlund von Tiamat, besonders beim ersten Song "Eternal Autumn". Genau wie es dieser Titel verrät
				kredenzen uns Forest Of Shadows mit ihrer Musik den idealen Soundtrack zu unserer herbstlichen
				Jahreszeit. Die Jungs machen definitiv Lust auf mehr und ich freue mich schon jetzt auf ihr erstes
				Full Length Album, welches nächstes Jahr erscheinen soll. Fazit: Wer mit Bands wie Katatonia, My
				Dying Bride, alte Paradise Lost und Godgory etwas anfangen kann, sollte diese Jungs auf jeden Fall
				mal antesten. Ein weiterer Grund den beiden Schweden eine Chance zu geben besteht darin, daß diese
				MCD im Rahmen der Newcomer Kampagne von Rage Of Achilles Records zum Single Preis in die Läden kommt!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Sebastian" zine="in-your-face.de" date="021223" rating="83%">
			<p>
				Nachdem mir FOREST OF SHADOWS schon auf dem Rage of Achilles-Label Sampler aufgefallen sind - das
				Review könnt Ihr HIER lesen - und ich sie da zur besten Band gekürt hatte, freue ich mich umso mehr
				das "Where dreams come true" nun in meinen Händen gelandet ist. Musikalisch tendeln die Schweden
				zwischen My Dying Bride und In the Woods .... , bieten aber sehr eigenständigen Dark- und Doom-Metal.
				Dieses Album, welches zum Preis einer Single in den Läden stehen wird, enthält die drei Songs
				"Eternal Autumn", "Wish" und "Of Sorrow Blue". Falls Ihr Euch denkt, dass drei Songs doch etwas
				wenig sind, muss man natürlich dazu sagen, dass eine Spielzeit von rund 30 Minuten erreicht wird,
				was ja schon an ein normales Album von Deceide rankommt. Für alle Freunde der düsteren, langsamen
				und anspruchsvollen Musik sind FOREST OF SHADOWS ein echter Kauftipp. Alle anderen dürfen sich gerne
				mal in ferne Wälder entführen lassen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="deathgrind.de" date="021223" rating="4/5">
			<p>
				Episch, hymnisch, verträumt und irgendwie... schön. So in etwa könnte man die Klangwelten des
				Schattenwaldes mit ein paar Worten umschreiben. Worte die natürlich mit keiner Silbe die warme Tiefe
				dieser Kompositionen wiederspiegeln. Ein eben solches Wort ist auch das von der Band offiziell
				gewählte Banner "Darkmetal" welches mitnichten die Vielschichtigkeit des Songmateriales wiedergeben
				könnte (aber welcher Schubladendeckel könnte das von sich behaupten). Mit "Where dreams turn into
				dust" hat das Duo den perfekten Soundtrack zur Entspannung einer malträtierten Metal - Seele
				erschaffen. Ein Traum, welcher einerseits aus dezentem Flötenspiel (u.a. Intro), Akustikgitarren und
				vollen, sehr warmen, cleanen Gesangpassagen besteht, anderseits aber auch mit hymnenhaften
				E-Gitarrenleads, Growls und Screams kokettieren, ohne jemals das harmonisch ausbalancierte Gesamtbild
				zu stören oder gar zu zerstören. Nach 30 Minuten und 3 Songs (!!!) ist dann leider der im Titel
				beschriebene Punkt erreicht und der Traum löst sich in Wohlgefallen auf...was bleibt sind 4
				wunderschöne Punkte... (taaataaa...)
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Andreas" zine="coreground.net" date="021222">
			<p>
				Was wird eine Band mit solchem Namen wohl für Musik spielen? Düsteren Metal, ganz recht. Reflexartig
				sucht man beim Flöten-Intro die Auswurftaste, in der Befürchtung, hier die Ethno-Vollbedienung zu
				bekommen, doch ist die Einleitung überstanden, geht es durchaus solide weiter. Forest Of Shadows
				bewegen sich ziemlich genau zwischen den Eckpfeilern My Dying Bride, ältere Theatre Of Tragedy,
				Amorphis und Moonspell. Alles sehr doomig, bedrückend und episch. Sie haben schöne Harmonien in den
				Stücken und insgesamt bleibt das Songwriting - trotzdem es gerne mal ausufert - einigermaßen
				nachvollziehbar. Ganz sicher nicht der Innovation letzter Schluss, aber allemal passend zur
				Jahreszeit und für Freunde des Genres sicher eine Entdeckung. Die Veröffentlichung ist Teil der Rage
				Of Achilles Newcomer-Serie und wird zum Preis einer Single in den Handel kommen.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Andreas" zine="amboss-mag.de" date="021222">
			<p>		
				Dies ist das erste Lebenszeichen der schwedischen Dark Metaller und als Vorgriff auf das in Kürze
				erscheinende Album zu sehen. Nordische Folklore trifft auf britischen Düster Metal in der Art von My
				Dying Bride oder Katatonia. Zwischen geflüsterten Growls und cleanem Gesang überzeugt die Musik mit
				ihrer atmosphärischen Ausrichtung. Während die Gitarren bleischwer in doomiger Weise einem Lava
				Strom gleichen, sorgt die mittelalterliche Instrumentierung mit Flute usw. für pure Melancholie.
				Tiefdepressiv mit Hang zum theatralischen sind drei episch, bombastische Stücke entstanden, welche
				auch den kleinsten Lichtschein in ein dunkles Etwas verwandeln. Orchestraler Doom erstreckt sich
				über dreißig Minuten und zieht den Hörer tief in den Abgrund der menschlichen Seele. Die perfekte
				Begleitmusik für einen nächtlichen Friedhofsspaziergang für Hartgesottene. Während die cleanen Parts
				von einer morbiden Romantik umgeben sind, erleben die growligen Parts die Auferstehung des Bösen. Ein
				musikalischer Alptraum ohne Hoffnung.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Markus Eck" zine="metalmessage.de" date="020915" rating="70%">
			<p>
				Dieses todtraurig anmutende schwedische Dunkelduo erfreut bzw. besser gesagt betrauert unsere Ohren
				mit	ihrem Debütminialbum "Where Dreams Turn To Dust". Melancholisch getragen, episch machtvoll,
				bombastisch	klangvoll, immens entrückt und in erster Linie zeitlos schwermütig zelebrieren die beiden
				dauerdepressiven Peinpoeten ihren massiv weltschmerzgetränkten Dark Metal, der mit einigen
				besinnlichen Akustikparts höchst sensibler und tränenerfüllter Emotionsnatur eindrucksvoll
				angereichert wurde. "Where Dreams Turn To Dust" weiß während knapp halbstündiger Spielzeit mit
				landestypischer, gewohnter skandinavischer Spielfinesse zu beeindrucken, jedoch ohne bereits
				vorhandene erfolgreiche Stilmuster solcher hier zu hörenden Inspirationshelfer wie älteren Katatonia
				oder frühen My Dying Bride blindlings zu kopieren. Forest Of Shadows setzen vielmehr auf eine
				prägnant nachdenklich wirkende Individualklangerscheinung, welche sich in wirklich faszinierender
				Instrumentaldarbietung veräußert: Von der mittelalterlich angehauchten, apokalyptischen Klangschwere
				einer Ausnahmeband wie Neurosis bis hin	zur atmosphärischen Dramaturgiedichte nordischer und
				britischer Dark Metal-Outfits reicht die reflektierte Bandbreite der verarbeiteten Einflüsse. Forest
				Of Shadows packen sich die allerbesten Gestaltungselemente solcher Acts und arrangieren sie
				ideenreich und versiert zu einem hochepischen und nachhaltig einnehmenden Tragiksound, der
				unweigerlich in seinen hypnotisierenden Bann zieht. Zu Anfang des Jahres 2003 ist der Release des
				erstes Longplayers geplant - wenn die Band auf diesem die durch dieses tolle Minialbum geweckten
				Erwartungen erfüllen kann, steht ein weiteres grandioses Werk nächtlicher schmerzerfüllter
				Sinnessehnsüchte an.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="voodoofire.co.uk" date="020723" rating="70%">
			<p>
				Not one for your cheery, dreaming of California Fu-Manchu fans this one - more of an opus to the
				misery of dark woods, moon-lit nights and the beauty in loneliness. Echoing the melancholic
				atmospheres of past masters such as My Dying Bride, or classic Paradise Lost, this half hour cut of
				doomed insanity peers through to the modern world courtesy of that bastion of quality Rage of
				Achilles. Hinting at the glory days of early 90s British deathly doom, FoS are clear lovers of the
				classic traditions of funeral marches, despair and ruin. If you need another dose of down-tuned,
				down-trodden, and most definitely down-tempo then look no further, for this one should be right down
				your (dark and scary) alley.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Pedro Azevedo" zine="Chronicles of Chaos #56" date="020304" rating="80%">
			<p>
				The debut EP by Sweden's Forest of Shadows contains three tracks of melodic doom/death lasting a
				total of over half an hour. Slow and mournful, Forest of Shadows combine death and clean vox, and
				also add an array of other instruments for a mildly orchestral feel. The music isn't overly complex,
				yet contains enough variety and changes frequently enough to avoid any monotony if you enjoy this
				kind of doom metal. Simultaneously funereal and catchy enough, the music contains a strong emotional
				charge as well as a pleasant kind of unpretentious quality. Forest of Shadows manage to successfully
				gather influences from several of the European doom metal giants and use them without coming across
				as very derivative, especially for a debuting band. An impressive debut by these northern doomsters,
				and a smart signing by Rage of Achilles.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item zine="aversionline.com" date="020117" rating="70%">
			<p>
				Three monstrously lengthy tracks of punishing, depressing doom from this two-man act out of Sweden.
				With likely influences obvious (My Dying Bride, early Paradise Lost, early Anathema, perhaps some
				early Katatonia), this is still strong material that doesn't have a completely unoriginal sound. The
				only thing I find distracting at times are the singing vocals, though when leaning more towards
				singing than speaking and held low in the mix they can be very nice. The aggressive vocals, on the
				other hand, are wonderful, resting off in the distance beneath a light sheen of reverb that makes
				them that much more interesting. The songwriting achieves an excellent balance between moving
				melodies and pounding heaviness, as well as spacious clean breaks and fluid changes. Synths are used
				incredibly tastefully, light lead lines accentuate devastating, heavy rhythms, the occasional
				acoustic break or use of upright bass adds further dimension to their sound, etc.
			</p>
			<p>
				From a recording standpoint this is pretty damn good considering two people take care of all of the
				vocals and instrumentation involved (including live drums and keyboards). The heavier portions are
				slightly muddy, without a whole lot of distinction between guitar and bass, but the raw density
				works well with the cold, distant vocals, so that doesn't bother me. During the calmer moments things
				become a bit brighter and retain more clarity, further offsetting the changes, but not to the point
				where it becomes problematic. it may even be a strength.
			</p>
			<p>
				Of course the fragmented lyrical content is full of utter despair and hopelessness, "How I wish in
				the midst of falling snow in a garden of endless grief my forlorn soul of misery where peace and rest
				can never dwell hope never comes I see no point in going on." A bit wordy and overdone, but anything
				less would be inappropriate for such musical ventures. The layout is very basic, mostly black with a
				simple band logo and some basic autumnal textures used very sparsely. Overall this is an astoundingly
				promising debut, and one of the most professional pieces of work I've ever heard from a project
				consisting of only two members. Definitely recommended.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Kristoffer R" zine="Vincentius webzine" date="020103" rating="95%">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows härstammar från Västergötland. De startade som ett solo-projekt av Niclas Frohagen
				(Ningizzia, Shubend) men har senare utvecklats till ett fyra-manna band. De har nyligen fått kontrakt
				med engelska bolaget Rage of Achilles. Stilen varierar mycket från slö döds med aktustiska delar till
				väldigt mörk, melankolisk metal. Brutala avgrundsvrål varvas med vanlig sång(inge jävla falsett
				sång).
			</p>
			<p>
				Eftersom att det är MCD så innehåller den bara tre stycken låtar, men ändock en speltid av 29:14 min.
				Skivan första spår, "Eternal Autumn", inleds med ett oerhört vackert flöjtstycke spelat av Anna
				Ekblad, för att senare gå över till tunga gitarriff o avgrundsvrål. Det andra spåret, "Wish", har
				ingen direkt inledning utan börjar med tunga gitarriff o Niclas fruktansvärt bra dödsång. Även det
				sista spåret, "Of Sorrow Blue", börjar utan inledning men här sjunger han med vanlig sång till en
				början, för att sedan börja med dödsången. Låten avslutas med ett akustiskt stycke som är välidgt
				sorgset o vackert.
			</p>
			<p>
				Den här mcd:n är bland det bästa jag hört. Skivan har en sån jävla känsla o stämning. De har planerat
				att släppa en fullängdare någongång under 2002, och jag ser fram emot den som fan!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Stephen H" zine="Sonic Death webzine" date="020103">
			<p>
				Opening with the gentle sound of a flute being played, this 3 track mini album has more than just a
				passing resemblance to My Dying Bride. The flute soon flows effortlessly into a somber guitar led
				piece with growled vocals, before Forest of Shadows go all Katatonia on us with carefully picked
				guitars and nicely sung vocals, and then resorting back to the doomy vision they had created at the
				beginning. 
			</p>
			<p>
				This then lays down the format for the rest of the mini album, a mixture a growled and clean vocals
				with the band forging an epic sounding doom framework, heartfelt feeling permeating every minute and
				although the sound they produce isn't dissimilar to the bands I've mentioned, there's a distinct
				freshness to the whole proceedings. It's slightly unfair however to base the sound of Forest Of
				Shadows on those bands but the sound they produce isn't too far away from them and it's the closest
				comparison.
			</p>
			<p>
				Guitars weave along a meandering pathway whilst the vocalist growls away in the background, and on
				more than one occasion, flashes of genius show themselves in the song structures. Bringing to mind
				the feeling of epic that this style of doom can often deliver, Forest of Shadows are clearly a band
				who know a good tune when they hear it. Mid paced track 'Wish' has all the ingredients of this,
				often slow but never boring, the guitar weaves in and out of a mixture of growled and cleanly sung
				vocal lines, producing a track which immediately demands your attention. Final track, 'Of Sorrow
				Blue', takes that remit even further with a faster (but still only mid paced) doom epic which has
				some inspired passages of surging guitars and beautifully growled vocals, interspersed with slower
				moments with more of a chugging riff, flutes (or possibly violins) and acoustic guitars appear later
				which only reinforce the overall vast sound of the track. The appearance of double bass towards the
				end combined with the growled vocals just reminds the listener that the band have all their bases
				covered and as the orchestral feel makes another not unwelcome appearance, I'm already ready to press
				the replay button. Unfortunately it's all over too quickly, a mere 30 minutes but this only wets the
				appetite for the upcoming full length.
			</p>
			<p>
				If My Dying Bride, Katatonia or even earlier Paradise Lost floats your boat then this EP will be a
				most welcome addition to the collection.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Marcus Grahn" zine="Close-Up #49" date="020103">
			<p>
				När MY DYING BRIDE-färgade FOREST OF SHADOWS knåpar ihop finurliga melodier - som i inledande
				"Eternal Autumn" - är de riktigt bra. När göteborgarna istället gör det lätt för sig och på tomgång
				harvar segdragna doomklyschor låter det därefter.
			</p>
			<p>
				Debuten består endast av tre skapelser, men är sammanlagt nästan en halvtimme lång. Vokalisten är
				katastrofalt kass när han försöker sjunga rent, batteristen behöver variera sig och det är
				synnerligen lätt att hamna i tankebanor som berör annat än musiken när "Wish" och "Of Sorrow Blue"
				brummar ur högtalarna.
			</p>
			<p>
				FOREST OF SHADOWS är (än så länge) ett dussinband med lätträknade höjdpunkter.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Gary Reeves" zine="Metal Hammer #94" date="011129" rating="80%">
			<p>
				"Disturbing swedish doom metal that promises much"
			</p>
			<p>
				Jesus Christ, where did these guys spring up from?! (erm..Sweden.) This mini cd bridges the gap until
				their full length platter is relesed next year and what a space filler!! Any individuals on the verge
				of suicide should avoid 'Where Dreams...' at all costs while those of sound mind should place their
				advance orders now. The three songs found on this disc are about as epic as serious doom metal can
				be. 'Eternal Autumn' is the death march into oblivion with echoing funeral chords, emotive classical
				segues and a downtuned undertow lurking beneath while 'Wish' rams this desperation and agony home
				further. The final hymn, 'Of Sorrow Blue' is a turbulent and disturbing journey. mercifully laid to
				rest by some mournful acoustics. Let's pray that Forest Of Shadows can maintain this grasp on the
				claustrophobic when they record their debut. If they do, it's time for My Dying Bride to vent
				concern. 
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Catherine Yates" zine="Kerrang" date="011017" rating="40%">
			<p>
				Gothic sweeps of melancholic metal form the latest offering from London label Rage Of Achilles in
				the form of Swedish duo Forest of Shadows. For those black-clad souls who stare sorrowfully to the
				likes of Katatonia and My Dying Bride, this is gloom-or-be-gloomed tinged manna from heaven. However,
				those who were more taken with the bloodcurdling dirge frenzies of labelmates Goatsblood, will be
				heartened by the fact that these epic laments only have a total running time of 30 minutes.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="James Hinchliff" zine="Terrorizer #94" date="011017" rating="80%">
			<p>
				It's very pleasing to see Forest of Shadows finally sign a record contract, since they've been
				producing extremely impressive work in demo form for some time. Indeed, 'Where Dreams Turn To Dust'
				was originally their third demo release, every aspect of it so professional that it's presented here
				with only slightly modified artwork and almost exactly as originally bedroom-recorded, not that
				you'd know it as the sombre and majestic, early Katatonia-esque doom lumbers out of the speakers
				with as much production punch as Unholy or My Dying Bride. Can't wait for the full-lengther due early
				next year.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Jack" zine="Metalbite webzine" date="010711" rating="95%">
			<p>
				"One of the best ever mcd/demo released in the history of metal."
			</p>
			<p>
				When I say mcd/demo, what I mean to say that it was previously demo material that was on mp3.com,
				and now an intelligent label has finally decided to sign these champions of dark metal up, Rage of
				Achilles is the intelligent label, that should hopefully catapult this band into extreme metal
				limelight. And they thoroughly deserve. Forest of Shadows are comprised of two members: Micce
				Andersson (responsible for bass, guitar, programming, synthesizers and violin) and Niclas Frohagen
				(guitar, programming, synthesizers and vocals). Influencing these overly talented musicians are
				outfits such as Katatonia, Opeth, My Dying Bride and Anathema. All fantastic bands in their own
				rights. All radically different. What Forest of Shadows does is take the best elements of each band,
				for example the somber parts of My Dying Bride, the cool solos of Opeth, and the heartfelt lyrics and
				vocals of Katatonia. But don't make the mistake of thinking that Forest of Shadows rip any of these
				bands off. They are completely innovative and unique.
			</p>
			<p>
				Niclas' voice is extremely hard to describe, and I wouldn't really do it justice to try and compare,
				or pigeonhole it with any other extreme act of today. Extremely deep, guttural roars that have a
				nice hollow sound to it. His clean voice is essentially indescribable, its unlike anything I've
				heard in metal today, suffice to say its fresh and compelling. "Where Dreams Turn to Dust" is
				comprised of three songs spanning nearly 30 minutes, that equates to epic songs in the tradition of
				Opeth and My Dying Bride. Never boring or drab each of the three tracks is unique in composition. All
				tracks are equally awesome and as a result there is no real standout track, only standout tracks.
				Bottom Line: Go to www.mp3.com, downloading a few Forest of Shadows, support this band by buying
				their upcoming mcd, and I guarantee they will change your perception of good, innovative metal.
				Forest of Shadows will go very far in future years.
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="where dreams turn to dust | demo 2000">
		<item author="Matthew" zine="Starvox" date="001101">
			<p>
				The lone word that springs to mind after hearing this band is Wow! Hailing from Gothenburg, Sweden,
				Forest of Shadows is a two piece band that deliver an unrivaled cornucopia of epic Doom, Gothic, and
				Power metal, all gathered into one bleak and emotionally devastating package. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Sounding like a head on collision between Opeth, old My Dying Bride and Katatonia, Forest Of Shadows
				take those popular styles and blend them ingeniously to cross over and appeal to fans of multiple
				dark music genres. Obviously their music has touched many as they have been reigning atop the Mp3
				Gothic Metal charts for the past month and a half with their tracks "Under The Dying Sun" and "The
				Silent Cry" with three other tracks close on their tails. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows is a very complex and ambitious band, with multi-faceted songs often nearing or
				exceeding ten minutes in length.  With multiple passages of acoustic guitar serenades, and haunting
				flute, piano, and violin solos, the band exhibit both a penchant for classical inspired doom with
				more upbeat, double-bass driven parts that gallop full-steam ahead into the realm of power metal. 
			</p>
			<p>
				But most importantly, the two musicians have a knack for composing striking melodies, as the twin
				guitars resonate with grief and sorrowful feeling, topped by agonized death metal growls and
				gorgeous clean vocal harmonies, best exemplified in an astounding melodic break in the song "Wish".
				With lush male choir vocals drifting atop a charging metallic backdrop, the band contributes an
				immortal moment in this genre that will be appreciated by many. It's a truly remarkable passage;
				long enough to captivate yet brief enough not to be monotonous. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Another memorable track is "Of Sorrow Blue", which is literally a maze of changes and shifts in
				mood, clocking in at over eleven minutes. A brooding tone is set immediately in the strong opening
				as a sludgy drum/power chord backbone is wed to a sweet, haunting riff. Gothic male vocals appear
				for the early verses as the melody carries to reach a short acoustic break, then to venture off into
				several different darker and heavier moments, where the guttural vocals take center stage. The song
				enfolds the listener within a suffocating mood that reaches its final destintation with a somber
				acoustic outro punctuated by a solo violin. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows are an amazing band with a wealth of talent, and their sound is so vast and
				encompassing in its grandiosity that it will not be hard for fans of dark progressive metal, goth
				metal, or death metal to fall head over heals in love with their music.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Jeremy GoreChrist Whitman" zine="Eternal Frost #1" date="011017">
			<p>
				Near brilliant doom/death with violins, flutes, and tons of melody. Forest of Shadows also mixes,
				with taste I must add, some elements of "goth metal" for extra range. What makes their sound work is
				their dynamic songwriting approach, trading off single instrument sessions to dual harmony segments
				and then exploding with rather emotional riffs. The melodies that flow throughout the disc seem
				molded into perfection, and they give Where Dreams Turn to Dust the long-lasting re-play value that
				most doom/death albums lack. Equally impressive is the fact that all instruments, with the exception
				of the flute, are played by Forest of Shadows' two members Micce Anderson and Niclas Frohagen. The
				only real problem is with the clean vocals, which remain slightly off-key and distinct in spots;
				justifying this flaw, most death metal vocalists who attempt clean vocals are much worse. I
				personally hear a lot of Skepticism-isms, especially in "Wish", and Paradise Lost influence.
				Everything else is refreshingly original, and as if I haven't given Forest of Shadows enough credit,
				these guys definitely have the guts to experiment with major chords in a way that I have never heard
				within these genres. Flowing rhythms, drenched in sad minors, occasionally drift towards an uplifting
				major scale for mere seconds, and then the minors resurge. Beautiful. Buy this, and support these
				guys.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Aldo Q" zine="doom-metal.com" date="010422">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows never ceases to amaze me and with this demo they have grown to new heights. The
				excellently performed melodic death/doom metal they serve us on this demo, clearly shows that they
				should have been signed to a label a long time ago. While this demo finally gained them a record
				deal with the small label Molded Skull Records (who will also release this demo as a Mcd) it is still
				beyond me why this took so long and why it had to be such a small label. After a beautiful sorrow
				filled flute intro, heavier sounds roll in creating a truly melancholic atmosphere. Their solid and
				slow metal is complimented by the occasional use of a violin or acoustic brake. Filling almost 30
				minutes with just 3 songs should give you a clear indication about the length of these songs. Forest
				of Shadows is a school example of the melodic death/doom genre. Of course this means they won't win
				any originality prices, but they pull it off so skilfully that this really doesn't matter. Where most
				bands try to stick out by experimenting, Forest of Shadows stick out by keeping to the often-threaded
				paths. Obvious references would be Katatonia, My Dying Bride and in my opinion also Empyrium
				(especially the occasional clean vocals). You can download the entire album from
				http://www.mp3.com/fos/ so I don't see what could stop you from checking out this demo!
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Jesse H" zine="Digitalmetal webzine" date="001122">
			<p>
				It is extremely rare a band that is so talented and has such a strong cult following goes so long
				without a killer record deal. Infact, I simply cannot believe that the 'major' metal labels haven't
				jumped all over this incredible band. Even if someone wasn't convinced by the music (which is hard to
				believe), Forest of Shadows has completely dominated the mp3.com gothic metal charts for months. They
				have earned nearly $5000 simply by putting their music online. Trust me when I say their popularity
				is due to the quality of their music, not some intensive promotional campaign.
			</p>
			<p>
				That said, I suppose there are still some of you out there who are still oblivious to this band, so
				hopefully this review will change that. "Where Dreams Turn to Dust" is Forest of Shadows' newest and
				strongest contribution to the genre of emotional melodic doom metal. The mCD contains three massive
				tracks which together span nearly 30 minutes of unbelievable depressing doom metal, with influences
				ranging from older Opeth and Katatonia to My Dying Bride. The first track, "Eternal Autumn" begins
				with the somber sound of a flute, which is performed by the band themselves, not a synth. It's not
				long before a wall of guitars collapse upon your unsuspecting ears and you are completely and
				utterly lost within an atmosphere of devastating sadness. Throughout your aural journey you will
				visit skillfully played acoustic passages, most similar to "Morningrise"-era Opeth and excellently
				executed clean and death style vocals -- not to mention brilliantly interwoven violins most similar
				to older My Dying Bride. One thing is clear, this band knows how to write extremely simple songs
				with the maximum emotional impact. Although I would have loved a real drummer on the recording, the
				slow and simple rhythms allow a drum machine to go virtually unnotice. The second song "Wish" is my
				personal favorite of the three, but none of them are weak at any point. There is no doubt in my mind
				that if you are a fan of Opeth, Katatonia, My Dying Bride, or any quality emotional metal band, that
				you will adore this mCD. Forest of Shadows is the real deal folks.
			</p>
			<p>
				Supposedly this mCD will be released on a small label called Molded Skull Records sometime soon, but
				hopefully a label with some money will wake up and realize what is under their noses. My advice to
				everyone is to check out this band as soon as you can. I'm willing to bet in a couple years when this
				band is big "everyone" will be talking about how they were into this band years ago. For now the best
				way to check out Forest of Shadows is through their enormously successful mp3.com page at
				www.mp3.com/fos.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Pedro" zine="Esoterica webzine" date="001122">
			<p>
				Given the quality of songwriting and execution demonstrated by their previous two demos, I'm
				genuinely surprised that Forest of Shadows ever made it to a third demo without being enslaved by a
				nefarious record label. Well, this demo has to be their last. From the moment the opener "Eternal
				Autumn"'s first riff emerges from the speakers, after the gentle flute intro, it is totally obvious
				that the band have reached a level of musical skill and professionalism which not only matches that
				of their contemporaries, but in the cases of many of those peers exceeds it entirely; if the process
				which led to bands being plucked from their bedrooms and given a half-decent position in the metal
				hierarchy were not so apparently random, Forest of Shadows would have been entertaining many more
				people for some time.
			</p>
			<p>
				Now, to be honest, I'm not saying that Where Dreams Turn Into Dust is perfect; there is still a
				Katatonia influence nudging the band's own personality slightly aside, and even within their field,
				Forest of Shadows have absolutely no chance of winning any awards for originality. Melodic doom/death
				metal has been done to, ahem, death by a long line of bands stretching back over a decade, and
				there's not much left for the genre to do in terms of revitalising itself; on reflection, though,
				Forest of Shadows make this work in their favour, because they are forced to rely on their aptitude
				for creating good music in their chosen pigeon-hole, rather than relying on any forced or spurious
				meanderings in the name of "experimentation". Consequently, since their soundworld is virtually pre-
				defined, the band have concentrated on perfecting the formula, and as such their output has all the
				ingredients one might expect, such as mournful clean singing supporting the throat-shredding roars,
				minimal but musically relevant and non-trivially orchestrated keyboards, acoustic interludes, violins
				etc. etc., all produced as well as any other player in this particular sub-genre. Without a doubt,
				Forest of Shadows are among the masters of their chosen field. Someone needs to discover them
				quickly.	
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="promotion-cd 2000 | demo 2000">
		<item author="Nikki Sixx" zine="Metal Storm" date="050723" rating="9/10">
			<p>
				Forest Of Shadows, this is where you lose yourself at times of deep sorrow and everlasting solitude
				while listening to their music, in a misty and dark forest of shadows letting the forlorn shades
				speak of tales of bleakness. "Under the Dying Sun" is their second demo released during 2000 and it
				consists only of one composition, the 15-minute ode to melancholy "Under the Dying Sun." Katatonia
				and My Dying Bride influences can be heard here and there, but being well-hidden since Forest Of
				Shadows are only influenced and do not copy, playing music from the artist's heart straight to the
				listener's.
			</p>
			<p>
				I could write down as a review only the lyrics of "Under the Dying Sun" that are pure poetry to my
				eyes, bleeding words, grieving tears from the eyes of Ligeia falling in the doleful darkness; they
				represent the sound of the band in a way that no man could do better. When the time comes to write
				down my thoughts concerning this band they flee from my mind, I cannot speak, I cannot recall what I
				was thinking simply because this band is so special to me dragging my soul out of my body drowning me
				into a forest of shadows.
			</p>
			<p>
				."Under the Dying Sun" seeing its scarlet rays fading in the darkening horizon. The mournful guitar
				riffing along with the floating doleful ethereal keyboard melodies that lurk behind the guitar sound
				open the gates of bereavement and Niclas' almost-crying desperate grunts enter to complete the bleak
				soundscape. The mournful slow guitar riffing dances in a heart-rending way with the melancholic
				guitar chords as withered rose-leafs start falling around you welcoming the grieving violin melodies
				when you realize that there's no escape from this bitter nightmare where pain and sorrow seem like
				joyful memories in front of the burden you have to bear. Niclas' grunts, desperate screams,
				melancholic chants and whispers are utterly descriptive as if he was an actor in the most tear-filled
				drama living every single word he utters from his bitter lips, words of the heart scarring deep your
				fragile soul becoming one with the melodies. The bleakness that the lyrics unfold harmonize in
				painful ways with the bleeding musical background, lyrics that speak of your beloved one embracing
				eternal sleep, fading "in fields of green, under the dying sun," "breathing her final breath," "in
				the fields of green you see her die," "you cry out in grief, for your beloved one," "you see her
				die."
			</p>
			<p>
				"Under the Dying Sun" will drown you in 15 minutes of utterly emotional melodic doom/death metal that
				will last for all eternity; don't miss it.
			</p>
		</item>
		<item author="Pedro" zine="Esoterica webzine" date="00????">
			<p>
				This is their newer promotional CD, weighing in at a heftier fifteen minutes, yet only featuring one
				song. That snippet of information alone would have many people screaming and trying to hide, but if
				you're anything like me, you'll think that long songs are great. "Under the Dying Sun" is generally
				noticably superior to the "The Silent Cry", with greater depth to the songwriting, and some proper
				metal sections, with grinding, sludgy guitar riffs.
			</p>
			<p>
				There's a very occasional descent into twee melodies in the keyboard parts, which is slightly
				niggling, but ephemeral enough to not detract too much from the otherwise omnipresent melancholy.
				All too often, when essaying long songs, bands fall into the trap of joining several short songs
				together, with stilted and artificial results, but Forest of Shadows pleasantly seem to have
				composed "Under the Dying Sun" in a more holistic fashion. This apparent consideration of the
				listener creates a musical experience which is kept interesting, yet also slow and dirge-like, and
				wins my approval.
			</p>
			<p>
				Again, the sound quality is very high indeed, as befits the genre, and on the strength of this, I
				have to assume strong label interest is just around the corner. Now, if they can just do something
				about that dodgy band name, this lot could well be onto something...
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="promotion-cd 1999 | demo 1999">
		<item author="Pedro" zine="Esoterica webzine" date="00????">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows come from Gothenburg, and so, as you might expect, they play..... doom?!? Yes,
				ignoring the hordes of widdly metal bands, this lot spew forth some pretty heavy doom metal. A quick
				check of my Children's Colour Atlas (1987 edition, which still has East Germany on it) confirmed
				that Göteborg is pretty much halfway between Yorkshire and Finland - a description which applies
				equally well to their music. The Silent Cry is their promo CD from last year, containing two songs,
				the original title track and a Katatonia cover. The original song is very nice indeed; violins meld
				with crushingly heavy guitars and transport the listener across time and space to Yorkshire in about
				1991, yet the Finnish school of doom exemplified by the likes of Unholy (slow, with a crushing bassy
				sound) is also called to mind. It's startling just how well Forest of Shadows have captured the vibe
				of that particular period of metal history (the heyday of the likes of Paradise Lost and My Dying
				Bride), yet also managed to sound contemporary. Subtle and not overused keyboards embroider the
				music without distracting, adding kitsch or lightening the mood, and the rest of the band produce a
				well-executed blend of melody and aggressiveness which doesn't descend into noodling. Topped with a
				deep-voiced and gruff growling singer, the band create a dark and gloomy atmosphere in a traditional
				style. The cover is "Rainroom" from Brave Murder Day, and is pretty straight, and so reasonably
				superfluous, although credit is due for the convincing Åkerfeldt impression, and it does serve to
				highlight another reference point for the band's own work. No expense has been spared on the studio,
				either, as both songs have top-notch sound quality, and as I have this on CD-R, comes across sounding
				better than half the albums I have by signed bands. Overall, this is a fine production, and fans of
				sonically detailed doom metal should keep an eye out for this lot.
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
	<album name="the silent cry | demo 1998">
		<item author="Aldo Q" zine="Dark desire webzine" date="99????" rating="50%">
			<p>
				Forest of Shadows is a doom-metal band who are heavily inspired by early work of My Dying Bride,
				Katatonia and Anathema. On this demo (pressed on CD), the band still exists out of one person,
				Niclas (also a member of Ningizzia). He does all instruments and vocals himself. A pity is that the
				production is not too good. The band has grown after the release of this demo, (including the use of
				violins) but you can't hear that on this demo yet. The music is slow and heavy, just like death-doom
				should be. Most noticeable are the grunts; they are very low, almost whispered grunts. This
				apparently because else the neighbours complained about the noise. While not overly creative, this
				demo did impress me and I do think this band, certainly with the addition the extra band member now,
				can go a long way (I'll admit I cheated as I have already heard a new song by them and it sounds very
				good!).
			</p>
		</item>
	</album>
</reviews>
